<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Book Review on Perl.com - programming news, code and culture</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/book-review/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Book Review on Perl.com - programming news, code and culture</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 21 Dec 2015 00:02:25 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/tags/book-review/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Modern Perl 4th edition, a review</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/article/205/2015/12/21/Modern-Perl-4th-edition--a-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Dec 2015 00:02:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/article/205/2015/12/21/Modern-Perl-4th-edition--a-review/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The 4th edition of &lt;a href=&#34;https://pragprog.com/book/swperl/modern-perl-fourth-edition&#34;&gt;Modern Perl&lt;/a&gt; by chromatic is out. I was given an advance copy to review and the book features my praise quote, so I figured it was about time I wrote my notes up into a longer review. Overall I really like the changes to the new edition; in my opinion, Modern Perl continues to provide a valuable introduction to idiomatic Perl programming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;learn-the-idiomatic-perl-style&#34;&gt;Learn the idiomatic Perl style&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modern Perl isn&amp;rsquo;t like your typical dry programming book. For one thing, it&amp;rsquo;s opinionated. Author chromatic draws on his experience to provide an insiders&amp;rsquo; guide that shows the &lt;em&gt;right&lt;/em&gt; way to program in Perl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The text is fast-moving and doesn&amp;rsquo;t baby the reader. Instead of &amp;ldquo;hello World&amp;rdquo;, the book begins by teaching the reader how to use &lt;code&gt;perldoc&lt;/code&gt; and draw upon the official documentation when they get stuck. Don&amp;rsquo;t waste time with Google when the answer &lt;a href=&#34;http://perltricks.com/article/155/2015/2/26/Hello-perldoc--productivity-booster&#34;&gt;can be found in seconds&lt;/a&gt; at the command line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chapters 1 and 2 introduce the Perl philosophy and Community. The book rapidly covers the major features of Perl (chapters 3 - 7) and even more advanced topics like recursion, anonymous functions and closures. Peppered throughout are gems of wisdom explaining the rationale behind a given concept. For instance, on including parentheses on all function calls (even ones without arguments):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While these parentheses are not strictly necessary for these examples—even with strict enabled—they provide clarity to human readers as well as Perl’s parser. When in doubt, use them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modern Perl 4th edition, Chapter 5, Declaring Functions&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The focus here, though is on the practical and chromatic quickly moves on to advising on elements of good Perl style and how to learn it (chapter 8) and real-World programming tips (chapter 9). This is an honest, expert&amp;rsquo;s account of Perl, and chapter 11 describes what to avoid in Perl (chapter 5 also has an entry on function misfeatures).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst this is an introductory text, chromatic does find time to touch upon several intermediate concepts like taint, schwartzian transforms and tail call optimizations. There is something for everybody: re-reading the &lt;a href=&#34;http://modernperlbooks.com/books/modern_perl_2014/05-perl-functions.html#U3RhdGV2ZXJzdXNDbG9zdXJlcw&#34;&gt;section&lt;/a&gt; State-versus-Closures (chapter 5) I learned a nuance that I hadn&amp;rsquo;t appreciated before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modern Perl does assume a lot and this could make it challenging for complete novices. For example the code snippets assume the reader can distinguish between command line and Perl programming context. Map and grep are used in examples but are not covered in the language overview chapters. But these are minor nits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;modern-perl&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Modern&amp;rdquo; Perl?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About 10 years ago, Perl enjoyed something of a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.modernperlbooks.com/mt/2009/07/milestones-in-the-perl-renaissance.html&#34;&gt;renaissance&lt;/a&gt; called &amp;ldquo;Modern Perl&amp;rdquo;. This was a movement that developed powerful new libraries, tools and applications which invigorated Perl programming and gave it a new lease-of-life. Today the phrase is almost synonymous with Perl &amp;ldquo;best practices&amp;rdquo; and its ethos continues to help Perl flourish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-s-changed&#34;&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s changed&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 4th edition brings a lot of changes, but it&amp;rsquo;s a case of evolution, not revolution. New Perl features like the double-diamond operator (&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;) and &lt;a href=&#34;http://perltricks.com/article/72/2014/2/24/Perl-levels-up-with-native-subroutine-signatures&#34;&gt;subroutine signatures&lt;/a&gt; are covered. Almost every paragraph has been &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/chromatic/modern_perl_book/commits/master&#34;&gt;updated&lt;/a&gt;), but the chapter structure remains the same and many of the edits are tweaks rather than wholesale re-writes. Many of the changes improve the readability of the text, others de-jargonize it, like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Functions are a prime mechanism for abstraction, encapsulation, and re-use in Perl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modern Perl, 3rd Edition, Chapter 5&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;became:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Functions are a prime mechanism for organizing code into similar groups, identifying individual pieces by name, and providing reusable units of behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modern Perl, 3rd Edition, Chapter 5&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which is clearly easier for beginners to understand. Code-wise, many of the examples have changed from a BSD to K&amp;amp;R style, presumably to save vertical space. Overall the book length remains about the same (205 vs 204 pages).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest change with the new edition comes from The Pragmatic Bookshelf - their version is simply &lt;em&gt;gorgeous&lt;/em&gt;. Full color with larger fonts, icons and callouts, the book really pops. This is the layout Modern Perl needs &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; deserves. See this comparison between the Onyx Neon and Pragmatic Bookshelf versions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/205/comparison.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;alternatives&#34;&gt;Alternatives&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an opinionated introduction to Perl, Modern Perl is a compromise between a tutorial and a best-practices style cookbook. I love the direction and terse writing style, but the book might move too fast for complete beginners. So it depends on what you&amp;rsquo;re looking for - &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Beginning-Perl-Curtis-Poe/dp/1118013840&#34;&gt;Beginning Perl&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Learning-Perl-Randal-L-Schwartz/dp/1449303587&#34;&gt;Learning Perl&lt;/a&gt; are fine introductions to the language. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Effective-Perl-Programming-Idiomatic-Development/dp/0321496949&#34;&gt;Effective Perl Programming&lt;/a&gt; is my favorite Perl cookbook. But Modern Perl is a unique blend of both styles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;where-to-get-it&#34;&gt;Where to get it&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can read Modern Perl &lt;a href=&#34;http://modernperlbooks.com/books/modern_perl_2014/index.html&#34;&gt;online&lt;/a&gt; for free, and there are downloadable versions available from &lt;a href=&#34;http://onyxneon.com/books/modern_perl/index.html&#34;&gt;Onyx Neon&lt;/a&gt;. If you want it as an ebook, I would recommend the Pragmatic Bookshelf &lt;a href=&#34;https://pragprog.com/book/swperl/modern-perl-fourth-edition&#34;&gt;version&lt;/a&gt; - it&amp;rsquo;s beautifully styled, free, and you&amp;rsquo;ll be eligible for updates to the text as/when they appear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;This article was originally posted on &lt;a href=&#34;http://perltricks.com&#34;&gt;PerlTricks.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book review: Mastering Perl 2nd edition</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/article/67/2014/2/10/Book-review--Mastering-Perl-2nd-edition/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2014 05:24:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/article/67/2014/2/10/Book-review--Mastering-Perl-2nd-edition/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The second edition of Mastering Perl by brian d foy has just been published by O&amp;rsquo;Reilly. We took a look at the new version to see what&amp;rsquo;s changed and to find out what it really means to become a Perl master.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-road-to-mastery&#34;&gt;The road to mastery&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perl is a deceptively deep language: a novice can be productive in Perl within minutes, yet it takes years of practice to understand all of Perl&amp;rsquo;s features and shortcomings. brian d foy knows this, and he prefaces Mastering Perl with the explanation that the journey to mastery will involve self-study and experimentation, and working with and learning from many different Perl programmers. What follows in the book is a tour-de-force of advanced Perl programming subjects intended to set the reader on the road to mastery and equip them with the knowledge they need to advance their own skills further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-s-in-mastering-perl&#34;&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s in Mastering Perl&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mastering Perl covers a lot of ground and you can find a complete listing of chapters &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.masteringperl.org/new-in-2e/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. In every chapter I learned something useful, amazing or just plain cool about Perl. There were too many to mention them all, but a few highlights for me were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The advanced regular expressions coverage, which culminates in writing a regex grammar (chapter 1)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In-depth coverage of taint, including how to circumvent it (chapter 2)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Writing your own Perl debugger (chapter 3)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fixing other people&amp;rsquo;s subroutines by wrapping them (chapter 9)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Writing/reading external data with Sereal (chapter 13)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Extending the modulino concept to work for testing (chapter 17)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mastering Perl is also a pleasure to read: brian d foy&amp;rsquo;s writing style is light hearted but professional, opinionated but reasoned. There is a good balance between code and words: concepts are introduced and explained without verbose prose and often the code examples do the talking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every chapter is self-contained: you won&amp;rsquo;t find yourself thumbing back through previous chapters to understand concepts discussed later in the book. And because of it&amp;rsquo;s modular structure, you can dive into the topics that interest you most and return to the remainder later on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;content-changes&#34;&gt;Content changes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The content of the new edition has been refreshed and beefed-up; it&amp;rsquo;s about 50 pages longer than the first time around. Every chapter has been updated and several have been extensively revised. A complete list of changes is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.masteringperl.org/new-in-2e/&#34;&gt;available&lt;/a&gt; however the chapters with the most changes are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Advanced Regular Expressions chapter now covers recursion, grammars and other advanced regex features, culminating in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.perlmonks.org/?node_id=995856&#34;&gt;Randal Scwartz&amp;rsquo; JSON parser&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Secure Programming Techniques has new sections on symbolic references and preventing SQL injection with DBI. The &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Safe&#34;&gt;Safe&lt;/a&gt; module is also covered.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Detecting and Reporting Errors chapter updates the Fatal content with &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/autodie&#34;&gt;autodie&lt;/a&gt;, and introduces &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/TryCatch&#34;&gt;TryCatch&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The data formats of the Data Persistence chapter have been reorganized into Perl specific data storage and Perl agnostic data storage. New material has been added on JSON, Storable&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.masteringperl.org/2012/12/the-storable-security-problem/&#34;&gt;security issue&lt;/a&gt;, and Booking.com&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Sereal&#34;&gt;Sereal&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;style-changes&#34;&gt;Style changes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/67/mastering_perl_first_second_cover.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The covers for the first and second editions are shown above. Style-wise O&amp;rsquo;Reilly has given Mastering Perl a spring clean. The cover title lettering has changed from Garamond to URW Typewriter, and the family of vicuñas has undergone a North Korean-style airbrushing, with the (presumably) troublesome second fawn removed entirely. I like the new cover, it feels cleaner and more modern but stays faithful to the Perl tradition with the blue background and camel-related animal on the cover. Beyond the cover, the book&amp;rsquo;s pages have not changed in style at all, with the same fonts and spacing used throughout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mastering Perl is enjoyable, informative and a worthy successor to Intermediate Perl. It equips the reader with a whole host of advanced tools and approaches for doing more with Perl now, whilst opening the doorway towards true language mastery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second edition of Mastering Perl is available to buy now from &lt;a href=&#34;http://shop.oreilly.com/product/0636920012702.do?intcmp=il-prog-books-videos-cat-intsrch_perl_ct&#34;&gt;O&amp;rsquo;Reilly&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/144939311X/ref=as_li_qf_sp_asin_il_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=9325&amp;amp;creativeASIN=144939311X&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;tag=perltrickscom-20&#34;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; (affiliate link).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enjoyed this article? Help us out and &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?original_referer=http%3A%2F%2Fperltricks.com%2Farticle%2F67%2F2014%2F2%2F10%2FBook-review-Mastering-Perl-2nd-edition&amp;amp;text=Book%20review%3A%20Mastering%20Perl%202nd%20edition&amp;amp;tw_p=tweetbutton&amp;amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fperltricks.com%2Farticle%2F67%2F2014%2F2%2F10%2FBook-review-Mastering-Perl-2nd-edition&amp;amp;via=perltricks&#34;&gt;retweet&lt;/a&gt; it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;This article was originally posted on &lt;a href=&#34;http://perltricks.com&#34;&gt;PerlTricks.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>

