<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Xps on Perl.com - programming news, code and culture</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/xps/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Xps on Perl.com - programming news, code and culture</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2017 09:43:53 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/tags/xps/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Laptop review: Dell XPS 13 2-in-1 (9365)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/article/laptop-review--dell-xps-13-2-in-1--9365-/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2017 09:43:53 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/article/laptop-review--dell-xps-13-2-in-1--9365-/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve got a new computer! It&amp;rsquo;s the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dell.com/en-us/shop/productdetails/xps-13-9365-2-in-1-laptop&#34;&gt;Dell XPS 13 2-in-1&lt;/a&gt; which was announced a couple of weeks ago at &lt;a href=&#34;http://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2017/01/dell-embraces-the-two-in-one-trend-with-new-xps-13-convertible/&#34;&gt;CES 2017&lt;/a&gt;. My model has an i7 processor and 8GB RAM, and I&amp;rsquo;m running Fedora 25. I was a big fan my last &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/article/187/2015/8/18/Laptop-review--Dell-XPS-13-2015/&#34;&gt;XPS 13&lt;/a&gt;, and was excited to see what&amp;rsquo;s changed with this version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;physicals&#34;&gt;Physicals&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Size-wise the laptop is approximately 11.8 x 7.9 x 0.5 inches making it slightly thinner than the older model. The laptop weighs 2.7 pounds, which is the same as before, although with the touchscreen, more weight is distributed onto the upper half of the machine than previously. If you&amp;rsquo;re like me and like coding in many different seating positions, (desk, sofa, beanbag) it can sometimes feel a bit top heavy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The machine has the same luxurious carbon composite interior which makes for a comfortable palm rest, I still prefer it to cold aluminum. The keyboard keys are slightly wider than before, making them easier to hit. And Dell have added dedicated Home, End, Page Up and Page Down keys too. These I like less, mostly because my hands are wired to use the Function key to access those, and in un-learning that behavior, I&amp;rsquo;ve been hitting a lot of wrong keys. Also the secondary function of the Home key is to switch into airplane mode, so a few times I&amp;rsquo;ve managed to lose my VPN and SSH connection by accidentally pressing Function + Home. I think I can disable that airplane mode function in the BIOS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The touchpad is unchanged (still excellent). The laptop camera has moved to bottom-center screen,  and whilst that&amp;rsquo;s not great, because it&amp;rsquo;s a 2 in 1, you can flip the machine into tent mode, and the camera is on the top. Dell switched out the SD card reader for a micro SD instead. The best thing about this is the micro SD only protrudes by a fraction, whereas the full size SD card used to stick out a lot - which means; convenient extended storage (yay!). Now I&amp;rsquo;ve got an extra 128GB available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dell kept the stupid battery charge indicator button. Every review talks about the USB-C ports - there are 2 of them, they work fine. One nice feature is you can charge the machine from either USB port; so if there&amp;rsquo;s not a lot of room on the left side, you can use the one on the right. Dell includes a dongle to convert older USB devices to use the USB-C port too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last time around, the laptop used to be difficult to open as the hinges were so stiff, it was hard to prise the top and bottom apart. With the 2-in-1 the hinges are not so stiff, but it&amp;rsquo;s still difficult to open the machine as there&amp;rsquo;s barely anything to lever your fingers against. The touchscreen and hinges do work well though, and I sometimes use the different configurations when watching movies or reading. Reading mode is a little weird: the 16:9 aspect ratio makes for a long, skinny reading viewport leaving the bottom 20% of the screen empty for a typical PDF.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dell has moved the power button to the side of the machine, which is good otherwise I would be pressing it inadvertently whenever I picked the laptop up. This has the side-benefit of reducing the amount of LED illumination which I complained about in my &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/article/187/2015/8/18/Laptop-review--Dell-XPS-13-2015/&#34;&gt;review&lt;/a&gt; of the older machine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I do not like as much is the screen. It&amp;rsquo;s glossy and reflects too much light, so I&amp;rsquo;ve had to switch to light terminal color schemes. The screen still has a great brightness range though - I tend to use it on low brightness most of the time, but it&amp;rsquo;s handy to have it when you&amp;rsquo;re watching a video, or showing something to friends. The glass screen is better integrated into the bezel too - my 2015 XPS (non touch) had a quarter-inch plastic bezel which used to stick out from the glass a little bit. All kinds of detritus got clogged in between the bezel and the screen. On this model the bezel is black glass, and part of the screen. The only plastic is a thin border around the edges of the bezel, which forms the outer shell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;power-and-performance&#34;&gt;Power and performance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll say it now - this machine is not lightning-fast. Startup definitely takes longer than before, maybe 10-20 seconds longer. Despite that, I find the machine plenty-fast for my needs, I don&amp;rsquo;t see a lot of delays in performing operations or anything like that. Intel&amp;rsquo;s firmware for scaling the CPU power on demand seems to work well. Whilst my OCD-side loves the fanless architecture, I will say that I can hear the machine &amp;ldquo;processing&amp;rdquo; when under load (kind of like that clicking sound desktop PCs make). I&amp;rsquo;ve not had an issue with the machine getting too hot, it generally runs very cool. I&amp;rsquo;ve also seen kernel messages where a controller reduces the capacity of the CPU when the machine is getting hot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my experience, the battery life appears to be significantly better than the older model (although I&amp;rsquo;m running Linux). I can get around 10 hours use before needing a charge. Longer battery life is important to me - I purposely avoided the higher resolution screen and 16GB RAM upgrades to save power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;miscellaneous&#34;&gt;Miscellaneous&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time around the machine came with an Intel WiFi card, so I didn&amp;rsquo;t have to buy one, which was nice. More disconcerting was the touchpad was &lt;strong&gt;loose&lt;/strong&gt; and rattled a bit. Apparently this is a general XPS 13 issue, and I found a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=q1Z9adYLkyw&#34;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt; which showed how to fix it. The fix mostly worked but it was very disappointing to unbox a high-end laptop and find it rattling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Dell pre-sales team deserve a special mention: the Dell website advertised a 512GB SSD upgrade option for the laptop&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;, but it was not available to purchase as an option when you went to the product customization screen. Pre-sales told me different things: the laptop &amp;ldquo;couldn&amp;rsquo;t handle&amp;rdquo; 512GB, they had &amp;ldquo;sold out&amp;rdquo; of that option (I bought the laptop on the day it launched) and that they advertised that option only so that I could install the hard drive myself at a future date. On the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dell.com/en-us/shop/productdetails/xps-13-9365-2-in-1-laptop/&#34;&gt;product page&lt;/a&gt;, Dell advertises the &amp;ldquo;Dell Hybrid Adapter + Power Bank&amp;rdquo; accessory which looks really cool - it&amp;rsquo;s a charger and battery pack in one. But like with the hard drive upgrade, the accessory was not available to purchase on the customization screen. I emailed pre-sales support to ask when it would be available to buy, 2 days later they responded: &amp;ldquo;Please phone Dell pre-sales &amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;.&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As before, Dell provides a full &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dell.com/support/manuals/us/en/19/xps-13-9365-2-in-1-laptop/XPS_9365_ServiceManual?guid=&amp;amp;lang=&#34;&gt;service manual&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dell.com/support/article/us/en/04/SLN304642&#34;&gt;product page&lt;/a&gt; where you can download driver and firmware updates, view technical specifications and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;linux-compatibility&#34;&gt;Linux-compatibility&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Warning:&lt;/strong&gt; I&amp;rsquo;ve heard a report that the XPS 13 2-in-1 BIOS M2.NVME configuration doesn&amp;rsquo;t support AHCI SATA mode. This means the 512GB SSD drive will not work with Linux until either Dell update the BIOS (apparently the 9360 model supports it already) or Linux gains support for NVME RAID. My advice is to go with the 128GB or 256GB drive for now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the 2015 XPS 13 was first released, Linux support was terrible - it was a new Intel architecture and the kernel just hadn&amp;rsquo;t caught up yet. This time the experience was much better: running the 4.9 kernel and Fedora 25, everything seemed to work - even the touchscreen and automatic screen rotation! I have found a few issues: resume from suspend is &lt;a href=&#34;https://bugzilla.kernel.org/show_bug.cgi?id=192591&#34;&gt;faulty&lt;/a&gt;, rebooting &lt;del&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://bugzilla.kernel.org/show_bug.cgi?id=192651&#34;&gt;shuts down the computer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/del&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;, the camera doesn&amp;rsquo;t &lt;a href=&#34;https://sourceforge.net/p/linux-uvc/mailman/message/35614418/&#34;&gt;work yet&lt;/a&gt; and the fingerprint reader will likely &lt;a href=&#34;https://bugs.freedesktop.org/show_bug.cgi?id=99462&#34;&gt;never work&lt;/a&gt; (that&amp;rsquo;s a feature in my book). Following the kernel development mailing &lt;a href=&#34;http://marc.info/?l=linux-pm&amp;amp;m=148528945028644&amp;amp;w=2&#34;&gt;lists&lt;/a&gt;, it looks like Intel are working on fixes for the power issues that will make it into the next stable kernel release (4.10).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently I&amp;rsquo;m dual booting Windows, and in my brief forays with Windows I can say I&amp;rsquo;ve noticed a few hardware issues there too - in particular the sound card does not seem to function correctly (it makes a static &amp;ldquo;popping&amp;rdquo; sound every minute or so). The natural light sensor continually adjusts the monitor brightness, which gets pretty annoying, and it&amp;rsquo;s not possible to disable it (on Linux it&amp;rsquo;s disabled or doesn&amp;rsquo;t work, I can&amp;rsquo;t tell which).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall I&amp;rsquo;m happy with the laptop. The flexibility provided by the 2-in-1 setup, practical extended storage via the micro SD and increased battery life are big wins. Coupled with some incremental improvements elsewhere, that&amp;rsquo;s good progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; The 512GB SSD upgrade option has been now been removed from the website for the 8GB RAM, 1920x1080 FHD touchscreen model.
&lt;br/&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; That adapter is still not available to purchase on Dell.com, but is available on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Dell-Power-Companion-18000-WCKF2/dp/B01B48YESU&#34;&gt;amazon&lt;/a&gt;. The larger 6-cell model (not compatible with the new XPS) looks &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pcworld.com/article/3099765/laptop-accessories/dell-power-companion-review-charge-your-laptop-on-the-go.html&#34;&gt;great&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;br/&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; Rebooting works with a BIOS &lt;a href=&#34;https://downloads.dell.com/FOLDER04127155M/1/XPS_9365_1_0_5.exe&#34;&gt;update&lt;/a&gt; released from Dell&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;This article was originally posted on &lt;a href=&#34;http://perltricks.com&#34;&gt;PerlTricks.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Laptop review: Dell XPS 13 2015</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/article/187/2015/8/18/Laptop-review--Dell-XPS-13-2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Aug 2015 12:34:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/article/187/2015/8/18/Laptop-review--Dell-XPS-13-2015/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year, Dell released the new XPS 13 to critical &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dell.com/us/p/xps-13-9343-laptop/pd#AnchorZone5&#34;&gt;acclaim&lt;/a&gt;. My review is based on the non-touch screen, i5 model with 8GB RAM running Fedora 21 &amp;amp; 22. I&amp;rsquo;ve been using the machine for the past 6 months and really like it, but there&amp;rsquo;s room for improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;physicals&#34;&gt;Physicals&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all this is the smallest 13&amp;rdquo; HD laptop on the market. Measuring 12&amp;rdquo; wide and 8&amp;rdquo; deep with a thickness of 0.6&amp;rdquo; it is the archetype ultraportable. To get there, Dell used an almost bezel-less, matte 1080p screen from Sharp. I love the screen: it&amp;rsquo;s crisp and precise enough to support multiple tmux panes on the same screen. It supports a wide range of brightness levels (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.anandtech.com/show/8983/dell-xps-13-review/5&#34;&gt;17 to 400 nits&lt;/a&gt;) so I can program on an low setting without hurting my eyes, and then crank up the brightness when watching a movie. And at only 2.6lbs, the XPS 13 weighs less than a MacBook Air.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The XPS 13 has a pleasant, near-full sized keyboard but it&amp;rsquo;s the silicon-coated touch pad that stands out: the smoothness and sensitivity are almost as good as the Mac touch pad, and certainly the best PC touch pad I&amp;rsquo;ve ever used. The laptop shell is made from aluminum and the interior palmrest and keyboard casing is a luxurious carbon composite material that &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.techradar.com/us/reviews/pc-mac/laptops-portable-pcs/laptops-and-netbooks/dell-xps-13-2015-1279013/review&#34;&gt;Tech Radar&lt;/a&gt; described as &amp;ldquo;delightful to touch&amp;rdquo;. After 6 months of heavy use, my XPS 13 shows no signs of wear and tear inside or out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The webcam is positioned in the bottom-left corner of the screen, which is far from ideal. When video conferencing it exacerbates the appearance that I&amp;rsquo;m not looking at the other person (this is a good &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.businessnewsdaily.com/images/i/000/007/961/i02/Photo5.jpg?1422635240&#34;&gt;example&lt;/a&gt; from one &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.businessnewsdaily.com/7729-dell-xps-13-laptop-review-business.html&#34;&gt;review&lt;/a&gt;). Another bum note is the laptop battery button on the left side of the machine. When pressed, a series of LEDs light up indicating the remaining battery charge. I never use it; if I want to know the battery charge I can look at the battery icon on the screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s talk about illumination. The keyboard has decent backlighting, but there are too many other lights. There is one on the power button, another on the tip of the power cable, and a large front-side light comes on when the battery is charging. Although I&amp;rsquo;ve grown used to them, in low-light settings the additional lighting can be a bit distracting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several XPS 13 reviews cited how difficult the laptop was to physically open when closed. I found this initially too, but the stiffness subsided after a couple of weeks and the screen hinge action remains reliably firm. A non-problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One under-appreciated feature are the &lt;a href=&#34;https://d3nevzfk7ii3be.cloudfront.net/igi/SVmnkACIFvh1Kxio.medium&#34;&gt;rubber supports&lt;/a&gt;: they&amp;rsquo;re great at holding the machine steady on low-friction surfaces. I never thought about this before, until on a recent trip my colleague&amp;rsquo;s machine was slipping all over the place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;power-and-performance&#34;&gt;Power and performance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Internally the XPS 13 uses the latest Intel Broadwell architecture and performs decently but not spectacularly in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.techradar.com/us/reviews/pc-mac/laptops-portable-pcs/laptops-and-netbooks/dell-xps-13-2015-1279013/review/2&#34;&gt;benchmarks&lt;/a&gt;. As a programmer I have modest performance needs and have found it powerful enough for casual gaming, audio and video editing. My personal yardstick is that unlike with my 2011 MacBook Air, the fan no longer goes crazy every time I watch a YouTube video. In fact the fan is silent most of the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Fedora I&amp;rsquo;ve found the battery to last for around 7-8 hours per charge, which is respectable but not amazing (Linux power management is not as efficient as Windows/OSX mostly due to &lt;a href=&#34;http://unix.stackexchange.com/questions/119606/why-does-linux-have-poor-battery-life-by-default-compared-to-windows#answer-119620&#34;&gt;proprietary driver issues&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I rarely use them but the external speakers seem just OK. Not particularly high quality nor particularly loud. I haven&amp;rsquo;t used the external microphone much either. The headphone input/output jack works great with my Apple headphones, including the microphone. For external audio/visual, the XPS 13 has a mini-DisplayPort. I&amp;rsquo;ve used it with an HDMI cable for presenting on many different projectors and screens and it works well, even the audio channel works (a first for me on Linux). I&amp;rsquo;ll often stream TV shows or movies through my home TV using it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;miscellaneous&#34;&gt;Miscellaneous&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One welcome change of using a Dell instead of an Apple machine: they provide a complete &lt;a href=&#34;http://downloads.dell.com/Manuals/all-products/esuprt_laptop/esuprt_xps_laptop/xps-13-9343-laptop_Service%20Manual_en-us.pdf&#34;&gt;service manual&lt;/a&gt;, including instructions on how to open the machine, upgrade it and change the battery. Dell peripherals are cheap too: I bought a spare power brick for $20 from Dell on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B00EM2V8AS&#34;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;. Now I don&amp;rsquo;t have to unplug my home one every time I&amp;rsquo;m going on a long journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I first got the machine in March, Linux support for it was mixed: the external speakers and microphone didn&amp;rsquo;t work, the touch pad only worked in PS/2 mode and the Broadcom WiFi needed patching to function. Enough to make one developer &lt;a href=&#34;https://major.io/2015/02/03/linux-support-dell-xps-13-9343-2015-model/&#34;&gt;replace it for a Thinkpad&lt;/a&gt;. There were workarounds: I used headphones, tolerated the mercurial mouse pointer and replaced the Broadcom WiFi card with an Intel one. Since then with version 4 of the kernel, Linux has caught up to the technology and once I installed Fedora 22, these issues went away. If you&amp;rsquo;re using a different Linux distro that is not yet on the version 4 kernel, your experience might be different (you can always compile your own kernel - &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linux.com/learn/tutorials/362602-how-to-compile-the-linux-kernel&#34;&gt;it&amp;rsquo;s easier than you think&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really like the XPS 13. I think Dell got the size right: it&amp;rsquo;s small enough to use it on an economy class flight with the seat in front fully reclined; yet it doesn&amp;rsquo;t feel compromised. The keyboard is a good size and I can lift the machine by its side without pressing the keys (unlike the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.apple.com/macbook/&#34;&gt;MacBook&lt;/a&gt;). Check out the Ars Technica &lt;a href=&#34;http://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2015/02/review-the-dell-xps-13-is-the-pc-laptop-to-beat/&#34;&gt;pictures&lt;/a&gt;; it&amp;rsquo;s gorgeous and performs well. I still can&amp;rsquo;t believe it&amp;rsquo;s a Dell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;This article was originally posted on &lt;a href=&#34;http://perltricks.com&#34;&gt;PerlTricks.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>

