<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<camelids>
  <species name="Camelus bactrianus">
    <common-name>Bactrian Camel</common-name>
    <physical-characteristics>
      <mass>450 to 500 kg.</mass>
      <appearance>
        The most noticeable feature of C. bactrianus is its two humps. At the hump, its average height is 213 cm (7 feet). A
        thick, shaggy, dark brown to beige coat covers the camel during cold weather and is shed when the temperature
        rises. Longer hair hangs from the neck and gives the appearance of a beard. Bushy eyebrows, a double row of eyelashes,
        ears lined with hair and the ability to close nostrils and lips tightly serve as protection from harsh
        conditions. Their tough, even-toed feet help them to cross the rocky desert in Asia and travel well through snow or
        sand.
      </appearance>
    </physical-characteristics>
    <natural-history>
       <food-habits>
         Camels are herbivores. Their preferred plants are dry, prickly, salty, and/or bitter. When other nutrient sources are
         not available, the camel may feed on bones, other animals' skin, or different kinds of flesh. In more extreme
         conditions, they may eat rope, sandals, and even tents. The camel's ability to feed on a wide range of foods allows
         it to live in areas with sparse vegetation. With tough mouths that can withstand sharp objects such as thorns, the digestion process
         begins. The first time food is swallowed it is not fully chewed. The partly masticated food (called cud) goes into
         the stomach and later is brought back up for further chewing. Camels can go for several days without water. When water is 
         available, they drink only to replace what is missing from their body. This amount can vary from nothing to 114
         liters. Drinking the whole 114 liters of water takes only ten minutes. The camel also has the ability to quench its
         thirst with salty or brackish water. In the winter months, plants alone provide water. A common misconception is that
         the camel's humps are for water storage. In reality, the humps contain a large amount of fat and are use for nourishment 
         when food is scarce. This feature gives the camel the capability to go many days without eating. Each hump can hold 
         up to 36 kg of fat. The hump decreases in size and become flabby as its contents are metabolized. Depletion of the 
         hump is directly linked to the time between eating and the amount of energy expended. Thus, the size of the hump
         serves as an indication of C. bactrian's health, food supply and general well-being. The stomach is the camel's
         water storage space. In it, water is retained in several sac-shaped containers. Approximately one and a half gallons
         of water can be held in the stomach.
       </food-habits>
       <reproduction>
         Mating season occurs in the fall, with inbreeding often involved in domesticated camels. The males during this time
         are often violent and may bite, spit, or attempt to sit on other male camels. The age of sexual maturity varies, but
         is usually reached at three to five years. Gestation lasts thirteen months. One or occasionally two calves are
         produced. The female can give birth to a new calf every other year. The baby calf is precocial, having the ability to
         stand at birth and walk only a few hours after. The young calf stays with its mother for three to five years, until
         it reaches sexual maturity. 
       </reproduction>
       <behavior>
         Domestic camels travel in caravans across the desert. An adult male acts as leader for a small group that may consist
         of six to twenty others. Constantspeed must be maintained at all times while moving. To help ensure this tempo the
         camels move by pacing. Pacing consists of two legs on the same sideof the body moving at once, creating a rolling
         motion. This shifts the weight from side to side; a passenger may find this movement very uncomfortable. Camels also
	 have the capability to run and can do so at ten to twenty miles per hour. 
       </behavior>
       <habitat>
         The camel's habitat consists mainly of Asia's deserts. The temperature ranges from -29 degrees Celsius in the winter
         to 38 degrees Celsius in the summer. 
       </habitat>
    </natural-history>
    <conservation status="endangered">
      <detail>
        Camels were thought to be extinct in the wild until an expedition found some wild C. bactrianus in the Gobi desert in
        1957. These wild groups are in the severedanger of going extinct and little is known about them. The estimated number
        of wild camels ranges from 500 to 1000. 
      </detail>
    </conservation>
  </species>
  <species name="Camelus dromedarius">
    <common-name>Dromedary, or Arabian Camel</common-name>
    <physical-characteristics>
      <mass>300 to 690 kg.</mass>
      <appearance>
        The dromedary camel is characterized by a long-curved neck, deep-narrow chest, and a single hump. The hump is composed
        of fat bound together by fibrous tissue, acting as food storage in times of need. The size of the hump varies with the
        nutritional status of the camel, becoming smaller to non-existent during times of starvation. The lips of the
        dromedary camel are thickened to allow consumption of course, thorny plants. Dromedaries are typically caramel brown
        or sandy brown in color, however, shades can range from almost black to nearly white. Hair length is longer on the
        throat, shoulder, and hump areas. The feet of dromedaries are pad-shaped and adapted for traveling on sand. They can
        be easily injured on sharp stones and are unsuitable for slippery or muddy conditions. Male dromedaries, in comparison
        to females, are about 10% heavier, weighing 400-600 kg, and are about 10 cm taller at shoulder height, measuring
        1.8-2.0 m. Additionally, male dromedaries have an inflatable soft palate which is used to attract females. Dromedary
        camels have a total of 34 teeth, with a dental formula of 1/3; 1/1; 3/2; 3/3.
      </appearance>
    </physical-characteristics>
    <natural-history>
       <food-habits>
         The dromedary camel is a herbivore. The camel eats primarily thorny plants, dry grasses and saltbush; however, it
         will eat most anything that grows in  the desert (Oakland Zoo 1993). Dromedaries primarily browse, with shrubs and
         forbs composing up to 70% of their diet. About 8-12 hours/day is  spent grazing with equal amounts spent ruminating
         (Kohler-Rollefson 1991). When foraging, camels tend to spread over large areas and select only a  few leaves from
         each plant. This type of feeding behavior reduces the stress on the plant communities and eases competition with
         other arid region herbivores (Busch Gardens 1996). Additionally, dromedaries need 6 to 8 times as much salt as other
         animals for adsorption and storage of water.  Consequently, 1/3 of their food intake must be halophytes. Dromedaries
         browse up to a height of 3.5 m, breaking off branches or stripping off the  leaves in one movement. While browsing,
         they use their lips to grasp the food, then chew each bite 40-50 times. The mouth is kept open while chewing  thorny
         food (Kohler-Rollefson 1991)
       </food-habits>
       <reproduction>
         The dromedary camel has a lifespan of about 40-50 years (Busch Gardens 1996). Females reach sexual maturity around
         age 3 and mate around age 4  or 5. Males begin to rut by age 3, but do not reach full sexual maturity until age
         6. Typically, males and females are seasonal breeders. Breeding occurs  in winter and overlaps with the rainy
         season; both vary in respect to the camel's geographic range. The onset of the breeding season is believed to be
         cued by nutritional status of the camel and the daylength. During competition for females, the males threaten each
         other by making low noises with the  fleshy fold of their mouths, stand as tall as possible, and repeat a series of
         head movements including lowering, lifting, and bending their necks  backwards. Upon confrontation, fighting males
         attempt to bring their opponent to the ground by biting at his legs and taking the opponent's head in  between his 
         jaws. Copulation time ranges from 7-35 minutes, averaging 11-15 minutes. The gestation period typically lasts for a
         period of 15 months,  followed by the birth of a single calf. The calf can move freely by the end of the first
         day. Maternal care generally lasts for 1 to 2 years. Calves typically  experience a growth rate of .19-.31 kg/day for
         the first year. (Gauthier-Pilthers and Dagg 1981, Kohler-Rollefson 1991) 
       </reproduction>
       <behavior>
         With the exception of rutting males, dromedaries show very little aggressive behavior. Confrontations among
         dromedaries include pushing each other  with their whole body or lowered head and neck; snapping at each other
         without biting; and occasionally vomiting cud when they are hurt or excited.  Dromedaries usually form groups of 2-20
         individuals. The basic social unit is the family, consisting of one male, and one to several females, subadults,  and
         young. The male within the family unit prevents contact between female camels within the family and stray males by
         either standing or walking in between them, or by driving the stray males away. The male is the dominant member of
         the family group and directs the family from the rear while the  females take turns leading. Dromedaries tend to
         travel by walking single file. Dromedary camels find comfort in scratching parts of their body with their  front or
         hind legs, or with their lower incisors. They are also often observed rubbing against trees. Additionally, they seem 
         to like to roll in sand  (Gauthier-Pilthers and Dagg 1981, Kohler-Rollefson 1991). 
       </behavior>
       <habitat>
         The camels prefer desert conditions characterized by a long dry season and a short rainy season. Introduction of the
         dromedary into other climates has proven unsuccessful as the camel is sensitive to the cold and humidity (Nowak
         1991). 
       </habitat>
    </natural-history>
    <conservation status="no special status">
      <detail>
        Since the dromedary camel is domesticated, the camel has no special status in conservation (Busch Gardens 1996). 
      </detail>
    </conservation>
  </species>
  <species name="Lama glama">
    <common-name>Llama</common-name>
    <physical-characteristics>
      <mass>130 to 155 kg.</mass>
      <appearance>
        Llamas feet are slender and their limbs are long. They have long, dense fine wool on their bodies. The hair on their
        head, neck, and limbs is shorter than on their torso. Llamas have remarkable variety in their body sizes and
        shapes. The larger  animals are more prevelant because of their use as "beasts of burden." Body length ranges from
        153-200 cm, shoulder height from 100-125 cm, and tail length from 22-25 cm. The coloring of their fur is also
        variable, ranging from all white,  to brown, yellow, blue and black, and sometimes with checks and spots. 
      </appearance>
    </physical-characteristics>
    <natural-history>
       <food-habits>
         Llamas are herbivorous, feeding on many kinds of grasses and leaves.
       </food-habits>
       <reproduction>
         Llamas reach sexual maturity at about 12-24 months. Females give birth every other year. Mating occurs in  August and
         September. The gestation period is 348-368 days. Llamas produce one offspring at a time  (rarely two). The weight at
         birth is 8-16 kg. Weaning occurs at 5-8 months. 
       </reproduction>
       <behavior>
         The Lama glama lives only in domestication. They are mostly kept grazing freely on grasslands and scrublands at
         elevations between 7,400-12,800 ft.  (2,300-4,000 m). Llamas are very graceful in their movements. They run with a
         swinging stride, with their front and hind legs moving in unison on each  side. Llamas lie down to rest and
         sleep. They are adept at spitting regurgitated food. Llamas use certain excretion sites that form dung heaps up to
         2.4 meters in diameter. Fighting between males involves leg biting and "neck dominance." Copulation occurs while
         animals are in a prone position. 
       </behavior>
       <habitat>
         Llamas are found in deserts, mountainous areas, and grasslands.
       </habitat>
    </natural-history>
    <conservation status="no special status">
      <detail>
        The population of llamas has declined since road building reduced their importance in transportation.
      </detail>
    </conservation>
  </species>
  <species name="Lama guanicoe">
    <common-name>Guanaco</common-name>
    <physical-characteristics>
      <mass>115 to 140 kg.</mass>
      <appearance>
        They stand at 1,100 to 1,200mm at the shoulder and have slender bodies with long limbs and neck. The head is typical
        of camelids with long, pointed ears and cleft, highly mobile lips. Their fur can be long, thick and wooly, especially
        along the  flanks, chest and thighs. It is reddish-brown dorsally, and the underparts are white. 
      </appearance>
    </physical-characteristics>
    <natural-history>
       <food-habits>
         Guanacos are herbivores that can inhabit dry areas and forego drinking for long periods. They are versatile foragers,
         both browsing and grazing on grasses and plants. 
       </food-habits>
       <reproduction>
         Females are apparently induced ovulators, and especially in the southern end of the range breeding reaches a peak in
         February. Young are born in December to February after an eleven month gestation period. They weigh 8-15kg at birth
         and nurse for eleven to fifteen months. Usually females do not breed until there third year. 
       </reproduction>
       <behavior>
         There are three types of social groups: family groups, male troops, and solitary males. A family band is composed of
         a single breeding male, several  females, and offspring. Males limit the size of their group by driving out young
         males of six to twelve months and driving off males and sometimes  females trying to enter the group. Males defend a
         territory that the group resides on, and the territory is demarcated by large communal defecation piles.  Only about
         18% of males are in a family group; the others are in bands or solitary. The all-male bands are generally made up of
         young males. Males in  these herds learn fighting ability through play fights. The solitary males tend to be mature
         males looking for females or herds to take over. 
       </behavior>
       <habitat>
         Guanacos inhabit grasslands and shrublands from sea level to 4,000m. Occasionally they winter in forests.
       </habitat>
    </natural-history>
    <conservation status="special concern">
      <detail>
        Guanacos have had their numbers drastically reduced due to human pressures of habitat encroachment, habitat
        destruction, and hunting. In addition, climatic changes are also blamed for decreases in population size and range. 
      </detail>
    </conservation>
  </species>
  <species name="Vicugna vicugna">
    <common-name>Vicuna</common-name>
    <physical-characteristics>
      <mass>35 to 65 kg.</mass>
      <appearance>
        The vicuna is the smallest living species among the family Camelidae. Head and body length is 1,250-1,900 mm, tail
        length is 150-250mm, and shoulder height is 700-1,100mm. A slender body and relatively long neck and limbs give a
        vicuna an elegant appearance. The ears are long, pointed, and narrow. The head is round and yellowish to red-brown in
        color. The long neck has yellowish red bib. The underside and inner parts of the flanks are dirty white. A strange
        mane, 20-30cm long, with silky-white hair adorns the chest. Overall, the pelage is uniform and soft. Compared to the
        similar-looking Lama guanicoe, the vicuna is one fourth the size, its body is paler, and it lacks callosities on the
        inner sides of the forelimbs. Relative weight of the brain is greater than that of the guanaco. Among living
        artiodactyls, vicunas  have unique, rodent-like incisors that are covered with enamel on only one side. Features
        believed to be adaptations to  high altitudes include a large heart, specialized blood cells with hemoglobin of
        greater affinty for oxygen, and a weight that  is 50 percent heavier than other mammals of the same size. Vision and
        hearing is good, although the former is far more  developed. Olfaction is fairly poor. Nowak (1991), Grizmek (1990). 
      </appearance>
    </physical-characteristics>
    <natural-history>
      <food-habits>
        The vicuna is strictly a grazer. Its diet consist of mostly short perennial grasses. The incisors are specially
        adapted to its diet. They are large and  continuously growing as in rodents. The young often graze while lying
        down. Both young and adults chew cud when they are at rest. Unlike most other  camelids, the vicuna requires daily
        intake of water. Therefore, when selecting a territory, it searches an area with favorable watering sites. The average
        feeding range is 184ha. Nowak (1991), Grizmek (1990), MacDonald (1984).
      </food-habits>
      <reproduction>
        Mating begins in March and April. They mate while lying down on their chests, and copulation lasts 10-20
        minutes. After 330-350 days of gestation  period, a female gives birth to a single offspring of 4-6 kg in February and
        March. The female gives birth in a standing position, and it neither licks nor  eats the afterbirth. The mother mates
        soon after giving birth. The young is mobile after just 15 minutes at birth. It remains close aside its mother for at
        least 8 months. It continues to suckle until it reaches 10 months. Young females at this stage are expelled from the
        herd by the dominant male. For  young males, this happens at 4-9 months. Expelled females are usually accepted into
        another group. Females are capable of mating when they reach 2  years. Some are still reproductively active at 19
        years. Vicunas in the wild live up to 15-20 years. In captivity, an individual was reported to have lived  24
        years. MacDonald (1984), Nowak (1991), Grizmek (1990).
      </reproduction>
      <behavior>
        Vicunas are alert and shy animals that flee very rapidly. They are capable of running 47 km/hr at an elevation of
        4,500 meters. Movement is extremely  graceful compared to any other hoofed animal. When in danger, vicunas make a
        clear, whistling sound. The dominant male warns its herd with an alarm  call, and positions itself between the threat
        and the members. A single dominant male leads a group of females and juveniles. It determines the range of  the
        territory and group membership, and it drives other males away from the family. The territorial male keeps its members
        closely together at a distance of no more than 160ft. Group members display submission to the male by laying their
        neck over the back. Family groups are closed societies,  excluding alien males and, at times, preventing even young
        females from joining. The average size of a family is 6-10 individuals depending on the  feeding condition in the
        territory. Vicunas are one of the few ungulates to possess a feeding territory and a separate sleeping territory. They
        are diurnal,  and at night they retreat to their sleeping areas at higher altitudes. Adult males that do not lead any
        herd become either solitary, or they form a large  group of 30 or even 150 individuals. However, there is low
        cohesiveness among the members of these bachelor herds, and hierarchy is absent. Nowak  (1991), Grizmek (1990). 
      </behavior>
      <habitat>
        Vicunas are found in semiarid rolling grasslands and plains at altitudes of 3,500-5,750 meters. These lands are
        covered with short and tough vegetation.  Due to their daily water demands, vicunas live in areas where water is
        readily accessible. Climate in the habitat is usually dry and cold. Nowak (1991),  Grizmek (1990).
      </habitat>
    </natural-history>
    <conservation status="endangered">
      <detail>
        The vicuna is classified as vulnerable by the IUCN, and as endangered by the USDI. During the period of the Incas, the
        total population reached 1.5 million. With the fall of the empire, the number dropped dramatically due to massive
        slaughter by the conquerors and the settlers. By 1960, the number decreased to only 6,000. Recent efforts of
        establishing national parks and organizations for protection of vicunas have brought the population back up to
        125,000. About half of this number live at the Pampas Galeras National Vicuna Reserve in Peru. Nowak (1991), Grzimek
        (1990). 
      </detail>
    </conservation>
  </species>
</camelids>
