<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Pittsburgh on Perl.com - programming news, code and culture</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/pittsburgh/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Pittsburgh on Perl.com - programming news, code and culture</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 Feb 2019 18:16:43 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/tags/pittsburgh/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>The Perl Conference in Pittsburgh - Call For Presentations</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/article/the-perl-conference-in-pittsburgh-cfp/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Feb 2019 18:16:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/article/the-perl-conference-in-pittsburgh-cfp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sure, there&amp;rsquo;s more than one way to do it, but yours is the best, right? Seize this opportunity to prove it by submitting a talk for The Perl Conference in Pittsburgh! Submit your presentation ideas by March 1. If it&amp;rsquo;s accepted you&amp;rsquo;ll attend the conference as a guest speaker for free and get a free room upgrade just for submitting your proposal!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are looking for all level of speakers, first-timers are welcome! The audience will range in levels of expertise and so all level of talks are welcome - your advanced talk is sure to be a hit, just like any &amp;ldquo;Getting started with&amp;rdquo; presentations geared toward beginners. We know the Perl community can benefit from what you have to say! Find out more and submit your idea &lt;a href=&#34;http://bit.ly/tpcipcfp&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not sure you want to give a presentation? We understand. Consider at least attending a few of them. The main conference is Jun 17-19 with master class tutorial sessions surrounding it on Jun 16, 20, and 21. Register to attend The Perl Conference in Pittsburgh &lt;a href=&#34;https://perlconference.us/tpc-2019-pit/registration/&#34;&gt;today&lt;/a&gt;, and you&amp;rsquo;ll receive the early bird discount!
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Cover image &lt;a href=&#34;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Pittsburgh_Skyline_at_night_(3021295447).jpg&#34;&gt;Wikimedia&lt;/a&gt; licensed under Creative Commons&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>

