<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Miniconf on Perl.com - programming news, code and culture</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/miniconf/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Miniconf on Perl.com - programming news, code and culture</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 May 2015 12:26:37 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/tags/miniconf/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Miniconf NYC - a free Perl conference</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/article/175/2015/5/14/Miniconf-NYC---a-free-Perl-conference/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 May 2015 12:26:37 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/article/175/2015/5/14/Miniconf-NYC---a-free-Perl-conference/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Just when you thought there couldn&amp;rsquo;t be more NYC based Perl events, another comes along! I&amp;rsquo;m one of the organizers for &lt;a href=&#34;http://mini-conf.com&#34;&gt;Miniconf&lt;/a&gt; a free Perl conference that&amp;rsquo;s running here in New York on Saturday June 6th, two days day before YAPC::NA. There&amp;rsquo;s also a pre-conference social event, and you can sign up for both events on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/The-New-York-Perl-Meetup-Group/http://www.meetup.com/The-New-York-Perl-Meetup-Group/&#34;&gt;meetup&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-to-expect&#34;&gt;What to expect&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have two large rooms for the day, one for training and the other for the hackathon. Taking our cue from the recent NYC Perl hackathon, for our hackathon we&amp;rsquo;re going to cluster attendees around projects they&amp;rsquo;re interested in working on, and each project team will have a leader responsible for helping attendees get up to speed. I like this approach because it&amp;rsquo;s newbie friendly, and encourages a productive use of the time. We&amp;rsquo;ve got a few teams already:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do you know Perl 5 and are interested in Perl 6? Then you might be interested joining my team which is converting Perl 5 modules to Perl 6.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Want to contribute to core Perl 5 development? Join the &amp;ldquo;Show core modules some love&amp;rdquo; team led by Richard Elberger and help close a few tickets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interested in Mojolicious web development? Help Curtis Brandt hack on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/aggrolite/Mojo-Snoo&#34;&gt;Mojo::Snoo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have a hackathon project you&amp;rsquo;d like to work on, &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:admin@mini-conf.com&#34;&gt;email us&lt;/a&gt; and we&amp;rsquo;ll add it to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://mini-conf.com&#34;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;. Of course, solo hackers are welcome too :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For training, in the morning we have brian d foy delivering his popular &amp;ldquo;Become a CPAN author in three hours&amp;rdquo; course. This is a great introductory course for aspiring CPAN contributors - learn how to create a Perl distribution, package it up and upload it to CPAN. Contributing to CPAN is one of the most fun and rewarding things a Perl developer can learn - once your distribution is on CPAN, &lt;strong&gt;anyone&lt;/strong&gt; can use it and benefit from it - how cool is that? It&amp;rsquo;s also interesting to get to know the Perl toolchain, and how systems like CPAN and PAUSE work. We currently have an afternoon training slot available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re going to see the day out with lightning talks - always a fun affair. At the moment we&amp;rsquo;re thinking the project teams can give a lightning talk to describe their progress for the day, but it might make sense to just have a more general lightning talk slot - if you want to give a lightning talk, &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:admin@mini-conf.com&#34;&gt;email us&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ll probably give a talk on one of my dumber &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Cache::Reddit&#34;&gt;modules&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-to-help&#34;&gt;How to help&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spread the word! We&amp;rsquo;re promoting the event through social media and other outlets (like this website, see the banner ad). Follow the Miniconf Twitter [feed]() - we&amp;rsquo;ll use it to communicate conference updates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re also looking for sponsors, if you work for a company interested in reaching New York based programmers, give them our email address, or even better send them introductory email cc&amp;rsquo;ing &lt;code&gt;admin@mini-conf.com&lt;/code&gt;. With sponsors we&amp;rsquo;re trying something a little bit different, we have sponsorship slots for particular aspects of the conference. So an organization can be the &amp;ldquo;pizza and soda sponsor&amp;rdquo; to make a more visible link between a sponsor&amp;rsquo;s contribution and the benefits of the conference. Every sponsor gets their logo on the conference website, on the big screens during the conference, and promotion through social media. We&amp;rsquo;re also running a &amp;ldquo;swag&amp;rdquo; table for sponsors to contribute merchandise, an obvious win-win, as the sponsor gets brand promotion and the attendees get free stuff!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a programmer and tech conference regular myself, I&amp;rsquo;m trying to create the kind of conference that I&amp;rsquo;d want to go to. If you have any questions or suggestions, &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:admin@mini-conf.com&#34;&gt;email us&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;m looking forward to seeing everyone there!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;This article was originally posted on &lt;a href=&#34;http://perltricks.com&#34;&gt;PerlTricks.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>

