<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Kim Ryan on Perl.com - programming news, code and culture</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/authors/kim-ryan/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Kim Ryan on Perl.com - programming news, code and culture</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 Jan 1999 00:00:00 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/authors/kim-ryan/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Success in Migrating from C to Perl</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/pub/1999/01/kr-perl.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jan 1999 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/pub/1999/01/kr-perl.html/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;This article describes how a large laser printing bureau in Sydney, Australia was able to migrate from C to Perl for most of its software development needs. As well as gaining the benefits from a modern and flexible programming language, the change gave an opportunity to improve the approach to code design, maintenance and documentation. Eventually, Perl was being used for activities that were not contemplated when the trial began, such as emailing and web enablement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;history&#34;&gt;History&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The company&amp;rsquo;s main business focus is the conversion of large amounts of customer&amp;rsquo;s financial data (increasingly supplied electronically) into printed and mailed invoices, pay slips, dividends and statements. Other items such as bar codes, price and cheque books are also produced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The large amount of variation in customer input data coupled with their requirements for printed output means that most jobs were handled with customised C programs on a Unix platform, in conjunction with various typesetting tools. The industry the company operates in is typically very competitive, and fast accurate turn around is essential. Some jobs have time frames of less than three days, from receipt of specifications to printing and mailing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;looking-for-alternatives&#34;&gt;Looking For Alternatives&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I began working as a contractor at the bureau in 1996. After gaining familiarity with the existing code base I began to look for a newer programming language. I had always been frustrated with the common problems of C such as -&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;memory violations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the need to accurately define variables types and memory requirements&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the number of times you were forced to use indirection&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the low (byte) level that strings were operated on&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These issues were more apparent in the very quick development cycle that the company worked under.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this stage I had not even heard of Perl, and thought that &lt;strong&gt;AWK&lt;/strong&gt; could be a solution. When trying to get a book on AWK the sales assistant suggested I try the Perl books, which at the time were just &amp;ldquo;Programming Perl&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Learning Perl&amp;rdquo;. The language was certainly different to anything I had used before, and required a change in mind set, but I could see many features that were very useful to us, like-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;full regular expressions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ability to read and extract text and binary data from any format (unpack statement)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;rapid prototyping&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;complex data structures created on the fly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;easy, complete and integrated debugging&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;programs failing gracefully, no core dumps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;first-steps&#34;&gt;First Steps&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few small, non critical jobs were selected for an initial trial. Perl&amp;rsquo;s flexibility and ease of use paid off in quick development time and frequent changes in user requirements were easily handled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In early 1997, a project came in from a Pay TV supplier for bill production, with a seven week schedule from reciept of final user requirements to first production printing. Over 8000 lines of code was written and tested, and delivered on schedule to a satisfied customer. A requirement for complex report tables was easily implemented with the WYSISWG style of Perl &lt;strong&gt;formats&lt;/strong&gt;, for which C has no equivalent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;larger-projects&#34;&gt;Larger Projects&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In April of 1997, the laser bureau won a tender for the out-sourcing of all printing requirements for a leading insurance company. The project would last for several years and consist of many stages. The company began to consider Perl as the development language for this critical project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the one hand, most of our programmers were only familiar with C, and recruiting experienced Perl programmers was just not possible at the time. All of our library of standard routines was written in C.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, Perl had already proved itself as a rapid and reliable development tool. The similarities between Perl and C would make training fairly straight forward. The library would have to be ported to Perl, but could also be improved and extended in the process. The decision was made to use Perl for this project, and to eventually extend it to all new development work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;building-the-library&#34;&gt;Building the Library&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first step was porting about 5000 lines of library code. The code was up to 8 years old in parts, and the original authors were not always around. Some modules were duplicated and others were undocumented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the conversion, modules were either translated by hand from C or completely rewritten. Some modules were created with an object-oriented approach, but our experience here was fairly limited. In nearly all cases, the number of lines of code was reduced . A conscious decision was made to avoid the more cryptic elements of Perl, and adopt features that improved readability and maintenance, such as-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the &lt;strong&gt;strict&lt;/strong&gt; pragma&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fully qualified calls to library modules (no use of &lt;strong&gt;Exporter&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the &lt;strong&gt;English&lt;/strong&gt; module&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;file and directory handles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;avoiding speed and space optimizations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;avoiding reference to special defaulting variables like $_&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All modules were thoroughly documented, using the excellent standards found in CPAN (Comprehensive Perl Archive Network) as a model. Eventually this documentation was converted to a Windows help file, allowing context sensitive search on module names within &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.premia.com&#34;&gt;Codewright&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; the programmers editor we used. This editor was very useful for automating code production in any language, with features like syntax chroma-coding , template expansion of language constructs, built in difference checking, symbol browsing, multi-file grep, and search and replace).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The staged introduction of Perl allowed the library to evolve. As we learned new techniques, or new modules (like file handles ) came along, we could work them into the library. As only a small amount of code relied on the library, it could be altered without too many problems. To maintain consistency, a single resource was need to approve library submissions and bug fixes. A strict conformance to regression testing was part of the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;perl-becomes-more-widespread&#34;&gt;Perl Becomes More Widespread&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the library converted, the implementation began for the insurance company&amp;rsquo;s projects. New staff were brought in and trained in Perl. Reusable sections of code were located, generalised and moved into the library.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before writing new modules, CPAN was checked to see if something similar existed. A good example of this was the &lt;strong&gt;Date::Manip&lt;/strong&gt; module, which could tell you if a given date is a working day, or what the date is 90 days from now. This was something we had to do frequently, and not having to code our own modules saved lots of valuable time. However, no code was found for tasks like reading the binary formats that COBOL uses to store numbers (the insurance company was an MVS shop), and this took some time to develop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project progressed well. The delivery schedule for the projects was demanding, and at times change requests flowed through daily, but we were able to keep up with just a handful of developers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Programmers working on other projects within the bureau began to use Perl. Eventually all new staff were trained in Perl, and quite often, they already had some exposure to the language The library now had a lot more functionality than the original C version. The portable nature of Perl meant that development could take place on a PC, if that was the programmer&amp;rsquo;s preference, and transferred to Unix without any changes. The library code was sent to affiliates of the bureau in other states.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;new-uses&#34;&gt;New Uses&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We found that Perl could easily handle new requirements, that were never imagined when the project started, including,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;automated report generation through &lt;strong&gt;SAMBA&lt;/strong&gt; and a Perl HP-PCL module&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Web-enabled work flow tracking with &lt;strong&gt;mySQL&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;CGI&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;automated email notification to customers on receipt of data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;conclusions&#34;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The introduction of Perl helped the bureau to confidently take on larger and more complex projects. We now have 11 programmers who can develop in Perl (as well as maintaining older C code) and over 100,000 lines of highly portable production code. Perl is routinely used for new projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perl&amp;rsquo;s flexibility certainly made the programmers job easier and more satisfying. The fact that Perl is an evolving language, and the large and well supported CPAN library means that there are a lot useful resources in the Perl community to draw on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although this is not specific to Perl, the migration from one language to another was a great opportunity to improve the quality and repeatabilty of our coding process, and was one of the key justifications. If you are going to switch languages, you need to commit to a big improvement on what has gone before.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>

