<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Conferences Yapc Tpc Oscon on Perl.com - programming news, code and culture</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/conferences-yapc-tpc-oscon/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Conferences Yapc Tpc Oscon on Perl.com - programming news, code and culture</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 06 May 2003 00:00:00 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/tags/conferences-yapc-tpc-oscon/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>2003 Perl Conferences</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/pub/2003/05/06/conferences.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2003 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/pub/2003/05/06/conferences.html/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The season of Perl conferences is almost upon us! In fact, the first of the YAPCs for this year is in less than a week. So I thought this would be a good time to give a tour of the various conferences and see what&amp;rsquo;s going on at each.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;yapc-israel&#34;&gt;YAPC::Israel&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first of the conferences, starting on Sunday, May 11, is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.perl.org.il/YAPC/2003&#34;&gt;YAPC::Israel&lt;/a&gt;. If you were planning to attend this, then please note that that&amp;rsquo;s one day earlier than originally announced. It&amp;rsquo;ll be at Haifa University, at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cri.haifa.ac.il/&#34;&gt;Caesarea Rothschild Institute&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s going on? Well, there&amp;rsquo;ll be a variety of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.perl.org.il/YAPC/2003/presentations.html&#34;&gt;presentations&lt;/a&gt; in Hebrew and in English: Reuven Lerner will be teaching the five things every Perl programmer should know; Yevgeny Menaker, author of &amp;ldquo;Programming Perl in the .NET Environment,&amp;rdquo; will be talking about .NET; and there&amp;rsquo;s a strong X Windows theme to the conference, with a Tk tutorial from Ido Trivizki, Ran Eliam presenting a new UI toolkit, and Mikhael Goikhman talking about X11 window managers and Perl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The usual collection of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.perl.org.il/YAPC/2003/schedule.html#light&#34;&gt;lightning talks&lt;/a&gt; will take place, and special guest &lt;a href=&#34;http://perl.plover.com&#34;&gt;Mark-Jason Dominus&lt;/a&gt; will be presenting a set of lightning talks all by himself. Mark is also keynoting with a retrospective of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://perl.plover.com/qotw/&#34;&gt;Quiz Of The Week&lt;/a&gt;. After the conference, Mark will be giving three one-day &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pti.co.il/mjd.html&#34;&gt;training courses&lt;/a&gt;. (Not included in the conference.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this and more for 150 Shekels. Can&amp;rsquo;t be bad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;yapc-canada&#34;&gt;YAPC::Canada&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hot on the heels of the Israel conference will be the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.yapc.ca/&#34;&gt;Canadian YAPC&lt;/a&gt;, on May 15-16. This will be 85 Canadian Dollars and includes dinner, a barbeque and CD-ROM proceedings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;YAPC::Canada will be keynoted by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.yapc.ca/keynote.html&#34;&gt;Dick Hardt&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.activestate.com/&#34;&gt;ActiveState&lt;/a&gt; - Dick will be talking about the history of Perl on Windows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;ll be both free and professional tutorials at this YAPC, with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psdt.com/news/yapc-canada.html&#34;&gt;Peter Scott&lt;/a&gt; giving tuition on object-oriented Perl. The two free tutorials are Mick Villeneuve&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Yet Another Perl Tutorial&amp;rdquo; for first-time Perl programmers, and Steve Jenkins&amp;rsquo; &amp;ldquo;Introduction to Regular Expressions.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The presentations will be divided into a beginner and an advanced stream; highlights include talks on the Perl debugger, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.class-dbi.com/&#34;&gt;Class::DBI&lt;/a&gt;, event loops, extreme testing, and Perl date and time handling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;perl-whirl&#34;&gt;Perl Whirl&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In June, some of us lucky individuals will be talking about Perl on a ship in the waters around Hawaii for the 2003 &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.geekcruises.com/home/pw3_home.html&#34;&gt;Perl Whirl&lt;/a&gt;. There&amp;rsquo;ll be a strong Perl 6 theme, with four half-day courses on Perl 6. Randal Schwartz will be presenting his packages, objects, references and modules tutorial to complement the new &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.oreilly.com/catalog/lrnperlorm&#34;&gt;sequel to Learning Perl&lt;/a&gt;. MJD will be there, too, giving his famous &lt;a href=&#34;http://perl.plover.com/yak/flags/&#34;&gt;Red Flags&lt;/a&gt; tutorial, and a half-day tutorial on iterators and generators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;ll be other talks, of course, although the program isn&amp;rsquo;t yet finalized. I shall attend, talking about how you can use Perl 6 right now - in a manner of speaking. &amp;hellip; And, of course, there&amp;rsquo;ll be Hawaii, the Wizards&amp;rsquo; Cocktail Party, and much more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;yapc-na&#34;&gt;YAPC::NA&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In mid-June comes the main &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.yapc.org/America/&#34;&gt;Yet Another Perl Conference&lt;/a&gt;. This year, it&amp;rsquo;s at Boca Raton, Fla., from June 16-18. The cost is $85.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tutorials include Damian Conway&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Everyday Perl&amp;rdquo; and Tim Maher&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Minimal Perl,&amp;rdquo; Randal&amp;rsquo;s PROM tutorial again, and Abigail&amp;rsquo;s half-day regex tutorial. Larry and Damian will present a two-hour slot on Perl 6 on the final day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other short talks that caught my eye were Helen Cook talking about video manipulation; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.oreillynet.com/pub/au/129&#34;&gt;Schuyler Erle&lt;/a&gt; on geocaching; and two talks from Piers Cawley, on refactoring and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www-106.ibm.com/developerworks/linux/library/l-pixie.html&#34;&gt;Pixie&lt;/a&gt; object persistence framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;oscon-tpc-7&#34;&gt;OSCon/TPC 7&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then in July, where we have the main event, &lt;a href=&#34;http://conferences.oreillynet.com/os2003/perl/&#34;&gt;The Perl Conference&lt;/a&gt;, on the theme of &amp;ldquo;Embracing and Extending Proprietary Software.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, Perl 6 will figure extensively, with talks from Damian on &amp;ldquo;What&amp;rsquo;s New in Perl 6,&amp;rdquo; the new &lt;code&gt;Perl6::Rules&lt;/code&gt; module, Dan Sugalski and Leon Brocard on Parrot, and Allison Randal explaining the Perl 6 design philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those of us still using Perl 5, I would recommend Ask Bjoern Hansen and Robert Spier&amp;rsquo;s explanation of &lt;a href=&#34;http://conferences.oreillynet.com/cs/os2003/view/e_sess/4252&#34;&gt;the perl.org single-signon process&lt;/a&gt;, Andy Wardley talking about &lt;a href=&#34;http://conferences.oreillynet.com/cs/os2003/view/e_sess/4028&#34;&gt;what&amp;rsquo;s new in Template Toolkit 3&lt;/a&gt;, and the unmissable &lt;a href=&#34;http://conferences.oreillynet.com/cs/os2003/view/e_sess/4191&#34;&gt;random talk by MJD&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, there&amp;rsquo;s more than just Perl things going on at OSCon - you can drop into sessions on Apache, MySQL and PostGreSQL, Python and Ruby, the XML track and the eclectic &amp;ldquo;Emerging Topics&amp;rdquo; track. There&amp;rsquo;s also be keynotes from Weta Digital on animating the &amp;ldquo;Lord of the Rings&amp;rdquo; movies, Mitch Kapor on his open-source desktop applications project, and George Dyson on &amp;ldquo;Von Neumann&amp;rsquo;s Universe.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s all happening at the Portland Mariott, from July 7-11. Make sure you&amp;rsquo;re there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;yapc-europe&#34;&gt;YAPC::Europe&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Less than two weeks after TPC comes the final event of the conference season, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://yapc.mongueurs.net/&#34;&gt;European YAPC&lt;/a&gt;, at the CNAM Conservatoire in Paris.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Details of speakers are not yet confirmed, but we know it&amp;rsquo;ll be July 23-25, and it&amp;rsquo;ll be vast quantities of fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;and-finally&#34;&gt;And finally &amp;hellip;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case you&amp;rsquo;re overwhelmed by the amount of conferences on this year, I maintain an at-a-glance calendar at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.icalx.com/html/PerlConf/year.php?cal=Perl32Conferences&#34;&gt;iCal Exchange&lt;/a&gt;; if you&amp;rsquo;re a user of Apple&amp;rsquo;s iCal, you can subscribe to the Perl Conferences calendar at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.icalx.com/public/PerlConf/Perl32Conferences.ics&#34;&gt;http://www.icalx.com/public/PerlConf/Perl32Conferences.ics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope to see you at one or more of the above!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>

