<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Elizabeth Mattijsen on Perl.com - programming news, code and culture</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/authors/elizabeth-mattijsen/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Elizabeth Mattijsen on Perl.com - programming news, code and culture</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2018 08:22:27 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/authors/elizabeth-mattijsen/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>An Open Letter to the Perl Community</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/article/an-open-letter-to-the-perl-community/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2018 08:22:27 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/article/an-open-letter-to-the-perl-community/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The past few months I&amp;rsquo;ve been wracking my brain on how to bring &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.perl.org&#34;&gt;Pumpkin Perl&amp;nbsp;5&lt;/a&gt; (or &lt;code&gt;perl&lt;/code&gt;, as in the version of Perl that is maintained by the Perl&amp;nbsp;5 Porters) and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.perl6.org&#34;&gt;Rakudo Perl&amp;nbsp;6&lt;/a&gt; (or &lt;code&gt;perl6&lt;/code&gt;, as in the implementation of Perl&amp;nbsp;6 based on NQP and &lt;a href=&#34;http://moarvm.org&#34;&gt;MoarVM&lt;/a&gt;) closer together again. Yes, I haven&amp;rsquo;t given up on this idea, although my first attempt (organizing the &lt;a href=&#34;https://szabgab.com/perl-reunification-summit-2012.html&#34;&gt;Perl Reunification Summit in 2012&lt;/a&gt;) hasn&amp;rsquo;t really worked out the way I had hoped it would. But it did have some positive effects, because it brought together people from the Perl community that normally would never have been in a discussion, and some nice advances were made for Perl&amp;nbsp;6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am still interested in getting Perl&amp;nbsp;5 and Perl&amp;nbsp;6 together, because they both share the same Perl Mindset, a mix of just enough DWIM (Do What I Mean) and not too much of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.destroyallsoftware.com/talks/wat&#34;&gt;WAT&lt;/a&gt; (What is it doing now???).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know Perl&amp;nbsp;6 has had a complicated development process. You could argue that Perl&amp;nbsp;6 is the fourth implementation attempt. It is also the first Perl&amp;nbsp;6 implementation that actually works, interfaces seamlessly with &lt;a href=&#34;http://modules.perl6.org/dist/Inline::Perl5:cpan:NINE&#34;&gt;Perl&amp;nbsp;5&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/niner/Inline-Python/blob/master/README.md&#34;&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt; or any &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.perl6.org/language/nativecall&#34;&gt;external C library&lt;/a&gt; out of the box, is beating Perl&amp;nbsp;5 on more and more &lt;a href=&#34;http://news.perlfoundation.org/2017/11/perl-6-performance-and-reliabi-4.html&#34;&gt;micro-benchmarks&lt;/a&gt;, and is being used in production, especially in the area of &lt;a href=&#34;http://mi.cro.services&#34;&gt;Micro Services&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://perl6advent.wordpress.com/2017/12/13/&#34;&gt;parsing of non-ASCII languages&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some consider Perl 6 to be a sister language to Perl 5. Personally, I consider Perl 6 more of a genetically engineered daughter language with the best genes from many parents. A daughter with a difficult childhood, in which she alienated many, who is now getting out of puberty into early adulthood. But I digress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-butterfly-perl-nbsp-5-project&#34;&gt;The Butterfly Perl&amp;nbsp;5 Project&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no clear upgrade path from Perl&amp;nbsp;5 to Perl&amp;nbsp;6 and this means that there is no chance of combining Perl&amp;nbsp;5 and Perl&amp;nbsp;6 to become more than the sum of their parts. The Perl&amp;nbsp;5 Porters are still adding features that are inspired by Perl&amp;nbsp;6, which further confuses the picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A radical idea would be that the Perl&amp;nbsp;5 Porters would go back to their original goal: &lt;strong&gt;porting&lt;/strong&gt; Perl&amp;nbsp;5. But this time, not to different operating systems, but porting Perl&amp;nbsp;5 to different Virtual Machines. Place a moratorium on new features, with development confined to maintenance on the current runtime. This would safeguard the most valued feature of Perl&amp;nbsp;5, its stability and backwards compatibility. But I digress again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Porting Perl&amp;nbsp;5 to NQP (Not Quite Perl, one of the implementation languages of Rakudo Perl&amp;nbsp;6) would provide such a migration path. Basically this would be the revival of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/rakudo-p5/v5&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;use v5&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; project, which implements a version of Perl&amp;nbsp;5 as a slang (sub-language) of Perl&amp;nbsp;6. Such an effort would provide a clear migration path from the 30 year old &lt;code&gt;perl&lt;/code&gt; interpreter to a modern VM, allowing execution of Perl&amp;nbsp;5 source code on MoarVM, JVM and JavaScript backends. Thus guaranteeing a life for Perl&amp;nbsp;5 as a programming language way into the future, taking advantage of all the multi-processing features that a modern VM provides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the short term, it would still be slower than Perl&amp;nbsp;5, but in the long run it would be running faster. This is because of the Just-In-Time compilation of hot code, which optimizes all source code to machine code on the fly, rather than the path of hand-optimizing hot code into XS. Although I wholeheartedly would support a Butterfly Perl&amp;nbsp;5 Project, I&amp;rsquo;ve also come to the conclusion that it is no longer an itch I would want to scratch personally at this moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-cpan-butterfly-plan&#34;&gt;The CPAN Butterfly Plan&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what does Perl&amp;nbsp;5 consist of anyway? It&amp;rsquo;s a runtime &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Perl/perl5&#34;&gt;written in C and a Macro language&lt;/a&gt;. But it&amp;rsquo;s also a core &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Perl/perl5/tree/blead/lib&#34;&gt;set of modules&lt;/a&gt; with defined APIs and documentation. To many, the modules on CPAN are an integral part of Perl 5. Many of these modules would need to be ported for a Butterfly Perl&amp;nbsp;5 Project. But porting them would be very useful to Perl&amp;nbsp;6 in and of itself because it would make porting user Perl 5 programs to Perl 6 much easier. Therefore I am starting an effort to mass-migrate Perl&amp;nbsp;5 modules to Perl&amp;nbsp;6, both core modules and others on CPAN.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are developing a &amp;ldquo;How to port a Perl&amp;nbsp;5 Module to Perl&amp;nbsp;6&amp;rdquo; guide, covering things like naming conventions, exports, translating Perl&amp;nbsp;5 OO into Perl&amp;nbsp;6 OO, scoping gotchas and threading. Plus notes on various built-in features of Perl&amp;nbsp;6 which may be useful when porting semantics rather than code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next we&amp;rsquo;ll create a website to register contributors who will take responsibility for porting a Perl&amp;nbsp;5 module to Perl&amp;nbsp;6 (e.g. from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/perl6/perl6-most-wanted&#34;&gt;Most Wanted list&lt;/a&gt;). Contributors will link to a GitHub repo from where they&amp;rsquo;ll write the code, handle Pull Requests and give out commit bits. Ported modules would be uploaded to CPAN as new Perl 6 distributions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ll create a leaderboard which ranks contributors progress. The position on the leaderboard could be defined as the product of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;size of the original Perl&amp;nbsp;5 module in lines of code + documentation + tests&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;% completion of the migration, to be indicated by the contributor and judged by a jury of peers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bonus points if the documentation and/or tests are improved on the fly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bonus points if XS code is involved and there is no Pure Perl implementation available&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sponsors would match migrated code with donations to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.perlfoundation.org/perl_6_core_development_fund&#34;&gt;Perl&amp;nbsp;6 Core development fund&lt;/a&gt;, so that contributors not only get to support Perl&amp;nbsp;6 directly, but also indirectly support the further development of the core of Perl&amp;nbsp;6. Something in the order of a cent per converted line of Perl&amp;nbsp;5 code / documentation / tests, to be donated at the moment a jury of peers has decided the converted module is functional enough to be &amp;ldquo;published&amp;rdquo; as a 1.0 version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The leaderboard would be backed by a website that that tracks all of this activity, along the lines of &lt;a href=&#34;https://alerts.perl6.org&#34;&gt;alerts.perl6.org&lt;/a&gt;, with an API and social media interface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This should make 2018 the year that people really start to migrate their code from Perl&amp;nbsp;5 to Perl&amp;nbsp;6. Be it because they can, they want to try, or just to see how Perl&amp;nbsp;6 will work out for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;winding-down&#34;&gt;Winding down&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I sincerely hope that enough people will support the CPAN Butterfly Plan, and maybe a Butterfly Perl&amp;nbsp;5 Project. So that we can all start moving forward in one direction, rather than two. If you&amp;rsquo;d like to get involved, please join us on the #perl6-dev channel on &lt;a href=&#34;http://freenode.net&#34;&gt;irc.freenode.net&lt;/a&gt;. If you don&amp;rsquo;t have an IRC app installed, you can talk to us in your browser via the &lt;a href=&#34;http://webchat.freenode.net/?channels=perl6-dev&amp;amp;nick=&#34;&gt;web-interface&lt;/a&gt; instead.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>

