<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Legacies on Perl.com - programming news, code and culture</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/legacy/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Legacies on Perl.com - programming news, code and culture</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2014 06:00:00 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/legacy/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Perl Today (February 2014)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/pub/2014/02/perl-today-february-2014.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2014 06:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/pub/2014/02/perl-today-february-2014.html/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/_pub_2014_02_perl-today-february-2014/headshot_small.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;brian d foy is the author of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.masteringperl.org&#34;&gt;Mastering Perl&lt;/a&gt;, now available in its second edition, as well as several other Perl books. As the founder of Perl mongers, he&amp;rsquo;s been active in the Perl community for almost 20 years.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perl&amp;rsquo;s so big now that it&amp;rsquo;s almost impossible to pay attention to everything going on. Instead of reading the thoughts of me, just one person, on the current state of Perl, why not gather several major players who can cover many areas that you may not have noticed? I&amp;rsquo;ve collected some voices from parts of the large and diverse Perl community to highlight a small fraction of everything going on, from community development, hard core coding, the job market, and various problem domains. Although not definitive, their combination makes a good summary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/_pub_2014_02_perl-today-february-2014/randal_small.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Randal Schwartz is the original author of Programming perl and Learning Perl, along with numerous other Perl credits. He&amp;rsquo;s the current host of &lt;a href=&#34;http://twit.tv/floss&#34;&gt;FLOSS Weekly&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perl started as a Unix shell replacement to help sysadmins get more productive with less risk and a flatter learning curve (you didn&amp;rsquo;t have to learn the quirks of dozens of small utilities, just the quirks of One &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wall.org/~larry/&#34;&gt;Larry Wall&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then along came the web, and &amp;ldquo;scripts&amp;rdquo; could be used to provide interactive web pages, and Perl became the darling language of the web, first with &amp;ldquo;cgi-lib.pl&amp;rdquo;, and then with CGI, and later with larger frameworks like &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.masonhq.com&#34;&gt;Mason&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.catalystframework.org&#34;&gt;Catalyst&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, Perl&amp;rsquo;s scripting abilities also matured, and the ability to scale Perl programs with modern testing and OO frameworks (like &lt;a href=&#34;http://moose.perl.org&#34;&gt;Moose&lt;/a&gt;) empowered programmers to write 10-line scripts and 100,000-line applications using the same core language features: a distinctive advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perl 5 development stagnated a bit, trigging the whole &lt;a href=&#34;http://perl6.org&#34;&gt;Perl 6&lt;/a&gt; revival, and the relationship between Perl 5 and Perl 6 is still not understood by most people outside the direct Perl community (nor even by some who are &lt;em&gt;in&lt;/em&gt; the community). But with the establishment of the quarterly point release, and the annual major releases, Perl 5 seems to have gotten firmly back in the saddle of modern development again. And while Perl 6 continues to be developed and redesigned, parts of it are already quite useful for early adopters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/_pub_2014_02_perl-today-february-2014/kp_headshot_small.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Karen Pauley was a founding member of the Belfast Perl Mongers, a volunteer with the YAPC Europe Foundation, and is the President of The Perl Foundation.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, Perl is a reason for creating community systems to support Perl itself. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.perlfoundation.org/&#34;&gt;The Perl Foundation&lt;/a&gt; doesn&amp;rsquo;t write the Perl language, we don&amp;rsquo;t influence its direction; instead we work with the Perl community to organize funding, volunteers, marketing, and legal counsel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;&amp;quot;http://www.perlfoundation.org/perl_5_core_maintenance_fund&#34;&gt;Perl 5 Core Maintenance&lt;/a&gt; fund was created in June 2011, in collaboration with some of Perl 5&amp;rsquo;s most generous supporters, such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.booking.com/&#34;&gt;booking.com&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.craigslist.org/about/charitable&#34;&gt;craigslist Charitable Fund&lt;/a&gt;. Our goal was to pay a few key volunteer developers to spend more of their time working on the maintenance and development of Perl 5. So far we have raised over $280,000 allowing us to compensate Perl internals experts including Nicholas Clark and Dave Mitchell to do more than they could on an unpaid basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.perlfoundation.org/&#34;&gt;The Perl Foundation&lt;/a&gt;, with help from our volunteers and donors, will continue to seek ways to strengthen the language, its community, and the F/OSS world in the coming years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/_pub_2014_02_perl-today-february-2014/steffen_head_small.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Steffen is a physicist-turned-software developer. A long time contributor to Perl and &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/author/SMUELLER&#34;&gt;author of many Perl modules&lt;/a&gt; on the CPAN, he currently works at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.booking.com/&#34;&gt;booking.com&lt;/a&gt; where he manages software infrastructure development.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.booking.com/&#34;&gt;booking.com&lt;/a&gt;, Perl powers one of the most successful, profitable e-commerce companies on the planet. Perl is used throughout our stack from the web layer to mission-critical, highly-available infrastructure. We love it because its flexibility aligns with our aggressive pace of development on our code base of millions of lines of code. We believe that the language&amp;rsquo;s versatility has given us a competitive advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outside of Booking.com, I am an individual contributor to Perl and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.metacpan.org&#34;&gt;CPAN&lt;/a&gt;. Thus I have had the chance to directly support users in more than just a handful of Fortune 500 companies including major banks as well as the IT, automotive, and chemical industries. Perl is used in critical systems of many companies albeit usually in much less prominent roles. It is a humble work horse and truly deserves its reputation as a Swiss Army Chainsaw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Booking.com, we believe that one of Perl&amp;rsquo;s great strengths is its community. Unlike many corporations, we maintain strong symbiotic ties to this development community. Many of our technical staff are active contributors to Perl and Perl modules on the CPAN. We encourage our developers to publish their code. This has both helped with getting our name out to potential future employees and improved the quality of our software overall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/_pub_2014_02_perl-today-february-2014/ricardo_signes.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ricardo Signes is the current Perl 5 project manager, part of the CPAN toolchain maintenance team, and a &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/author/RJBS&#34;&gt;prolific contributor to the CPAN&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perl 5 is entering its fifth year of fixed-schedule releases, meaning that the first few releases on the yearly plans are now out of their supported lifetime. With the release support policy solidly in place, we&amp;rsquo;ve begun to hammer out exactly how we handle Perl&amp;rsquo;s iffiest behaviors: deprecated and experimental features. Enumerating just which features are experimental let us get an idea of what we mean when we say something is experimental, which has led to a means to add new features to Perl without as much fear of getting locked in to bad ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ve gotten a number of exciting new features in the latest perl builds, as experiments. Lexical subroutines, regexp character sets, and postfix dereferencing are the three I&amp;rsquo;m most excited about, and the prospect of experimental subroutine signatures still looks good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the next few releases, I&amp;rsquo;m hoping we&amp;rsquo;ll see improvement continue in three main areas: Perl 5&amp;rsquo;s already-excellent Unicode support, the useful but troublesome PerlIO system, and the ability to provide annotations for improving performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/_pub_2014_02_perl-today-february-2014/Joel_small.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Joel Berger has a Ph.D. in Physics from the University of Illinois at Chicago. He is currently employed writing software for a major financial institution.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perl is my language of choice for almost any task. In my research I routinely found that the flexibility of Perl allowed me to structure a script or simulation in the way that I was thinking about the problem, not the way the language wanted me to think about it. Modern tools like the &lt;a href=&#34;http://moose.perl.org/&#34;&gt;Moose object framework&lt;/a&gt; give Perl the ability to model the most complex set of interdependent classes (as often arises in Physics) with ease. Combine that with the massive &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.metacpan.org/&#34;&gt;CPAN&lt;/a&gt; module archive, from which you can find tools to transform nearly any data format, manipulate and analyze data, or do nearly any other task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my spare time, I contribute to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://mojolicio.us/&#34;&gt;Mojolicious&lt;/a&gt; web framework, which brings the trendy non-blocking web to Perl, a robust and stable language (and the only language with CPAN). Mojolicious comes with lots of functionality like a non-blocking UserAgent (which is also the backbone of the extensive test framework), DOM parser, WebSockets, JSON, and a powerful template system, all built in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/_pub_2014_02_perl-today-february-2014/sawyer_small.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sawyer X is one of the core developers on &lt;a href=&#34;&amp;quot;http://www.perldancer.org&#34;&gt;Dancer&lt;/a&gt;, a Perl web framework inspired by Ruby&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sinatrarb.com/&#34;&gt;Sinatra&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perl is often remembered as the original language of the web. It had good CGI support and was the go-to language for any web programming. The CGI protocol had its issues and so was replaced in time by FastCGI, embedded interpreters in the web servers (mod_perl, mod_php, etc.), and servers implemented in the application language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While you weren&amp;rsquo;t watching, Perl has developed a common protocol, binding web servers, web frameworks, and web applications: &lt;a href=&#34;http://plackperl.org&#34;&gt;PSGI&lt;/a&gt;. PSGI allows any web server to support any web framework and web application. It allows any web framework to support any server, and any user to use any framework on top of any server. In two words: &lt;em&gt;anything goes&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On one hand new frameworks appeared (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.perldancer.org&#34;&gt;Dancer&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://mojolicio.us/&#34;&gt;Mojolicious&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://amon.64p.org/&#34;&gt;Amon2&lt;/a&gt;) and mature frameworks (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.catalystframework.org&#34;&gt;Catalyst&lt;/a&gt;) started supporting PSGI, and on the other hand web servers written entirely in Perl grew into existence, such as Starman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/_pub_2014_02_perl-today-february-2014/stevan_little_small.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Stevan Little created &lt;a href=&#34;http://moose.perl.org/&#34;&gt;Moose&lt;/a&gt;, a post-modern object system for Perl 5. He&amp;rsquo;s working on adding this to the Perl core language.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perl has had object oriented capabilities since the first release of Perl 5 almost 20 years ago. Since then, best practices have come and gone, along with a sea of modules on the CPAN to help programmers implement those best practices. Although many OO styles still abound, the current &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.onyxneon.com/books/modern_perl/index.html&#34;&gt;Modern Perl&lt;/a&gt; movement has come to settle around the style of OO implemented by the &lt;a href=&#34;http://moose.perl.org/&#34;&gt;Moose&lt;/a&gt; module.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moose itself is based heavily on the OO features that have been designed for &lt;a href=&#34;http://perl6.org&#34;&gt;Perl6&lt;/a&gt;, along with input from several other languages including LISP, Ruby, Smalltalk and others. Moose brings not only support for basic class based OO programming, but it also brings deep meta programming capabilities, and the idea of &amp;ldquo;Roles&amp;rdquo; to Perl OO programming. Roles - which were originally derived from the Smalltalk community where they were called &amp;ldquo;Traits&amp;rdquo; - provide a means of code re-use similar to mix-ins but with an added degree of compositional safety through the use of conflict detection. Moose was originally released in 2006 and in the past 7 years more 2,100 CPAN modules have been released which depend upon it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/_pub_2014_02_perl-today-february-2014/mertens_small.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;David Mertens is a Visiting Assistant Professor at Dickinson College and a contributor to PDL and Prima.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been using Perl for my scientific computing since roughly 2007. Prior to Perl I wrote the bulk of my scientific code in C++ and Matlab. My first exposure to Perl was due to its well known string processing capabilities, but I quickly realized that it was a well designed general purpose programming language. After programming in Perl, Matlab felt cludgy and C++ felt verbose. Once I discovered the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pdl.perl.org&#34;&gt;PDL (Perl Data Language)&lt;/a&gt;, I switched all of new scientific computing to Perl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My most exciting work with Perl has been at the interface of PDL and other modules. A few years ago I discovered the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.prima.eu.org&#34;&gt;Prima graphical toolkit&lt;/a&gt; and eventually wrote PDL-based methods for fast and flexible drawing to a Prima canvas. As my familiarity with Prima has grown, I have begun using it to write interactive simulations for talks and lectures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time and again I found other Perl developers had solved 90% of my problem, leaving the last and most exciting 10% to me. From numerical simulations to web servers to interactive lectures, I can always find the right Perl tool for the job, and the right Perl glue to put it all together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/_pub_2014_02_perl-today-february-2014/Dave.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dave Cross is the owner of &lt;a href=&#34;http://mag-sol.com&#34;&gt;Magnum Solutions Ltd.&lt;/a&gt;, a Perl training and consultancy company based in London. He founded &lt;a href=&#34;http://london.pm.org/&#34;&gt;London.pm&lt;/a&gt;, the first Perl Monger group outside of North America. Dave blogs about Perl at &lt;a href=&#34;http://perlhacks.com/&#34;&gt;Perl Hacks&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been running Perl training courses for six or seven years. The demand for these courses has never been higher than I&amp;rsquo;ve seen over the last year, coming from all kinds of companies&amp;ndash;financial services companies, media giants, dotcoms and many others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nature of those enquiries has been changing. Previously I would get enquiries about generic beginners, intermediate or advanced Perl courses, these days it is just as likely to be a request for training about a specific Perl module like &lt;a href=&#34;http://moose.perl.org/&#34;&gt;Moose&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/DBIx::Class&#34;&gt;DBIx::Class&lt;/a&gt;. These enquiries are coming from companies who have been using Perl for many years but who finally seem to be getting the message that Perl has changed over the last ten years and that by keeping the knowledge of their Perl teams up to date they will retain the competitive advantage that was the reason for them choosing Perl in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of this, I&amp;rsquo;m sure, is driven by the recruitment market in London. There are a lot of companies trying to employ a relatively small number of Perl programmers. This means that the best programmers can be picky and only work for companies that are only using the most modern tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/_pub_2014_02_perl-today-february-2014/ash2013_small.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Andrew Shitov is a Perl enthusiast working with the language since 1998, the organiser of 30+ local and international Perl events in 8 countries, including two YAPC::Europe conferences. [Moscow.pm](&lt;a href=&#34;http://moscow.pm.org&#34;&gt;http://moscow.pm.org&lt;/a&gt; leader in 2007-2013.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perl is not the only programming language in the Universe any more, and thus it might feel that developers do not consider it as the only option. This, on the one hand, is a very pleasant time for improving the language, but on the other hand, Perl suffers from the fact that the language core developers might not feel the responsibility for keeping their product perfect, compatible and suitable for the need of modern programming. Perl faces the danger coming from inside of itself: we have seen a number of annoying incompatibilities introduced in recent releases, not counting the delay of Perl 6 which made Perl less competitive. All in all, Perl is now in a very comfortable position to be able to flush all the bad stuff and be re-born.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;from brian: since Andrew is active in the Russian Perl community, I wanted to publish his response in Russian too.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Сегодня перл находится в таком состоянии, когда он уже не единственный язык во Вселенной, поэтому ему может казаться, что разработчики больше не выбирают его. Это, с одной стороны, очень приятное время для развития языка, но, с другой стороны, перл страдает от того факта, что разработчики языка не ощущают ответственности за поддержание своего продукта качественным, совместимым и отвечающим нуждам современного программирования. Перл столкнулся с опасностью, исходящей из самого себя: мы видели много раздражающих несовместимостей, введенных в последних релизах, не считая задержку с Perl 6, которая сделала перл менее конкурентноспособным. Так или иначе, сейчас перл находится в очень удобном положении и способен сбросить все плохое и переродиться. Мы должны воспользоваться этим шансом.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/_pub_2014_02_perl-today-february-2014/neilb_small.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Neil has managed research and development teams for startups and multinationals. He&amp;rsquo;s currently working on a startup that uses Perl, and also likes to work on projects related to CPAN curation. He started programming in Perl in 1993.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Perl Authors Upload Server (PAUSE), our gateway to CPAN, has been seeing more and more action. 844 people created a new account in 2013 (second only to 2012, with 858). Of those 844 new users, 389 have released something on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cpan.org&#34;&gt;CPAN&lt;/a&gt; to date. Overall, 1803 of the 11k PAUSE users released something in 2013 (2012&amp;rsquo;s total was 1759). Those 1803 users released 7440 different distributions in 2013, the best year ever. Read more about CPAN in 2013 on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://neilb.org/cpan-report/&#34;&gt;CPAN Report&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://birmingham.pm.org/talks/barbie/ct-future/index.html&#34;&gt;Recent upgrades&lt;/a&gt; to the awesome &lt;a href=&#34;http://cpantesters.org&#34;&gt;CPAN Testers&lt;/a&gt; mean we see results within an hour of uploading a module. Within days of releasing a distribution we get feedback on how well our code tests out on a wide range of configurations. Roughly one million reports are uploaded each month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://prepan.org/&#34;&gt;PrePAN&lt;/a&gt; is a new website where we can describe module ideas and get feedback before we commit a specific design to CPAN.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://questhub.io/&#34;&gt;Questhub&lt;/a&gt; has a growing community of Perl developers who use it to manage their backlog of Perl projects (&amp;lsquo;quests&amp;rsquo;). [Template quests](&lt;a href=&#34;http://questhub.io/realm/perl/stencils&#34;&gt;http://questhub.io/realm/perl/stencils&lt;/a&gt; encourage you to contribute to Perl, get involved with the community, improve your distributions, and help others with theirs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://neilb.org/adoption/&#34;&gt;adoption list&lt;/a&gt; identifies stale distributions that are of value to CPAN (e.g. being &lt;a href=&#34;http://deps.cpantesters.org/depended-on-by.pl&#34;&gt;used by other distributions&lt;/a&gt;), but might have lost their primary developer. If you&amp;rsquo;re looking for a project, consider taking on something from the list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Year in Perl 2013 Retrospective</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/pub/2014/01/the-year-in-perl-2013-retrospective.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 06:00:01 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/pub/2014/01/the-year-in-perl-2013-retrospective.html/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-year-in-perl-2013&#34;&gt;The Year in Perl 2013&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome to 2014, Perl mongers, fans, hackers, and dabblers. It&amp;rsquo;s been a big year in our quirky little language. The community has grown. The CPAN has expanded. Bugs have been squashed, conferences attended, and projects released. Here&amp;rsquo;s a cross-section of what happened that you may have missed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;january-2013&#34;&gt;January 2013&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.perloasis.info/opw2013/&#34;&gt;2013 Perl Oasis conference&lt;/a&gt; took place in Orlando, Florida, US.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the Perl Oasis conference, Stevan Little gave a talk entitled &lt;a href=&#34;https://speakerdeck.com/stevan_little/perl-is-not-dead-it-is-a-dead-end&#34;&gt;Perl is not Dead, it is a Dead End&lt;/a&gt; about forking Perl to experiment with new design and implementation ideas. The talk included an announcement of &lt;a href=&#34;http://moeorganization.github.io/moe-web/&#34;&gt;Moe&lt;/a&gt;, a reimplementation of parts of Perl. By September, Moe would go dormant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shawn Moore formally deprecated &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Any::Moose&#34;&gt;Any::Moose&lt;/a&gt;. If you need a lightweight OO system which can upgrade to Moose when you use Moose features, use &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Moo&#34;&gt;Moo&lt;/a&gt; instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nick Perez wrote an article about &lt;a href=&#34;http://perl-yarg.blogspot.ca/2013/01/cloudpan.html&#34;&gt;CloudPAN, a way to use modules locally without installing them&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dan Write of &lt;a href=&#34;http://perlfoundation.org/&#34;&gt;TP&lt;em&gt;/a&lt;/em&gt; published a&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://news.perlfoundation.org/2013/01/perl-5-core-maintenance-fund-s.html&#34;&gt;report on the Perl 5 Core Maintenance Fund&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matsuno Tokuhiro announced &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.64p.org/entry/2013/01/21/134639&#34;&gt;plenv, a Pler installation management tool&lt;/a&gt;. Compare it to &lt;a href=&#34;http://perlbrew.pl/&#34;&gt;perlbrew&lt;/a&gt; and Ruby&amp;rsquo;s rbenv.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Perl 5 Porters announced &lt;a href=&#34;https://rt.perl.org/rt3//Public/Bug/Display.html?id=116491&#34;&gt;core modules scheduled for removal in Perl 5.20&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;VM Brasseur tackled the problem of recruiting new programmers to Perl in &lt;a href=&#34;http://anonymoushash.vmbrasseur.com/2013/01/22/improving-perls-new-programmer-outreach/&#34;&gt;Improving Perl&amp;rsquo;s New Programmer Outreach&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.perl.org/users/ovid/2013/01/testclassmoose-on-the-cpan.html&#34;&gt;Ovid announced the release of Test::Class::Moose&lt;/a&gt; to the CPAN. Since then, he&amp;rsquo;s expanded the combination of &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Test::Class&#34;&gt;Test::Class&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href=&#34;http://moose.perl.org/&#34;&gt;Moosey goodness&lt;/a&gt; to create the ultimate testing tool. See the &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.perl.org/users/ovid/2013/09/testclassmoose-introductory-video.html&#34;&gt;Test::Class::Moose introduction video&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dagolden.com/index.php/1838/goodbye-path-class-hello-path-tiny/&#34;&gt;David Golden announced Path::Tiny, the successor to Path::Class&lt;/a&gt;. If you&amp;rsquo;re still using &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/File::Spec&#34;&gt;File::Spec&lt;/a&gt;, try &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Path::Tiny&#34;&gt;Path::Tiny&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;february-2013&#34;&gt;February 2013&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.perl.org/users/vyacheslav_matjukhin/2013/02/play-perl-is-online.html&#34;&gt;Vyacheslav Matjukhin announced Play Perl&lt;/a&gt;. This is a public system for announcing and accepting quests to accomplish Perl-related tasks. Play Perl has become &lt;a href=&#34;http://questhub.io/&#34;&gt;Questhub&lt;/a&gt;, but it is still powered by Perl. Ruslan Zakirov quickly added &lt;a href=&#34;http://cubloid.blogspot.co.il/2013/02/my-play-perl-and-perl5-core-quests_21.html&#34;&gt;quests for Perl core development&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sawyer X and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://perldancer.org/&#34;&gt;Dancer&lt;/a&gt; team released Dancer2, the new version of the powerful Dancer micro web framework. Dancer 1 is still maintained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kartik Thakore and &lt;a href=&#34;http://yapgh.blogspot.ca/2013/03/sdl2-api-stabilization-and-new-work.html&#34;&gt;the Perl SDL team announced bindings to SDL2&lt;/a&gt;, the update to the cross-platform graphic, sound, and input libraries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perl pumpking &lt;a href=&#34;http://rjbs.manxome.org/rubric/entry/1986&#34;&gt;RJBS converted Email::Sender to Moo&lt;/a&gt; and saw tremendous test suite time savings. (See also the deprecation of &lt;code&gt;Any::Moose&lt;/code&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lists.scsys.co.uk/pipermail/dbix-class/2013-February/011109.html&#34;&gt;Peter Rabbitson announced a faster DBIx::Class&lt;/a&gt;, with many impressive speed improvements. The 0.08250 release in late April would prove to be the fastest stable release yet. (See &lt;a href=&#34;http://jjnapiorkowski.typepad.com/modern-perl/2013/05/perl-dbixclass-an-awesome-orm-now-with-super-speed.html&#34;&gt;John Napiorkowski&amp;rsquo;s post on the 20% speed improvements in the new DBIC release&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PAUSE administrator and Perl guru &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.perl.org/users/brian_d_foy/2013/02/mark-your-modules-as-adoptable-if-you-dont-want-them.html&#34;&gt;brian d foy reminded CPAN authors to set their modules free&lt;/a&gt; when the time has come to hand over maintenance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rob Hammond explained &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.perl.org/users/robhammond/2013/02/web-scraping-with-perl-phantomjs.html&#34;&gt;how to use Perl and PhantomJS to scrape the JavaScript web&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paul Fenwick wowed the crowd, as always, with his talk &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oZ5xTI1QRTA&#34;&gt;The Perl Renaissance&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://act.perl.org.il/ilpw2013/&#34;&gt;Israeli Perl Workshop&lt;/a&gt; took place in Tel Aviv, Israel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;march-2013&#34;&gt;March 2013&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://perlnews.org/2013/03/rehashing-flaw/&#34;&gt;A flaw in Perl&amp;rsquo;s rehashing mechanism&lt;/a&gt; (resizing hash tables when adding new keys) was corrected in the five most recent stable releases of Perl. Perl 5.18 would make hash key order slightly more random, exposing long-standing bugs in several programs. 5.18 also introduced &lt;a href=&#34;http://rjbs.manxome.org/rubric/entry/2016&#34;&gt;lexical subroutines&lt;/a&gt;, which will be very useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A project called &lt;a href=&#34;http://prepan.org/&#34;&gt;PrePA (footnote: /a) emerged. PrePAN is a place where you can discuss modules before you decide to upload them to the CPAN. In March 2013,&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.perl.org/users/kentaro/2013/03/joined-cpan-api-metacpan-team.html&#34;&gt;PrePAN joined the CPAN-API organization&lt;/a&gt;. (You may know CPAN-API better as &lt;a href=&#34;http://metacpan.org/&#34;&gt;MetaCPA (footnote: /a).&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Michael Schwern announced &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/schwern/perl5i/wiki/Quickstart-Guide&#34;&gt;a quick start guide for perl5i&lt;/a&gt;. perl5i is an experimental distribution of Perl which includes a lot of syntax-warping modules that may or may not influence core development in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;brian d foy experimented with &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.perl.org/users/brian_d_foy/2013/03/my-catincan-funded-cpan1-fastest-mirror-enhancement.html&#34;&gt;a small community-funded CPAN project&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neil Bowers began experimenting with &lt;a href=&#34;http://theperlhub.com/&#34;&gt;The Perl Hub&lt;/a&gt;, a sort of dashboard to the Perl community. It includes links to blog posts, CPAN reviews, talks, events, and quests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Giel Goudsmit wrote &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.booking.com/the-little-script-that-could.html&#34;&gt;a decade retrospective of Booking.com&lt;/a&gt;, the Perl powerhouse in the Netherlands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps drawing from Play Perl (or perhaps from his relentless research into psychology, motivation, and fun), Paul Fenwick announced &lt;a href=&#34;http://privacygeek.blogspot.com.au/2013/03/gamifiy-your-command-line-with-habitrpg.html&#34;&gt;a CLI tool for HabitRPG&lt;/a&gt;, a todo app in a fantasy setting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://pragmaticperl.com/&#34;&gt;Pragmatic Perl&lt;/a&gt;, a Russian web newsletter, published its first issue. The newsletter interviews Perl developers and the English translations of its interviews are often full of insights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://perltricks.com/&#34;&gt;Perl Tricks&lt;/a&gt; web site launched to promote Perl with short articles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://act.yapc.eu/gpw2013/&#34;&gt;German Perl Workshop&lt;/a&gt; took place in Berlin, Germany.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://act.perl-workshop.ch/spw2013/&#34;&gt;Swiss Perl Workshop&lt;/a&gt; took place in Bern, Switzerland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;april-2013&#34;&gt;April 2013&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perl.org&amp;rsquo;s Subversion hosting service ended. &lt;a href=&#34;http://log.perl.org/2013/03/svnperlorg-shutdown-in-one-month.html&#34;&gt;svn.perl.org shutdown announced on log.per.org&lt;/a&gt;. Github, Bitbucket, and other free DVCS hosting are great alternatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Best Practical updated &lt;a href=&#34;http://rt.cpan.org/&#34;&gt;rt.cpan.org&lt;/a&gt;, the bug tracker for CPAN and the Perl core, to RT 4. The &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.bestpractical.com/2013/04/rt-cpan-upgrade.html&#34;&gt;rt.cpan.org 4 upgrade announcement&lt;/a&gt; has more details about what this means for CPAN authors and Perl hackers. In September, Best Practical would announce &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.bestpractical.com/2013/10/rt-420-released.html&#34;&gt;the release of RT 4.2.0&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tim Bunce announced &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.timbunce.org/2013/04/08/nytprof-v5-flaming-precision/&#34;&gt;the release of Devel::NYTProf 5&lt;/a&gt;, which includes a flame graph in the profile. This is a great visualization of where your program spends its time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andy Lester and the ack developers announced &lt;a href=&#34;http://perlbuzz.com/2013/04/ack-20-has-been-released.html&#34;&gt;the release of ack 2.0&lt;/a&gt;. ack&amp;rsquo;s selling point is &amp;ldquo;better than grep&amp;rdquo;, and it certainly is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2013 Perl QA hackathon took place. David Golden summarized &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dagolden.com/index.php/2098/the-annotated-lancaster-consensus/&#34;&gt;the Lancaster Consensus&lt;/a&gt;, the latest guideline for toolchain support when managing CPAN distributions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fred Moyer announced &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.perl.org/users/phred/2013/04/mod-perl-208-has-been-released.html&#34;&gt;the release of mod_perl 2.08&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.osdc.tw/2013/&#34;&gt;Open Source Developers Conference Taiwan&lt;/a&gt; took place in Taipei, Taiwan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Daisuke Maki published &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.perl.org/users/lestrrat/2013/04/perl5-census-japan-2013.html&#34;&gt;results of the 2013 Perl 5 Census Japan&lt;/a&gt;. Perl in Japan looks very different from Perl in the US or EU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gabor Szabo linked to &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.perl.org/users/gabor_szabo/2013/05/pinto-tutorial-in-8-languages.html&#34;&gt;Pinto tutorials in multiple languages&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.perlworkshop.nl/nlpw2013/&#34;&gt;Dutch Perl Workshop&lt;/a&gt; took place in Arnhem, The Netherlands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://dcbpw.org/&#34;&gt;DC Baltimore Perl Workshop&lt;/a&gt; took place in Baltimore, Maryland, USA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;may-2013&#34;&gt;May 2013&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In sad news, CPAN developer AMORETTE—Hojung Yoon—passed away on May 8, 2013. South Korea and Perl lost a valued member of the community. &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/aer0/status/333229465293443072&#34;&gt;C.H. Kang posted a small tribute to Hojung Yoon on Twitter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Perl 5 Porters announced &lt;a href=&#34;http://perlnews.org/2013/05/perl-5-18-0-released/&#34;&gt;the release of Perl 5.18&lt;/a&gt;. This yearly release added a couple of nice new features, fixed a slew of bugs, updated some core modules, and updated plans to continue Perl&amp;rsquo;s evolution to 5.20 and beyond. See the &lt;a href=&#34;https://perldoc.perl.org/perl5180delta.html&#34;&gt;Perl 5.18 delta&lt;/a&gt; documentation for more details. CPAN developers had some work to do; see David Oswald&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.perl.org/users/david_oswald/2013/05/a-call-to-action-for-cpan-authors.html&#34;&gt;A call to action for CPAN authors&lt;/a&gt; about finding and fixing hash order bugs in library code as well as Mark Fowler&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.twoshortplanks.com/2013/05/20/5-18-hash-keys/&#34;&gt;explanation of hash key ordering changes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Mojolicious team started beating the drum about the upcoming Mojolicious 4.0 release. &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.perl.org/users/joel_berger/2013/05/mojolicious-40-is-coming-soon.html&#34;&gt;Joel Berger introduced some new features of Mojolicious 4.0&lt;/a&gt;. Mojolicious creator Sebastian Riedel provided the &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.kraih.com/post/50517069291/mojolicious-4-0-released-perl-real-time-web-framework&#34;&gt;Mojolicious 4.0 release announcement&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Bugzilla developers announced &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bugzilla.org/news/#release44&#34;&gt;the releases of Bugzilla 4.4 and 4.2.6&lt;/a&gt;. The code in this long-lived project keeps getting better and better as development continues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joel Berger also finished a TPF grant. His &lt;a href=&#34;http://news.perlfoundation.org/2013/05/alienbase-grant---report-9-fin.html&#34;&gt;report at the completion of the Alien::Base grant&lt;/a&gt; gives a retrospective of the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Toby Inkster continued making things smaller, faster, and easier to use in isolation. While his &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Moops&#34;&gt;Moops&lt;/a&gt; module is your editor&amp;rsquo;s favorite, his &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.perl.org/users/toby_inkster/2013/05/typetiny---not-just-for-attributes.html&#34;&gt;Type::Tiny constraint system&lt;/a&gt; has a lot of potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Timm Murray announced &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.perl.org/users/timm_murray/2013/05/announcing-uavpilot-v01.html&#34;&gt;Perl modules for controlling unmanned drones&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tokuhiro Matsuno received far too little attention for his work with &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Compiler::Lexer&#34;&gt;Compiler::Lexer&lt;/a&gt;. See his &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.64p.org/entry/2013/05/25/085607&#34;&gt;CLI for Compiler::Lexer&lt;/a&gt; for more details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;VM Brasseur and Jeffrey Thalhammer (the man who was approximately everywhere in Perl in 2013) announced &lt;a href=&#34;http://anonymoushash.vmbrasseur.com/2013/05/29/announcing-the-perl-companies-project/&#34;&gt;the Perl Companies Project&lt;/a&gt;, a single place to list all of the companies using Perl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Testing guru and frustrated economist Ovid explained &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.perl.org/users/ovid/2013/05/if-theres-a-shortage-of-programmers-why-arent-wages-up.html&#34;&gt;the lack of good developers and the surprising lack of rise in programmer wages&lt;/a&gt;. Programmers need to learn more practical math.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://lists.parrot.org/pipermail/parrot-members/Week-of-Mon-20130520/000069.html&#34;&gt;members of the Parrot Foundation voted to dissolve the foundation and let TPF take over&lt;/a&gt;. This puts the copyrights, governance, and other artifacts of the Parrot VM and its projects under the supervision of the Perl Foundation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://act.yapc.eu/plpw2013/&#34;&gt;Polish Perl Workshop 2013&lt;/a&gt; took place in Warsaw, Poland. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/user/polishperl/videos&#34;&gt;Videos of the Polish Perl Workshop 2013&lt;/a&gt; are available online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;june-2013&#34;&gt;June 2013&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stevan Little announced &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.perl.org/users/stevan_little/2013/06/once-more-unto-the-breach.html&#34;&gt;the resurrection of his efforts to add a proper MOP to Perl&lt;/a&gt;. The code progressed throughout the year, as did Peter Martini&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.yapcna.org/yn2013/talk/4556&#34;&gt;patch for proper function parameters in Perl&lt;/a&gt;. While neither one is yet suitable for either inclusion in the core or general deployment to production, their progress is heartening. In particular, &lt;a href=&#34;http://damien.krotkine.com/2013/09/17/p5-mop.html&#34;&gt;Damien Krotkine&amp;rsquo;s exploration of p5-mop as a user&lt;/a&gt; is a great example of what will soon be possible in Perl. (Stevan Little&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.perl.org/users/stevan_little/2013/09/on-porting-a-moose-module.html&#34;&gt;porting a Moose module to p5-mop&lt;/a&gt; is also interesting, if a little more esoteric.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://journeesperl.fr/fpw2013/&#34;&gt;French Perl Workshop 2013&lt;/a&gt; took place in Nancy, France.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.yapcna.org/yn2013/&#34;&gt;YAPC::NA 2013&lt;/a&gt; took place in Austin, Texas, USA. Brian Wisti gathered &lt;a href=&#34;http://randomgeekery.org/wp/2013/06/yapcna-2013-links-from-a-non-attendee/&#34;&gt;links to YAPC::NA 2013 slides and videos&lt;/a&gt;. Todd Rinaldo uploaded &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/yapcna&#34;&gt;YAPC::NA talks on YouTube&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aristotle Pagaltzis reflected on &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.perl.org/users/aristotle/2013/06/toolchain-decade.html&#34;&gt;a decade of Module::Build in the Perl core&lt;/a&gt;. Module::Build will likely leave the core by 5.22.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;july-2013&#34;&gt;July 2013&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fred Moyer announced &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.perl.org/users/phred/2013/07/the-state-of-soaplite---here-comes-10.html&#34;&gt;the imminent release of SOAP::Lite 1.0&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chad Granum released &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.perl.org/users/chad_exodist_granum/2013/07/fennec-v2x---testing-made-better.html&#34;&gt;Fennec v2, an advanced testing system for Perl&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;http://perlmaven.com/chad-granum&#34;&gt;Perl Maven interviewed Granum about Fennec&lt;/a&gt;. Between his work and Ovid&amp;rsquo;s on Moose-based testing, the time may be ripe for a new testing book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jessy Shy published &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.perl.org/users/jesse_shy/2013/07/announce-classmithcom.html&#34;&gt;an announcement about Classsmith.com&lt;/a&gt;, an app for home schoolers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tatsuhiko Miyagawa&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Carton&#34;&gt;Carton&lt;/a&gt; tool for managing CPAN dependencies reached 1.0 status. Miyagawa published his &lt;a href=&#34;https://speakerdeck.com/miyagawa/carton-1-dot-0-at-oscon-2013&#34;&gt;Carton slides from OSCON 2013&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://weblog.bulknews.net/post/57356232719/carton-1-0-is-released&#34;&gt;the Carton 1.0 release announcement&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The music fan and hacker known as Barbie addressed &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.cpantesters.org/diary/164&#34;&gt;frequently asked questions about CPANTS and CPAN Testers&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brian Medley announced &lt;a href=&#34;http://closebargains.com/&#34;&gt;CloseBargains.com&lt;/a&gt;, a startup site written in Perl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://patch.pm/p0/&#34;&gt;patch -p0 hackathon&lt;/a&gt; took place in Paris, France.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;august-2013&#34;&gt;August 2013&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perl 5.18.1 was released.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yuki Kimoto published the &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.perl.org/users/yuki_kimoto/2013/08/released-gitprep-12---add-import-repositories-feature-blame-feature.html&#34;&gt;release announcement of GitPrep 1.2&lt;/a&gt;, a free software replacement for Github.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Perl Foundation accepted &lt;a href=&#34;http://news.perlfoundation.org/2013/08/improving-perl-5-grant-extende-3.html&#34;&gt;Nicholas Clark&amp;rsquo;s grant to improve the Perl core&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://act.yapc.eu/ye2013/&#34;&gt;YAPC::EU 2013&lt;/a&gt; took place in Kiev, Ukraine. &lt;a href=&#34;http://act.yapc.eu/ye2013/slides&#34;&gt;All of the slides of YAPC::EU 2013 are available online&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://conference.perlchina.org/bjpw2013/&#34;&gt;Beijing Perl Workshop 2013&lt;/a&gt; took place in Beijing, China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;september-2013&#34;&gt;September 2013&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Toby Inkster announced &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.perl.org/users/toby_inkster/2013/09/-welcome-to-the-first.html&#34;&gt;the inagural monthly Planet Moose roundup&lt;/a&gt; of the news in the Moose/Mouse/Moo/Mo/M/whatever worlds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://brainturk.com/&#34;&gt;Brainturk.com&lt;/a&gt; went live with a new version. Of course it uses Perl and the CPAN. The &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.perl.org/users/kiran/2013/09/brainturkcom-is-live.html&#34;&gt;rainturk release announcement&lt;/a&gt; included a sizable discount for Perl community members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://helios.logicalhelion.org/&#34;&gt;Helios&lt;/a&gt; distributed job processing system &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.perl.org/users/lajandy/2013/09/helios-261-released.html&#34;&gt;announced the Helios 2.61 release&lt;/a&gt;. This software is available from the CPAN, of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dave Cross released &lt;a href=&#34;http://perlhacks.com/2013/09/perl-search-revisited/&#34;&gt;a new version of his Perl-specific search engine&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://yapcasia.org/2013/&#34;&gt;YAPC::Asia 2013&lt;/a&gt; took place in Tokyo, Japan. The &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.perl.org/users/lestrrat/2013/09/a-lookback-of-yapcasia-tokyo-2013.html&#34;&gt;YAPC::Asia 2013 recap&lt;/a&gt; is worth reading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;october-2013&#34;&gt;October 2013&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tom Christiansen and brian d foy spent time &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.perl.org/users/brian_d_foy/2013/10/perlcritic-for-the-camel.html&#34;&gt;working on Perl::Critic policies based on recommendations from the 4th edition of Programming Perl&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://perltv.org/&#34;&gt;Perl TV&lt;/a&gt; published &lt;a href=&#34;http://perltv.org/v/why-is-perl-like-a-human-language&#34;&gt;Larry Wall&amp;rsquo;s talk on Why Perl Is Like a Human Language&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joel Berger announced &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.perl.org/users/joel_berger/2013/10/pdl-2007-released.html&#34;&gt;the release of PDL 2.007&lt;/a&gt;. This release adds 64-bit support. David Mertens gave &lt;a href=&#34;http://perltv.org/v/introduction-to-the-perl-data-language&#34;&gt;an introduction to the Perl Data Language&lt;/a&gt; and PerlTV posted it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shawn Moore mentored the incredible Upasana Shukla in &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.perl.org/users/upasana/2013/10/yay-moose-is-free-from-stringy-exceptions.html&#34;&gt;removing string exceptions from Moose&lt;/a&gt;. This is a great achievement. Shawn&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://sartak.org/2013/10/structured-exceptions-in-moose-mentorship.html&#34;&gt;retrospective of the structured exceptions project&lt;/a&gt; is also worth reading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The DadaMail Project (a modern mailing list manager written in Perl and released under the GNU GPL) &lt;a href=&#34;http://dadamailproject.com/cgi-bin/dada/mail.cgi/archive/dada_announce/20131001183416/&#34;&gt;released DadaMail 6.7.0&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The TWiki project announced the &lt;a href=&#34;http://twiki.org/cgi-bin/view/Blog/BlogEntry201310x1&#34;&gt;TWiki 6.0.0 release&lt;/a&gt;. This is a venerable Perl project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://act.osdc.fr/osdc2013fr/&#34;&gt;Open Source Development Conference France 2013&lt;/a&gt; took place in Paris, France.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://osdc.org.nz/&#34;&gt;Open Source Developers Conference New Zealand&lt;/a&gt; took place in Auckland, New Zealand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://pghpw.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Perl Workshop&lt;/a&gt; 2013 took place in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, USA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://reneeb-perlblog.blogspot.hu/2013/09/frankfurter-perl-community-workshop-2013.html&#34;&gt;Perl Community Workshop 2013&lt;/a&gt; took place in Frankfurt, Germany.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://workshop.perl.pt/ptpw2013/&#34;&gt;Portugese Perl Workshop 2013&lt;/a&gt; took place in Lisbon, Portugal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;november-2013&#34;&gt;November 2013&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jeffrey Thalhammer (the creator of &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Perl::Critic&#34;&gt;Perl::Critic&lt;/a&gt; launched a public beta of his &lt;a href=&#34;http://stratopan.com/&#34;&gt;Stratopan&lt;/a&gt; service. Stratopan lets you freeze a stack of CPAN modules as development and deployment targets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John Napiorkowski announced &lt;a href=&#34;http://jjnapiorkowski.typepad.com/modern-perl/2013/11/perl-catalyst-hamburg-is-now-stable-version-590050-is-now-on-cpan.html&#34;&gt;the Catalyst 5.90050 stable release&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team behind Padre, a Perl IDE, announced &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.perl.org/users/peter_lavender/2013/11/padre-100-has-been-released.html&#34;&gt;the release of Padre 1.0&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foswiki announced &lt;a href=&#34;http://foswiki.org/Download/FoswikiRelease01x01x09&#34;&gt;the release of Foswiki 1.1.9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tudor Constantin announced &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.builtinperl.com/&#34;&gt;Built in Perl&lt;/a&gt;, a web site listing companies that rely on Perl. Add your own company!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peteris Krumins announced that &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.catonmat.net/blog/perl-one-liners-no-starch-press/&#34;&gt;No Starch Press has published Perl One-Liners&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perl TV posted Larry Wall&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://perltv.org/v/5-programming-languages-everyone-should-know&#34;&gt;5 Programming Languages Everyone Should Know&lt;/a&gt; video.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Core hacker Yves Orton posted &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.booking.com/hardening-perls-hash-function.html&#34;&gt;a technical explanation of the hash security changes in Perl&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://2013.yapcbrasil.org.br/&#34;&gt;YAPC::Brazil 2013&lt;/a&gt; took place in Curitiba, Brazil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://act.useperl.at/apw2013/&#34;&gt;Austrian Perl Workshop 2013&lt;/a&gt; took place in Salzburg, Austria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://act.yapc.eu/npw2013/&#34;&gt;Nordic Perl Workshop 2013&lt;/a&gt; took place in Copenhagen, Denmark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://act.yapc.eu/lpw2013/&#34;&gt;London Perl Workshop 2013&lt;/a&gt; took place in London, UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;december-2013&#34;&gt;December 2013&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;December is Advent season in the Perl world. That means lots of Advent calendars, with a post a day for 24 (or 25) days. Some of these calendars include the &lt;a href=&#34;http://perladvent.org/2013/&#34;&gt;Perl Advent calendar&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.catalystframework.org/calendar/&#34;&gt;Catalyst Advent calendar&lt;/a&gt;, and (new this year) the &lt;a href=&#34;http://leonerds-code.blogspot.com/2013/12/futures-advent-day-1.html&#34;&gt;Futures Advent calendar&lt;/a&gt;. Even though Advent season is over, that&amp;rsquo;s still enough articles to fill the rest of the month with good reading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Dancer developers sadly couldn&amp;rsquo;t get their Advent calendar going (for happy, family reasons, so they get a pass this year), but they did announce &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.perl.org/users/sawyer_x/2013/12/new-dancer-2-release-011.html&#34;&gt;the Dancer 2 0.11 release&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.modernperlbooks.com/mt/2013/12/perl-is-26-today.html&#34;&gt;Perl turned 26 years old.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;brian d foy announced the &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.perl.org/users/brian_d_foy/2013/12/the-2013-white-camels.html&#34;&gt;2013 White Camel winners&lt;/a&gt;. Congratulations to Thaigo Rondon, Fred Moyer, and Dijkmat&amp;rsquo;s Wendy and Liz. All of these winners have deserved this award for many years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Perl Foundation accepted &lt;a href=&#34;http://news.perlfoundation.org/2013/09/grant-application-maintaining-1.html&#34;&gt;Dave Mitchell&amp;rsquo;s grant to maintain the Perl core&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steffen Mueller announced &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.perl.org/users/steffen_mueller/2013/12/sereal-v2-finally-released-as-stable.html&#34;&gt;the release of Sereal v2&lt;/a&gt;. Sereal is a serialization mechanism for data that&amp;rsquo;s much faster than Data::Dumper and Storable, not to mention much safer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neil Bowers compiled &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.perl.org/users/neilb/2014/01/the-cpan-report-2013.html&#34;&gt;The CPAN Report 2013&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://patch.pm/p1/&#34;&gt;patch -p1&lt;/a&gt; took place in Paris, France.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://event.yapcrussia.org/saintperl5/&#34;&gt;Saint Perl 2013 workshop&lt;/a&gt; took place in Saint Petersburg, Russia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Perl NOC (Ask and Robert) announced &lt;a href=&#34;http://log.perl.org/2013/12/2013-year-end-maintenance.html&#34;&gt;year end maintenance for perl.org services&lt;/a&gt;. Usually you don&amp;rsquo;t notice when they do their (unsung and impressive) work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s it for a great year in Perl!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Enable Backtraces with Carp::Always (Modern Perl Tips)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/pub/2013/10/enable-backtraces-with-carpalways-modern-perl-tips.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2013 06:00:01 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/pub/2013/10/enable-backtraces-with-carpalways-modern-perl-tips.html/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Suppose you&amp;rsquo;re working on a large application in Perl. Your code is in multiple files with multiple packages, and you&amp;rsquo;ve built your application in layers. You have a data storage layer, a framework to manage control flow, a layer for business rules, and at least one form of user interface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine someone discovers a bug. When a user attempts to log in but mistypes her email address—using a comma instead of dot, for example—the web site crashes. She sees a nearly empty &amp;ldquo;500 Server Error&amp;rdquo; page instead of the attractive error pages the designer created and the logs show only that &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; went wrong. Your custom error handler didn&amp;rsquo;t even get called.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If that sounds familiar, you may have had a week like I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back when Perl and Java seemed like two poles of the professional software development axis, we Perl programmers often teased Java programmers about Java&amp;rsquo;s propensity to emit page long backtraces whenever anything somewhere went wrong. Over a decade later, my views have grown to include a little more nuance. The problem isn&amp;rsquo;t backtraces &lt;em&gt;per se&lt;/em&gt;; the problem is Java&amp;rsquo;s call stacks are so deep and the stack traces so verbose that real problems may be obscured in irrelevant details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perl code sometimes goes too far the other direction. It makes sense to use &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Carp&#34;&gt;Carp&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;carp()&lt;/code&gt; to warn about the dubious use of code in libraries from the point of view of the caller, but modern Perl applications tend to grow beyond a single program calling to a few libraries. Our libraries depend on other libraries and something can go wrong in one layer but only produce an error in another layer. Sometimes it&amp;rsquo;s nice to have the option to enable verbose backtraces for warnings and errors only temporarily, during debugging, without modifying any of your code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s what &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Carp::Always&#34;&gt;Carp::Always&lt;/a&gt; does. If you can reproduce the error in a test case (whether a formal test script or a small, standalone program), launch the program with the command line option &lt;code&gt;-MCarp::Always&lt;/code&gt; to get a verbose backtrace on warnings or errors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(The &lt;code&gt;-M&lt;/code&gt; flag tells &lt;code&gt;perl&lt;/code&gt; to load a named module, just as if you&amp;rsquo;d written &lt;code&gt;use Carp::Always;&lt;/code&gt; in your program.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For bonus debugging powers, I like to use command lines of the form:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ perl -MCarp::Always my_test_case.pl 2&amp;gt; log; less log; rm log
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip; so that the backtrace goes to the &lt;code&gt;less&lt;/code&gt; pager, where I can scroll up and down and search. When I quit the pager, the temporary file goes away so it doesn&amp;rsquo;t clutter up my directory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By tracking all control flow to the point of the error, I found the problem more quickly. You can, of course, solve this problem in multiple ways, including attaching a debugger to a running process, but when that&amp;rsquo;s not an option and when you can reproduce the exception or warning in a small test file, forcing a full backtrace can be very helpful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;chromatic is the author of &lt;a href=&#34;http://modernperlbooks.com/books/modern_perl/&#34;&gt;Modern Perl: the book&lt;/a&gt;. His non-programming hobbies include gradually curating a list of &lt;a href=&#34;https://blenderrecipereviews.com/recipes/smoothies/how-to-make-a-smoothie&#34;&gt;smoothie&lt;/a&gt; recipes and &lt;a href=&#34;https://trendshare.org/how-to-invest/&#34;&gt;value investing&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lexing and Parsing Continued</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/pub/2013/01/lexing-and-parsing-continued.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Jan 2013 18:50:54 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/pub/2013/01/lexing-and-parsing-continued.html/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;This article is the second part of a series which started with &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/pub/2012/10/an-overview-of-lexing-and-parsing.html&#34;&gt;An Overview of Lexing and Parsing&lt;/a&gt;. That article aimed to discuss lexing and parsing in general terms, while trying to minimize the amount on how to actually use Marpa::R2 to do the work. In the end, however, it did have quite a few specifics. This article has yet more detail with regard to working with both a lexer and a parser. BTW, Marpa&amp;rsquo;s blog&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(For more information, see the Marpa blog or download the example files for this article.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;brief-recap-the-two-grammars&#34;&gt;Brief Recap: The Two Grammars&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Article 1 defined the first sub-grammar as the one which identifies tokens and the second sub-grammar as the one which specifies which combinations of tokens are legal within the target language. As I use these terms, the lexer implements the first sub-grammar and the parser implements the second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;some-context&#34;&gt;Some Context&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider this image:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://savage.net.au/Ron/html/graphviz2.marpa/teamwork.svg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s actually a copy of the image of a manual page for &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Graph::Easy&#34;&gt;Graph::Easy&lt;/a&gt;. Note: My module &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Graph::Easy::Marpa&#34;&gt;Graph::Easy::Marpa&lt;/a&gt; is a complete re-write of &lt;code&gt;Graph::Easy&lt;/code&gt;. After I offered to take over maintenance of the latter, I found the code so complex I literally couldn&amp;rsquo;t understand any of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three ways (of interest to us) to specify the contents of this image:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As a Perl program using the &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/GraphViz2&#34;&gt;GraphViz2&lt;/a&gt; module&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As a Graphviz DOT file written in a little language&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As a DOT file&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article is about using &lt;code&gt;GraphViz2::Marpa&lt;/code&gt; to parse DOT files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course the Graphviz package itself provides a set of programs which parse DOT files in order to render them into many different formats. Why then would someone write a new parser for DOT? One reason is to practice your Marpa skills. Another is, perhaps, to write an on-line editor for Graphviz files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alternately you might provide add-on services to the Graphviz package. For instance, some users might want to find all clusters of nodes, where a cluster is a set of nodes connected to each other, but not connected to any nodes outside the cluster. Yet other uses might want to find all paths of a given length emanating from a given node.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I myself have written algorithms which provide these last two features. See the module &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/GraphViz2::Marpa::PathUtils&#34;&gt;GraphViz2::Marpa::PathUtils&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://savage.net.au/Perl-modules/html/graphviz2.pathutils/index.html&#34;&gt;PathUtils demo page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But back to using &lt;code&gt;Marpa::R2&lt;/code&gt; from within &lt;code&gt;GraphViz2::Marpa&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;scripts-for-testing&#34;&gt;Scripts for Testing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The code being developed obviously needs to be tested thoroughly, because any such little language has many ways to get things right and a horrendously large number of ways to get things slightly wrong, or worse. Luckily, because graphs specified in DOT can be very brief, it&amp;rsquo;s a simple matter to make up many samples. Further, other more complex samples can be copied from the Graphviz distro&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;graphs/directed/&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;graphs/undirected/&lt;/em&gt; directories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;GraphViz2::Marpa&lt;/code&gt; distro I developed includes with 86 &lt;em&gt;data/*.gv&lt;/em&gt; (input) files and the 79 corresponding &lt;em&gt;data/*.lex&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;data/*.parse&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;data/*.rend&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;html/*.svg&lt;/em&gt; (output) files. The missing files are due to deliberate errors in the input files, so they do not have output files. The distribution also includes obvious scripts such as &lt;em&gt;lex.pl&lt;/em&gt; (lex a file), &lt;em&gt;parse.pl&lt;/em&gt; (parse a lexed file), rend.pl (render a parsed file back into DOT), and one named vaguely after the package, &lt;em&gt;g2m.pl&lt;/em&gt;, which runs the lexer and the parser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why a rend.pl? If the code &lt;em&gt;can&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em&gt; reconstruct the input DOT file, something got lost in translation&amp;hellip;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The distribution also includes scripts which operate on a set of files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;data/*.gv&lt;/em&gt; -&amp;gt; &lt;em&gt;dot2lex.pl&lt;/em&gt; -&amp;gt; runs &lt;em&gt;lex.pl&lt;/em&gt; once per file -&amp;gt; &lt;em&gt;data/*.lex&lt;/em&gt; (CSV files).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;data/*.lex&lt;/em&gt; -&amp;gt; &lt;em&gt;lex2parse.pl&lt;/em&gt; -&amp;gt; runs &lt;em&gt;parse.pl&lt;/em&gt; once per file -&amp;gt; &lt;em&gt;data/*.parse&lt;/em&gt; (CSV files).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;data/*.parse&lt;/em&gt; -&amp;gt; &lt;em&gt;parse2rend.pl&lt;/em&gt; -&amp;gt; runs &lt;em&gt;rend.pl&lt;/em&gt; once per file -&amp;gt; &lt;em&gt;data/*.rend&lt;/em&gt; (dot files).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;data/*.rend&lt;/em&gt; -&amp;gt; &lt;em&gt;rend2svg.pl&lt;/em&gt; -&amp;gt; &lt;em&gt;html/*.svg&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, &lt;em&gt;generate.demo.pl&lt;/em&gt; creates &lt;a href=&#34;http://savage.net.au/Perl-modules/html/graphviz2.marpa/&#34;&gt;the GraphViz2 Marpa demo page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Normal users will use &lt;em&gt;g2m.pl&lt;/em&gt; exclusively. The other scripts help developers with testing. See the &lt;a href=&#34;http://savage.net.au/Perl-modules/html/GraphViz2/Marpa.html#Scripts&#34;&gt;GraphViz2 Marpa scripts documentation&lt;/a&gt; for more information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;some-modules&#34;&gt;Some Modules&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/GraphViz2:Marpa::Lexer::DFA&#34;&gt;GraphViz2::Marpa::Lexer::DFA&lt;/a&gt; is a wrapper around &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Set::FA::Element&#34;&gt;Set::FA::Element&lt;/a&gt;. It has various tasks to do:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Process the State Transition Table (STT)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Transform the STT from the input form (spreadsheet/CSV file) into what Set::FA::Element expects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set up the logger&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provide the code for all the functions which handle enter-state and exit-state events&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run the DFA&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Check the result of that run&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is some sample data which ships with &lt;code&gt;GraphViz2::Marpa&lt;/code&gt;, formatted for maximum clarity:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A DOT file, &lt;em&gt;data/27.gv&lt;/em&gt;, which is input to the lexer:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A token file, &lt;em&gt;data/27.lex&lt;/em&gt;, which is output from the lexer:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see the details on &lt;a href=&#34;http://savage.net.au/Perl-modules/html/graphviz2.marpa/&#34;&gt;the GraphViz2 Marpa demo page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;some-notes-on-the-stt&#34;&gt;Some Notes on the STT&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, note that the code allows whole-line comments (matching &lt;code&gt;m!^(?:#|//)!&lt;/code&gt;. These lines are discarded when the input file is read, and so do not appear in the STT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;working-with-an-incomplete-bnf&#34;&gt;Working With An Incomplete BNF&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suppose you&amp;rsquo;ve gone to all of the work to find or create a BNF (&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Backus%E2%80%93Naur_Form&#34;&gt;Backus-Naur Form&lt;/a&gt;) grammar for your input language. You might encounter the situation where you can use BNF to specify your language in general, but not precisely in every situation. DOT is one offender.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DOT IDs can be surrounded by double-quotes, and in some case &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; be surrounded by double-quotes. To be more specific, if we regard an attribute declaration to be of the form &lt;code&gt;key=value&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;em&gt;both&lt;/em&gt; the key and the value can be embedded in double-quotes, and sometimes the value &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even worse, IDs can be attributes. For instance, you might want your font color to be green. That appears to be simple, but note: attributes &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; be attached to some component of the graph, something like &lt;code&gt;node_27_1 [fontcolor = green]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the pain. In DOT, the &lt;em&gt;thing&lt;/em&gt; to which the attribute belongs &lt;em&gt;may be omitted&lt;/em&gt; as implied. That is, the name of the thing&amp;rsquo;s owner is &lt;em&gt;optional&lt;/em&gt;. For instance, you might want a graph which is six inches square. Here&amp;rsquo;s how you can specify that requirement:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;graph [size = &amp;quot;6,6&amp;quot;]&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;[size = &amp;quot;6,6&amp;quot;]&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;size = &amp;quot;6,6&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But wait, there&amp;rsquo;s more! The &lt;em&gt;value&lt;/em&gt; of the attribute can be omitted, if it&amp;rsquo;s true. Hence the distro, and the demo page, have a set of tests, called &lt;em&gt;data/42.*.gv&lt;/em&gt;, which test that feature of the code. Grrrr.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this means is that when the terminator of the attribute declaration (in the input stream) is detected, and we switch states from &lt;code&gt;within-attribute&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;after-attribute&lt;/code&gt;, the code which emits output from the lexer has to have some knowledge of what the hell is going on, so that it can pretend it received the first of these three forms even if it received the second or third form. It &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; output &lt;code&gt;graph&lt;/code&gt; (the graph as a whole) as the owner of the attribute in question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you&amp;rsquo;ve seen, any attribute declaration can contain a set of attribute &lt;code&gt;key=value&lt;/code&gt; pairs as in &lt;code&gt;node_27_2 [ color = green fontcolor = red ]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can&amp;rsquo;t solve this with regexps, unless you have amazing superpowers and don&amp;rsquo;t care if anyone else can maintain your code. Instead, be prepared to add code in two places:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At switch of state&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After all input has been parsed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;understanding-the-state-transition-table&#34;&gt;Understanding the State Transition Table&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I included this diagram in the first article:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;             DOT&#39;s Grammar
                  |
                  V
        ---------------------
        |                   |
     strict                 |
        |                   |
        ---------------------
                  |
                  V
        ---------------------
        |                   |
     digraph     or       graph
        |                   |
        ---------------------
                  |
                  V
        ---------------------
        |                   |
       $id                  |
        |                   |
        ---------------------
                  |
                  V
                {...}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A dot file starts with an optional &lt;code&gt;strict&lt;/code&gt;, followed by either &lt;code&gt;graph&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;digraph&lt;/code&gt;. (Here &lt;code&gt;di&lt;/code&gt; stands for directed, meaning edges between nodes have arrowheads on them. Yes, there are many attributes which can be attached to edges. See &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.graphviz.org/content/attrs&#34;&gt;http://www.graphviz.org/content/attrs&lt;/a&gt; and look for an &lt;code&gt;E&lt;/code&gt; (edge) in the second column of the table of attribute names).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;/(di|)graph/&lt;/code&gt; is in turn followed by an optional ID.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;line-one&#34;&gt;Line One&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the first non-heading line of the STT, you can see how I ended up with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A start state flag =&amp;gt; &lt;code&gt;Yes&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An accept flag =&amp;gt; &lt;code&gt;&#39;&#39;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A state name =&amp;gt; &lt;code&gt;initial&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An event =&amp;gt; &lt;code&gt;strict&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A next state =&amp;gt; &lt;code&gt;graph&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An entry function =&amp;gt; &lt;code&gt;&#39;&#39;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An exit function =&amp;gt; &lt;code&gt;save_prefix&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A regexp =&amp;gt; &lt;code&gt;(?:&amp;quot;[^&amp;quot;]*&amp;quot;|&amp;lt;\s*&amp;lt;.*?&lt;/code&gt;\s*&amp;gt;|[a-zA-Z_][a-zA-Z_0-9]*|-?(?:\.[0-9]+|[0-9]+(?:\.[0-9])*))&amp;gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An interpretation =&amp;gt; &lt;code&gt;ID&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;line-two&#34;&gt;Line Two&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The event in the second line, &lt;code&gt;/(?:graph|digraph)/&lt;/code&gt;, indicates what to do if the &lt;code&gt;strict&lt;/code&gt; is absent from the input stream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To clarify this point, recall that the DFA matches entries in the Event column one at a time, from the first listed against the name of the state&amp;ndash;here, &lt;code&gt;/(?:strict)/&lt;/code&gt;&amp;ndash;down to the last for the given state&amp;ndash;here, &lt;code&gt;/(?:\s+)/&lt;/code&gt;. The first regexp to match wins, in that the first regexp to match will triggersthe &lt;em&gt;exit&lt;/em&gt; state logic and that its entry in the Next column specifies the next state to enter, which in turn specifies the (next) state&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;entry&lt;/em&gt; function to call, if any.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If &lt;code&gt;strict&lt;/code&gt; is not at the head of the input stream, and it can definitely be absent, as is seen in the above diagram, this regexp&amp;ndash;&lt;code&gt;/(?:graph|digraph)/&lt;/code&gt;&amp;ndash;is the next one tested by the DFA&amp;rsquo;s logic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;line-three&#34;&gt;Line Three&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hard-to-read regexp &lt;code&gt;\/\*.*\*\/&lt;/code&gt; says to skip C-language-style multi-line (&lt;code&gt;/* ... */&lt;/code&gt;) comments. The skip takes place because the Next state is &lt;code&gt;initial&lt;/code&gt;, the current state. In other words, discard any text at the head of the input stream which this regexp will gobble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why does it get discarded? That&amp;rsquo;s the way &lt;code&gt;Set::FA::Element&lt;/code&gt; operates. Looping &lt;em&gt;within&lt;/em&gt; a state does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; trigger the exit-state and enter-state functions, and so there is no opportunity to stockpile the matched text. That&amp;rsquo;s good in this case. There&amp;rsquo;s no reason to save it, because it&amp;rsquo;s a comment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think about the implications for a moment. Once the code has discarded a comment (or anything else), you can never recreate the verbatim input stream from the stockpiled text. Hence you should only discard something once you fully understand the consequences. If you&amp;rsquo;re parsing code to execute it (whatever that means), fine. If you&amp;rsquo;re writing a pretty printer or indenter, you cannot discard comments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, we can say this regexp is used often, meaning we accept such comments at many places in the input stream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;line-four&#34;&gt;Line Four&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The regexp &lt;code&gt;\s+&lt;/code&gt; says to skip spaces (in front of or between interesting tokens). As with the previous line, we skip to the very same state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This state has four regexps attached to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;more-states&#34;&gt;More States&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Re-examining the STT shows two introductory states, for input with and without a (leading) &lt;code&gt;strict&lt;/code&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ve called these states by the arbitrary names &lt;code&gt;initial&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;graph&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the initial &lt;code&gt;strict&lt;/code&gt; is present, state &lt;code&gt;initial&lt;/code&gt; handles it (in the exit function) and jumps to state &lt;code&gt;graph&lt;/code&gt; to handle what comes next. If, however, &lt;code&gt;strict&lt;/code&gt; is absent, state &lt;code&gt;initial&lt;/code&gt; still handles the input, but then jumps to state &lt;code&gt;graph_id&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A (repeated) word of warning about &lt;code&gt;Set::FA::Element&lt;/code&gt;. A loop &lt;em&gt;within&lt;/em&gt; a state does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; trigger the exit-state and enter-state functions. Sometimes this can actually be rather unfortunate. You can see elsewhere in the STT where I have had to use pairs of almost-identically named states (such as &lt;code&gt;statement_list_1&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;statement_list_2&lt;/code&gt;), and designed the logic to rock the STT back and forth between them, just to allow the state machine to gobble up certain input sequences. You may have to use this technique yourself. Be aware of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proceeding in this fashion, driven by the BNF of the input language, eventually you can construct the whole STT. Each time a new enter-state or exit-state function is needed, write the code, then run a small demo to test it. There is no substitute for that testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-graph-state&#34;&gt;The &lt;code&gt;graph&lt;/code&gt; State&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You reach this state simply by the absence of a leading &lt;code&gt;strict&lt;/code&gt; in the input stream. Apart from not bothering to cater for comments (as did the &lt;code&gt;initial&lt;/code&gt; state), this state is really the same as the &lt;code&gt;initial&lt;/code&gt; state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few paragraphs back I warned about a feature designed into Set::FA::Element, looping within a state. That fact is why the &lt;code&gt;graph&lt;/code&gt; state exists. If the &lt;code&gt;initial&lt;/code&gt; state could have looped to itself upon detecting &lt;code&gt;strict&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; executed the exit or entry functions, there would be no need for the &lt;code&gt;graph&lt;/code&gt; state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-graph-id-state&#34;&gt;The &lt;code&gt;graph_id&lt;/code&gt; State&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, look for an optional graph id, at the current head of the input stream (because anything which matched previously is gone).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the first use of a formula: Cell H2 contains &lt;code&gt;(?:&amp;quot;[^&amp;quot;]*&amp;quot;|&amp;lt;[^&amp;gt;]*&amp;gt;|[a-zA-Z_][a-zA-Z_0-9]*|-?(?:\.[0-9]+|[0-9]+(?:\.[0-9])*))&lt;/code&gt;. This accepts a double-quoted ID, or an ID quoted with &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;, or an alphanumeric (but not starting with a digit) ID, or a number.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the code sees such a token, it jumps to the &lt;code&gt;open_brace&lt;/code&gt; state, meaning the very next non-whitespace character had better (barring comments) be a &lt;code&gt;{&lt;/code&gt;, or there&amp;rsquo;s an error, so the code will die. Otherwise, it accepts &lt;code&gt;{&lt;/code&gt; without an ID and jumps to the &lt;code&gt;statement_list_1&lt;/code&gt; state, or discards comments and spaces by looping within the &lt;code&gt;graph_id&lt;/code&gt; state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-remaining-states&#34;&gt;The Remaining States&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What follows in the STT gets complex, but in reality is more of the same. Several things should be clear by now:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The development of the STT is iterative&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need lots of tiny but different test data files, to test these steps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need quite a lot of patience, which, unfortunately, can&amp;rsquo;t be downloaded from the internet&amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;lexer-actions-callbacks&#34;&gt;Lexer Actions (Callbacks)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matching something with a DFA only makes sense if you can capture the matched text for processing. Hence the use of state-exit and state-entry callback functions. In these functions, you must decide what text to output for each recognized input token.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help with this, I use a method called &lt;code&gt;items()&lt;/code&gt;, accessed in each function via &lt;code&gt;$myself&lt;/code&gt;. This method manages an stack (array) of items of type &lt;code&gt;Set::Array&lt;/code&gt;. Each element in this array is a hashref:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;    {
        count =&amp;gt; $integer, # 1 .. N.
        name  =&amp;gt; &#39;&#39;,       # Unused.
        type  =&amp;gt; $string,  # The type of the token.
        value =&amp;gt; $value,   # The value from the input stream.
    }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever a token is recognized, push a new item onto the stack. The value of the &lt;code&gt;type&lt;/code&gt; string is the result of the DFA&amp;rsquo;s work identifying the token. This identification process uses the first of the two sub-grammars mentioned in the first article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-long-exit-state-function&#34;&gt;A long Exit-state Function&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;save_prefix&lt;/code&gt; function looks like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;    # Warning: This is a function (i.e. not a method).

    sub save_prefix
    {
        my($dfa)   = @_;
        my($match) = trim($dfa -&amp;gt; match);

        # Upon each call, $match will be 1 of:
        # * strict.
        # * digraph.
        # * graph.

        # Note: Because this is a function, $myself is a global alias to $self.

        $myself -&amp;gt; log(debug =&amp;gt; &amp;quot;save_prefix($match)&amp;quot;);

        # Input     =&amp;gt; Output (a new item, i.e. a hashref):
        # o strict  =&amp;gt; {name =&amp;gt; strict,  value =&amp;gt; yes}.
        # o digraph =&amp;gt; {name =&amp;gt; digraph, value =&amp;gt; yes}.
        # o graph   =&amp;gt; {name =&amp;gt; digraph, value =&amp;gt; no}.

        if ($match eq &#39;strict&#39;)
        {
            $myself -&amp;gt; new_item($match, &#39;yes&#39;);
        }
        else
        {
            # If the first token is &#39;(di)graph&#39; (i.e. there was no &#39;strict&#39;),
            # jam a &#39;strict&#39; into the output stream.

            if ($myself -&amp;gt; items -&amp;gt; length == 0) # Output stream is empty.
            {
                $myself -&amp;gt; new_item(&#39;strict&#39;, &#39;no&#39;);
            }

            $myself -&amp;gt; new_item(&#39;digraph&#39;, $match eq &#39;digraph&#39; ? &#39;yes&#39; : &#39;no&#39;);
        }

    } # End of save_prefix.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-tiny-exit-state-function&#34;&gt;A tiny Exit-state Function&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s one of the shorter exit functions, attached in the STT to the &lt;code&gt;open_brace&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;start_statement&lt;/code&gt; states:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;    sub start_statements
    {
        my($dfa) = @_;

        $myself -&amp;gt; new_item(&#39;open_brace&#39;, $myself -&amp;gt; increment_brace_count);

    } # End of start_statements.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The code to push a new item onto the stack is just:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;    sub new_item
    {
        my($self, $type, $value) = @_;

        $self -&amp;gt; items -&amp;gt; push
            ({
                count =&amp;gt; $self -&amp;gt; increment_item_count,
                name  =&amp;gt; &#39;&#39;,
                type  =&amp;gt; $type,
                value =&amp;gt; $value,
             });

    } # End of new_item.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;using-marpa-in-the-lexer&#34;&gt;Using Marpa in the Lexer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, you can use Marpa in the lexer, as discussed in the first article. I prefer to use a spreadsheet full of regexps&amp;ndash;but enough of the lexer. It&amp;rsquo;s time to discuss the parser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-parser-s-structure&#34;&gt;The Parser&amp;rsquo;s Structure&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The parser incorporates the second sub-grammar and uses &lt;code&gt;Marpa::R2&lt;/code&gt; to validate the output from the lexer against this grammar. The parser&amp;rsquo;s structure is very similar to that of the lexer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Initialize using the parameters to &lt;code&gt;new()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Declare the grammar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run Marpa&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Save the output&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;marpa-actions-callbacks&#34;&gt;Marpa Actions (Callbacks)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with the lexer, the parser works via callbacks, which are functions named within the grammar and called by &lt;code&gt;Marpa::R2&lt;/code&gt; whenever the input sequence of lexed items matches some component of the grammar. Consider these four &lt;em&gt;rule descriptors&lt;/em&gt; in the grammar declared in &lt;code&gt;GraphViz2::Marpa::Parser&lt;/code&gt;&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;grammar()&lt;/code&gt; method:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;    [
    ...
    {   # Prolog stuff.
        lhs =&amp;gt; &#39;prolog_definition&#39;,
        rhs =&amp;gt; [qw/strict_definition digraph_definition graph_id_definition/],
    },
    {
        lhs    =&amp;gt; &#39;strict_definition&#39;,
        rhs    =&amp;gt; [qw/strict/],
        action =&amp;gt; &#39;strict&#39;, # &amp;lt;== Callback.
    },
    {
        lhs    =&amp;gt; &#39;digraph_definition&#39;,
        rhs    =&amp;gt; [qw/digraph/],
        action =&amp;gt; &#39;digraph&#39;, # &amp;lt;== Callback.
    },
    {
        lhs    =&amp;gt; &#39;graph_id_definition&#39;,
        rhs    =&amp;gt; [qw/graph_id/],
        action =&amp;gt; &#39;graph_id&#39;, # &amp;lt;== Callback. See sub graph_id() just below.
    },
    ...
    ]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In each case the &lt;code&gt;lhs&lt;/code&gt; is a name I&amp;rsquo;ve chosen so that I can refer to each rule descriptor in other rule descriptors. That&amp;rsquo;s how I chain rules together to make a tree structure. (See the &lt;em&gt;Chains and Trees&lt;/em&gt; section of the previous article.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This grammar fragment expects the input stream of items from the lexer to consist (at the start of the stream, actually) of three components: a strict thingy, a digraph thingy, and a graph_id thingy. Because I wrote the lexer, I can ensure that this is exactly what the lexer produces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To emphasise, the grammar says that these the items are the only things it will accept at this point in the input stream, and that only if they are in the given order, and that they must literally consist of the three tokens (see &lt;code&gt;rhs&lt;/code&gt;): &lt;em&gt;strict&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;digraph&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;graph_id&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These latter three come from the &lt;em&gt;type&lt;/em&gt; key in the array of hashrefs built by the lexer. The three corresponding &lt;em&gt;value&lt;/em&gt; keys in those hashrefs are &lt;code&gt;yes&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;no&lt;/code&gt; for &lt;em&gt;strict&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;code&gt;yes&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;no&lt;/code&gt; for &lt;em&gt;digraph&lt;/em&gt;, and an id or the empty string for &lt;em&gt;graph_id&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with the lexer, when in incoming token (&lt;em&gt;type&lt;/em&gt;) matches expectations, &lt;code&gt;Marpa::R2&lt;/code&gt; triggers a call to an &lt;em&gt;action&lt;/em&gt;, here called (for clarity) the same as the &lt;code&gt;rhs&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider one of those functions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;    sub graph_id
    {
        my($stash, $t1, undef, $t2)  = @_;

        $myself -&amp;gt; new_item(&#39;graph_id&#39;, $t1);

        return $t1;

    } # End of graph_id.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The parameter list is courtesy of how &lt;code&gt;Marpa::R2&lt;/code&gt; manages callbacks. &lt;code&gt;$t1&lt;/code&gt; is the incoming graph id. In &lt;em&gt;data/27.gv&lt;/em&gt; (shown earlier), that is &lt;code&gt;graph_27&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marpa does not supply the string &lt;code&gt;graph_id&lt;/code&gt; to this function, because there&amp;rsquo;s no need. I designed the grammar such that this function is only called when the value of the incoming &lt;em&gt;type&lt;/em&gt; is &lt;code&gt;graph_id&lt;/code&gt;, so I know precisely under what circumstances this function was called. That&amp;rsquo;s why I could hard-code the string &lt;code&gt;graph_id&lt;/code&gt; in the body of the &lt;code&gt;graph_id()&lt;/code&gt; function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-grammar-in-practice&#34;&gt;The Grammar in Practice&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you might be thinking: Just a second! That code seems to be doing no more than copying the input token to the output stream. Well, you&amp;rsquo;re right, sort of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;True understanding comes when you realize that Marpa calls that code only at the appropriate point precisely because the &lt;em&gt;type&lt;/em&gt; &lt;code&gt;graph_id&lt;/code&gt; and its &lt;em&gt;value&lt;/em&gt; &lt;code&gt;graph_27&lt;/code&gt; were at exactly the right place in the input stream. By that I mean that the location of the pair:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;    (type =&amp;gt; value)
    (&#39;graph_id&#39; =&amp;gt; &#39;graph_27&#39;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;in the input stream was exactly where it had to be to satisfy the grammar initialized by &lt;code&gt;Marpa::R2::Grammar&lt;/code&gt;. If it had not been there, Marpa would have thrown an exception, which we would recognize as a syntax error&amp;ndash;a syntax error in the input stream fed into the &lt;em&gt;lexer&lt;/em&gt;, but which Marpa picked up by testing that input stream against the grammar declared in the &lt;em&gt;parser&lt;/em&gt;. The role of the lexer as an intermediary is to simplify the logic of the code as a whole with a divide-and-conquer strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, it&amp;rsquo;s no accident that that function gets called at a particular point in time during the parser&amp;rsquo;s processing of its input stream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider another problem which arises as you build up the set of &lt;em&gt;rule descriptors&lt;/em&gt; within the grammar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;trees-have-leaves&#34;&gt;Trees Have Leaves&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first article discussed chains and trees (see the &lt;code&gt;prolog_definition&lt;/code&gt; mentioned earlier in this article). Briefly, each &lt;em&gt;rule descriptor&lt;/em&gt; must be chained to other &lt;em&gt;rule descriptors&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The astute reader will have already seen a problem: How do you define the meanings of the leaves of this tree when the chain of definitions must end at each leaf?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s part of the &lt;em&gt;data/27.lex&lt;/em&gt; input file:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;    &amp;quot;type&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;value&amp;quot;
    strict          , &amp;quot;no&amp;quot;
    digraph         , &amp;quot;yes&amp;quot;
    graph_id        , &amp;quot;graph_27&amp;quot;
    start_scope     , &amp;quot;1&amp;quot;
    node_id         , &amp;quot;node_27_1&amp;quot;
    open_bracket    , &amp;quot;[&amp;quot;
    attribute_id    , &amp;quot;color&amp;quot;
    equals          , &amp;quot;=&amp;quot;
    attribute_value , &amp;quot;red&amp;quot;
    attribute_id    , &amp;quot;fontcolor&amp;quot;
    equals          , &amp;quot;=&amp;quot;
    attribute_value , &amp;quot;green&amp;quot;
    close_bracket   , &amp;quot;]&amp;quot;
    ...
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The corresponding rules descriptors look like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;    [
    ...
    {
        lhs =&amp;gt; &#39;attribute_statement&#39;,
        rhs =&amp;gt; [qw/attribute_key has attribute_val/],
    },
    {
        lhs    =&amp;gt; &#39;attribute_key&#39;,
        rhs    =&amp;gt; [qw/attribute_id/], # &amp;lt;=== This is a terminal.
        min    =&amp;gt; 1,
        action =&amp;gt; &#39;attribute_id&#39;,
    },
    {
        lhs    =&amp;gt; &#39;has&#39;,
        rhs    =&amp;gt; [qw/equals/],
        min    =&amp;gt; 1,
    },
    {
        lhs    =&amp;gt; &#39;attribute_val&#39;,
        rhs    =&amp;gt; [qw/attribute_value/], # &amp;lt;=== And so is this.
        min    =&amp;gt; 1,
        action =&amp;gt; &#39;attribute_value&#39;,
    },
    ...
    ]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The items marked as terminals (standard parsing terminology) have no further definitions, so &lt;code&gt;attribute_key&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;attribute_val&lt;/code&gt; are leaves in the tree of &lt;em&gt;rule descriptors&lt;/em&gt;. What does that mean? The terminals &lt;code&gt;attribute_id&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;attribute_value&lt;/code&gt; must appear literally in the input stream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Switching between &lt;code&gt;attribute_key&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;attribute_id&lt;/code&gt; is a requirement of Marpa to avoid ambiguity in the statement of the grammar. Likewise for &lt;code&gt;attribute_val&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;attribute_value&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;min&lt;/code&gt; makes the attributes mandatory. Not in the sense that nodes and edges &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; have attributes, they don&amp;rsquo;t, but in the sense that if the input stream has an &lt;code&gt;attribute_id&lt;/code&gt; token, then it &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; have an &lt;code&gt;attribute_value&lt;/code&gt; token and vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember the earlier section &amp;ldquo;Working With An Incomplete BNF&amp;rdquo;? If the original &lt;em&gt;*.gv&lt;/em&gt; file used one of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;    size = &amp;quot;6,6&amp;quot;
    [size = &amp;quot;6,6&amp;quot;]
    graph [size = &amp;quot;6,6&amp;quot;]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip; then the one chosen really represents the graph attribute:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;    graph [size = &amp;quot;6,6&amp;quot;]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make this work, the lexer must force the output to be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;    &amp;quot;type&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;value&amp;quot;
    ...
    class_id        , &amp;quot;graph&amp;quot;
    open_bracket    , &amp;quot;[&amp;quot;
    attribute_id    , &amp;quot;size&amp;quot;
    equals          , &amp;quot;=&amp;quot;
    attribute_value , &amp;quot;6,6&amp;quot;
    close_bracket   , &amp;quot;]&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This matches the requirements, in that both &lt;code&gt;attribute_id&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;attribute_value&lt;/code&gt; are present, is their (so to speak) owner, the object itself, which is identified by the &lt;em&gt;type&lt;/em&gt; &lt;code&gt;class_id&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this should reinforce the point that the design of the lexer is intimately tied to the design of the parser. By taking decisions like this in the lexer you can standardize its output and simplify the work that the parser needs to don.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;where-to-go-from-here&#34;&gt;Where to go from here&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recently released Perl module &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/MarpaX::Simple::Rules&#34;&gt;MarpaX::Simple::Rules&lt;/a&gt; takes a BNF and generates the corresponding grammar in the format expected by &lt;code&gt;Marpa::R2&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jeffrey Kegler (author of Marpa) &lt;a href=&#34;http://jeffreykegler.github.com/Ocean-of-Awareness-blog/individual/2012/06/the-useful-the-playful-the-easy-the-hard-and-the-beautiful.html%3E&#34;&gt;has blogged about MarpaX::Simple::Rules&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a very interesting development, because it automates the laborious process of converting a BNF into a set of Marpa&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;rule descriptors&lt;/em&gt;. Consequently, it makes sense for anyone contemplating using &lt;code&gt;Marpa::R2&lt;/code&gt; to investigate how appropriate it would be to do so via &lt;code&gt;MarpaX::Simple::Rules&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;wrapping-up-and-winding-down&#34;&gt;Wrapping Up and Winding Down&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;ve seen samples of lexer output and some parts of the grammar which both define the second sub-grammar of what to expect and what should match precisely the input from that lexer. If they don&amp;rsquo;t match, it is in fact the parser which issues the dread syntax error message, because only it (not the lexer) knows which combinations of input tokens are acceptable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like in the lexer, callback functions stockpile items which have passed Marpa::R2&amp;rsquo;s attempt to match up input tokens with rule descriptors. This technique records exactly which rules fired in which order. After Marpa::R2 has run to completion, you have a stack of items whose elements are a (lexed and) parsed version of the original file. Your job is then to output that stack to a file, or await the caller of the parser to ask for the stack as an array reference. From there, the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more details, consult &lt;a href=&#34;http://savage.net.au/Ron/html/writing.graph.easy.marpa.html%3E&#34;&gt;my July 2011 article on Marpa::R2&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-lexer-and-the-state-transition-table-revisited&#34;&gt;The Lexer and the State Transition Table - Revisited&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The complexity of the STT in &lt;code&gt;GraphViz2::Marpa&lt;/code&gt; justifies the decision to split the lexer and the parser into separate modules. Clearly that will not always be the case. Given a sufficiently simple grammar, the lexer phase may be redundant. Consider this test data file, &lt;em&gt;data/sample.1.ged&lt;/em&gt;, from &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Genealogy::Gedcom&#34;&gt;Genealogy::Gedcom&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;    0 HEAD
    1 SOUR Genealogy::Gedcom
    2 NAME Genealogy::Gedcom::Reader
    2 VERS V 1.00
    2 CORP Ron Savage
    3 ADDR Box 3055
    4 STAE Vic
    4 POST 3163
    4 CTRY Australia
    3 EMAIL ron@savage.net.au
    3 WWW http://savage.net.au
    2 DATA
    3 COPR Copyright 2011, Ron Savage
    1 NOTE
    2 CONT This file is based on test data in Paul Johnson&#39;s Gedcom.pm
    2 CONT Gedcom.pm is Copyright 1999-2009, Paul Johnson (paul@pjcj.net)
    2 CONT Version 1.16 - 24th April 2009
    2 CONT
    2 CONT Ron&#39;s modules under the Genealogy::Gedcom namespace are free
    2 CONT
    2 CONT The latest versions of these modules are available from
    2 CONT my homepage http://savage.net.au and http://metacpan.org
    1 GEDC
    2 VERS 5.5.1-5
    2 FORM LINEAGE-LINKED
    1 DATE 10-08-2011
    1 CHAR ANSEL
    1 SUBM @SUBM1@
    0 TRLR
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each line matches &lt;code&gt;/^(\d+)\s([A-Z]{3,4})\s(.+)$/&lt;/code&gt;: an integer, a keyword, and a string. In this case I&amp;rsquo;d skip the lexer, and have the parser tokenize the input. So, horses for courses. (GEDCOM defines genealogical data; see &lt;a href=&#34;http://wiki.webtrees.net/File:Ged551-5.pdf%3E&#34;&gt;the GEDCOM definition&lt;/a&gt; for more details).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sample-output&#34;&gt;Sample Output&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve provided several links of sample output for your perusal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://savage.net.au/Perl-modules/html/graphviz2/&#34;&gt;GraphViz2 (non-Marpa)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://savage.net.au/Perl-modules/html/graphviz2.marpa/&#34;&gt;GraphViz2::Marpa&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://savage.net.au/Perl-modules/html/graphviz2.pathutils/&#34;&gt;GraphViz2::Marpa::PathUtils&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://savage.net.au/Perl-modules/html/graph.easy.marpa/&#34;&gt;Graph::Easy::Marpa&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy lexing and parsing!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Consuming RESTful Services with Perl</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/pub/2012/12/consuming-restful-services-with-perl.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2012 06:00:01 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/pub/2012/12/consuming-restful-services-with-perl.html/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;In my previous article I described &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/pub/2012/11/designing-board-games-with-perl.html&#34;&gt;how to create board game images using &lt;code&gt;Image::Magick&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, thus allowing you to design board games using Perl. This time I want to show you how to upload those images to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thegamecrafter.com/&#34;&gt;The Game Crafter&lt;/a&gt; so you get get a professional copy of the game manufactured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last article I &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thegamecrafter.com/games/lacuna-expanse:-a-new-empire&#34;&gt;created a board game version&lt;/a&gt; of the video game called &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lacunaexpanse.com&#34;&gt;The Lacuna Expanse&lt;/a&gt;. This time I&amp;rsquo;ll show how to upload those images to the site to create a custom board game. Don&amp;rsquo;t worry if you&amp;rsquo;re not ready to create a board game or if you&amp;rsquo;ll never be ready; the principles of designing a useful API and using it apply to all sorts of services you might want to use, from weather tracking to stocks to medical systems. I picked games for two reasons. One, me and I team just built this system, so it&amp;rsquo;s shiny and new and I&amp;rsquo;ve learned a lot. Two, games are more fun (and visual) than showing how to record invoice information in a RESTful ERP application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;getting-ready&#34;&gt;Getting Ready&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, get yourself a copy of &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/TheGameCrafter::Client&#34;&gt;TheGameCrafter::Client&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s a Perl module that makes it trivial to interact with The Game Crafter&amp;rsquo;s RESTful web service API. When you &lt;code&gt;use TheGameCrafter::Client;&lt;/code&gt; it imports &lt;code&gt;tgc_get()&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;tgc_post()&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;tgc_put()&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;tgc_delete()&lt;/code&gt; into your program for easy use. &lt;em&gt;Good APIs are descriptive and obvious.&lt;/em&gt; From there you can have a look at The Game Crafter&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thegamecrafter.com/developer/&#34;&gt;developer documentation&lt;/a&gt; to do any custom stuff you want. &lt;em&gt;Good APIs have useful documentation.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;ll also need to activate the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thegamecrafter.com/account&#34;&gt;developer setting in your TGC account&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thegamecrafter.com/account/apikeys&#34;&gt;request an API key&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Good APIs demonstrate security in authorization and authentication.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-little-about-the-game-crafter-s-api&#34;&gt;A Little about The Game Crafter&amp;rsquo;s API&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;TheGameCrafter::Client&lt;/code&gt; is just a tiny wrapper around our RESTful web services. I designed the web services atop &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Dancer&#34;&gt;Dancer&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/DBIx::Class&#34;&gt;DBIx::Class&lt;/a&gt;. My goal with this was to build a very reliable and consistent API not only for external use but internal. You see, the &lt;em&gt;entire&lt;/em&gt; TGC web site actually runs off these web services. Not only that, but these web services tie directly into our manufacturing facility, so they are controlling the physical world in addition to the virtual. &lt;em&gt;Good APIs allow you to build multiple clients with different uses.&lt;/em&gt; (They don&amp;rsquo;t &lt;em&gt;require&lt;/em&gt; multiple clients, but they don&amp;rsquo;t forbid it and do enable it.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Lacuna, I built &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/JSON::RPC::Dispatcher&#34;&gt;JSON::RPC::Dispatcher&lt;/a&gt; (JRD), which is a JSON-RPC 2.0 web service handler on top of &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Plack&#34;&gt;Plack&lt;/a&gt;. I love JRD, but it has two weaknesses, one of them fatal. One weakness is that you must format parameters using JSON, which means that it&amp;rsquo;s not easy to just call a URL and get a result with something like &lt;code&gt;curl&lt;/code&gt;. (&lt;em&gt;Good RESTful APIs allow multiple clients.&lt;/em&gt; If you can&amp;rsquo;t use &lt;code&gt;curl&lt;/code&gt;, you probably have a problem.) The fatal weakness of JSON-RPC 2.0 is that there is no way to do file uploads within the spec. The Game Crafter is all about file uploads, so that meant I either needed to handle those separately (aka inconsistently), or develop something new. I opted for the latter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With TGC&amp;rsquo;s web services I decided to adopt some of the things I really liked about JSON-RPC, namely the way it handles responses whether they be result sets or errors. So you always get a consistent return:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;{ &amp;quot;result&amp;quot; : { ... } }

{
   &amp;quot;error&amp;quot; : {
        &amp;quot;code&amp;quot; : 404,
        &amp;quot;message&amp;quot; : &amp;quot;File not found.&amp;quot;,
        &amp;quot;data&amp;quot; : &amp;quot;file_id&amp;quot;
   }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With TGC I also wanted a consistent and easy way of turning &lt;code&gt;DBIx::Class&lt;/code&gt; into web services through Dancer. I looked into things like &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/AutoCRUD&#34;&gt;AutoCRUD&lt;/a&gt;, but I&amp;rsquo;m not a fan of Catalyst, and it also took too much configuration (in my opinion) to get it working. I wanted something simpler and faster, so I decided to roll my own. The result was a thin layer of glue between Dancer and &lt;code&gt;DBIx::Class&lt;/code&gt; that allows you to define your web service interface in your normal &lt;code&gt;DBIx::Class&lt;/code&gt; declarations. It automatically then generates the web services, databases tables, web form handling, and more for you. This little glue layer is now in use in all web app development within &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.plainblack.com/&#34;&gt;Plain Black&lt;/a&gt;, and eventually we&amp;rsquo;ll be releasing it onto CPAN for all to use for free. The best part of that is that you know you&amp;rsquo;re getting a production-ready system because it&amp;rsquo;s been running The Game Crafter and other sites for over a year now. (&lt;em&gt;Good APIs are often extracted from working systems.&lt;/em&gt;) More on that in a future article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;let-s-do-this-thing-already&#34;&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s Do This Thing Already&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before you can make any API calls, you need to authenticate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt; my $session = tgc_post(&#39;session&#39;,{
   username    =&amp;gt; &#39;me&#39;,
   password    =&amp;gt; &#39;123qwe&#39;,
   api_key_id  =&amp;gt; &#39;abcdefhij&#39;,
 });
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before you can start uploading, fetch your user account information. This contains several pieces of info that you can use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt; my $user = tgc_get(&#39;user&#39;, {
   session_id    =&amp;gt; $session-&amp;gt;{id},           # using our session to do stuff
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think of TGC projects like filesystems: you have folders which contain folders and files. First create a folder, then upload a file:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt; my $folder = tgc_post(&#39;folder&#39;, {
  session_id  =&amp;gt; $session-&amp;gt;{id},
  name        =&amp;gt; &#39;Lacuna&#39;,
  user_id     =&amp;gt; $user-&amp;gt;{id},
  parent_id   =&amp;gt; $user-&amp;gt;{root_folder_id},  # putting this in the home folder
 });

 my $file = tgc_post(&#39;file&#39;, {
  session_id  =&amp;gt; $session-&amp;gt;{id},
  name        =&amp;gt; &#39;Mayhem Training&#39;,
  file        =&amp;gt; [&#39;mayhem.png&#39;],         # the array ref signifies this is a file path
  folder_id   =&amp;gt; $folder-&amp;gt;{id},       # putting it in the just-created folder
 });
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assuming at this point you&amp;rsquo;ve uploaded all of your files, you can now build out your game. The Game Crafter has this notion of a &amp;ldquo;Designer&amp;rdquo;, which is sort of like your very own publishing company. Games are attached to the designer, so first you must create the designer, then the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt; my $designer = tgc_post(&#39;designer&#39;, {
  session_id  =&amp;gt; $session-&amp;gt;{id},
  user_id     =&amp;gt; $user-&amp;gt;{id},
  name        =&amp;gt; &#39;Lacuna Expanse Corp&#39;,
 });

 my $game = tgc_post(&#39;game&#39;, {
  session_id  =&amp;gt; $session-&amp;gt;{id},
  designer_id =&amp;gt; $designer-&amp;gt;{id},
  name        =&amp;gt; &#39;Lacuna Expanse: A New Empire&#39;,
 });
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a game created and assets uploaded, you can now create a deck of cards. This is pretty straight forward just like before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt; my $deck = tgc_post(&#39;minideck&#39;, {
  session_id =&amp;gt; $session-&amp;gt;{id},
  name       =&amp;gt; &#39;Planet&#39;,
  game_id    =&amp;gt; $game-&amp;gt;{id},
 });

 my $card = tgc_post(&#39;minicard&#39;, {
  session_id =&amp;gt; $session-&amp;gt;{id},
  name       =&amp;gt; &#39;Mayhem Training&#39;,
  face_id    =&amp;gt; $file-&amp;gt;{id},
  deck_id    =&amp;gt; $deck-&amp;gt;{id},
 });
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have probably noticed already how closely this resembles CRUD operations, because it does. Behind the scenes, who knows what TGC does with this information? (I do, but that&amp;rsquo;s because I wrote it.) It doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter to the API, because all of those details are hidden behind a good API. *Good APIs expose only the necessary details*—in this case, the relationships between folders and files and between designers and games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also see that the API is as stateless as possible, where the session identifier is part of every API call. It&amp;rsquo;s easy to imagine a more complicated API which hides this, but I stuck with the bare-bones REST for at least two reasons: it&amp;rsquo;s simple, and it&amp;rsquo;s easy to see what&amp;rsquo;s happening. Someone could build over the top of this API if desired. &lt;em&gt;Good APIs allow extension and further abstraction.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like that, you&amp;rsquo;ve created a game and added a deck of cards to it. There are of course lots of other fancy things you can do with the API, but this should get you started. I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t leave you hanging there, however. I&amp;rsquo;ve &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/plainblack/Lacuna-Board-Game&#34;&gt;open sourced the actual code&lt;/a&gt; I used to create &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thegamecrafter.com/games/lacuna-expanse:-a-new-empire&#34;&gt;the Lacuna Expanse board game&lt;/a&gt; so you&amp;rsquo;d have something to reference. There&amp;rsquo;s also a &lt;a href=&#34;https://community.thegamecrafter.com/forums/developers&#34;&gt;developer&amp;rsquo;s forum&lt;/a&gt; if you have any questions. Good luck to you, and happy gaming!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Designing Board Games With Perl</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/pub/2012/11/designing-board-games-with-perl.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Nov 2012 06:00:01 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/pub/2012/11/designing-board-games-with-perl.html/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Board games are hotter than they&amp;rsquo;ve ever been. In fact, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.icv2.com/articles/news/24066.html&#34;&gt;the board game market has grown 25% in the past year while the video game market shrank 20%&lt;/a&gt;. But you&amp;rsquo;re a Perl hacker, not an Adobe Illustrator, so how can you design a board game? Well, that&amp;rsquo;s exactly what I aim to show you in this article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, you need an idea. You can turn literally anything into a game. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thegamecrafter.com/games/adventurelings&#34; title=&#34;Adventurelings&#34;&gt;Whether&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thegamecrafter.com/games/plague-the-card-game&#34; title=&#34;Plague&#34;&gt;you&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thegamecrafter.com/games/merc&#34; title=&#34;MERC&#34;&gt;just&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thegamecrafter.com/games/the-decktet-firmament-&#34; title=&#34;The Decktet&#34;&gt;want&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thegamecrafter.com/games/zombiezone&#34; title=&#34;ZombieZone&#34;&gt;to&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thegamecrafter.com/games/surviving-design-projects&#34; title=&#34;Surviving Design Projects&#34;&gt;design&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thegamecrafter.com/games/rejection-therapy-the-game&#34; title=&#34;Rejection Therapy&#34;&gt;your&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thegamecrafter.com/games/hackers-agents&#34; title=&#34;Hackers
    and Agents&#34;&gt;own&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thegamecrafter.com/games/the-tarat&#34; title=&#34;The
    TaRat&#34;&gt;custom&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thegamecrafter.com/games/wild-pursuit-&#34; title=&#34;Wild
    Pursuit&#34;&gt;playing&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thegamecrafter.com/games/jump-gate&#34; title=&#34;Jump
    Gate&#34;&gt;cards&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thegamecrafter.com/games/sandwich-city&#34; title=&#34;Sandwich
    City&#34;&gt;or&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thegamecrafter.com/games/shake-out-&#34; title=&#34;Shake Out&#34;&gt;you&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thegamecrafter.com/games/trade-fleet&#34; title=&#34;Trade
    Fleet&#34;&gt;want&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thegamecrafter.com/games/diggity&#34; title=&#34;Diggity&#34;&gt;to&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thegamecrafter.com/games/elemental-clash:-the-basic-set&#34; title=&#34;Elemental Clash&#34;&gt;make&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thegamecrafter.com/games/black-and-red&#34; title=&#34;Black and
    Red Playing Cards&#34;&gt;a&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thegamecrafter.com/games/frogs-&#34; title=&#34;Frogs!&#34;&gt;full&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thegamecrafter.com/games/phytocats&#34; title=&#34;Phytocats&#34;&gt;on&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thegamecrafter.com/games/city-of-gears&#34; title=&#34;City of
    Gears&#34;&gt;custom&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thegamecrafter.com/games/gibs&#34; title=&#34;Gibs&#34;&gt;board&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thegamecrafter.com/games/dr-pergias-race&#34; title=&#34;Doctor
    Pergaias&#39; Race Across The Continent&#34;&gt;or&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thegamecrafter.com/games/goblin-warlord&#34; title=&#34;Goblin
    Warlord&#34;&gt;card&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thegamecrafter.com/games/braaaaains-&#34; title=&#34;Braaaaains!&#34;&gt;game&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thegamecrafter.com/games/the-great-race1&#34; title=&#34;The
    Great Race&#34;&gt;the&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thegamecrafter.com/games/road-to-magnate&#34; title=&#34;Road to
    Magnate&#34;&gt;options&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thegamecrafter.com/games/zerpang-&#34; title=&#34;Zerpang!&#34;&gt;are&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thegamecrafter.com/games/angels-elements&#34; title=&#34;Angels
    Elements&#34;&gt;limitless&lt;/a&gt;. (Full disclosure: I&amp;rsquo;m one of the owners of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thegamecrafter.com/&#34;&gt;The Game Crafter&lt;/a&gt;, which itself is written entirely in Perl. )&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the purposes of this article, I&amp;rsquo;m going to make &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thegamecrafter.com/games/lacuna-expanse:-a-new-empire&#34;&gt;a board game version&lt;/a&gt; of the popular Perl-based web game &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lacunaexpanse.com&#34;&gt;The Lacuna Expanse&lt;/a&gt;. (I&amp;rsquo;m also one of the owners of Lacuna.) I chose this because I already have some artwork for it, albeit not in board game form. However, &lt;a href=&#34;https://community.thegamecrafter.com/publish/file-preparation/art-resources&#34;&gt;you can get free art from various sites around the web&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My Lacuna-based board game will be a tile placement game where all the players work together cooperatively to fend off an alien invasion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;let-s-get-to-the-perl-already&#34;&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s Get To The Perl Already!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several great image manipulation libraries on the CPAN, but my personal favorite is &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Image::Magick&#34;&gt;Image::Magick&lt;/a&gt;. I started by creating a base image which I could manipulate in any way that I wanted. (I based my choice off of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thegamecrafter.com/publish/pricing&#34;&gt;The Game Crafter&amp;rsquo;s list of component sizes and prices&lt;/a&gt;.) I decided to use &lt;a href=&#34;https://community.thegamecrafter.com/publish/templates/cards/mini-cards&#34;&gt;mini cards&lt;/a&gt;, because the table would fill up too quickly with full poker-sized cards; there&amp;rsquo;ll be a lot of cards on the table!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt; my $card = Image::Magick-&amp;gt;new(size=&amp;gt;&#39;600x825&#39;);
 say $card-&amp;gt;ReadImage(&#39;canvas:white&#39;);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that I used &lt;code&gt;say&lt;/code&gt; in front of the &lt;code&gt;ReadImage&lt;/code&gt; call. &lt;code&gt;Image::Magick&lt;/code&gt; will emit a textual exception on each call if anything goes wrong. I could easily wrap that with better error handling, but for now printing to the screen is sufficient for my needs.
When printing things (really &lt;em&gt;printing&lt;/em&gt; them, with ink and all) you also have to take into account something called &lt;a href=&#34;http://youtu.be/NqZSFpmS2dM&#34;&gt;bleed and cut lines&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s easy to draw the cut line on the card in red as the boundary of the printable image content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt; say $card-&amp;gt;Draw(stroke=&amp;gt;&#39;red&#39;, fill =&amp;gt; &#39;none&#39;, strokewidth=&amp;gt;1, primitive=&amp;gt;&#39;rectangle&#39;, points=&amp;gt;&#39;38,38 562,787&#39;);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/_pub_2012_11_designing-board-games-with-perl/blank.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;blank with cut lines&#34; /&gt;
So far so good. The next step is to give this card a background so that it starts to look like a card. For this I&amp;rsquo;ll take one of the planet surface images from the Lacuna Expanse and rotate it and stretch it to fit the shape of the card.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt; my $surface = Image::Magick-&amp;gt;new;
 say $surface-&amp;gt;ReadImage(&#39;surface-p17.jpg&#39;);
 say $surface-&amp;gt;Rotate(90);
 say $surface-&amp;gt;Resize(&#39;600x825!&#39;);
 say $card-&amp;gt;Composite(compose =&amp;gt; &#39;over&#39;, image =&amp;gt; $surface, x =&amp;gt; 0, y =&amp;gt; 0);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note the exclamation point (&lt;strong&gt;!&lt;/strong&gt;) on the &lt;code&gt;Resize&lt;/code&gt; command. That tells &lt;code&gt;Image::Magick&lt;/code&gt; to distort the native aspect ratio of the image. In other words, stretch the image to fill the size I&amp;rsquo;ve specified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/_pub_2012_11_designing-board-games-with-perl/background.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;background&#34; /&gt;
You may have noticed that this image looks enormous. That&amp;rsquo;s because it&amp;rsquo;s for print (on paper!) rather than screens. Print has more &lt;a href=&#34;http://proshooter.com/article_whatisa300dpiJPeg.htm&#34;&gt;pixels per inch/centimeter&lt;/a&gt; than screens, thus the image looks bigger when you display it on a screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the card needs a title. Adding text to the image is straightforward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt; $card-&amp;gt;Annotate(text =&amp;gt; &#39;Mayhem Training&#39;, font =&amp;gt; &#39;ALIEN5.ttf&#39;, y =&amp;gt; -275, fill =&amp;gt; &#39;white&#39;, pointsize =&amp;gt; 70, gravity =&amp;gt; &#39;Center&#39;);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/_pub_2012_11_designing-board-games-with-perl/title.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;title&#34; /&gt;
As you can see I&amp;rsquo;ve used a custom font. &lt;code&gt;Image::Magick&lt;/code&gt; is capable of using nearly any OpenType or TrueType font.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a background and a title, the next step is to overlay the card with a picture of the Mayhem Training building from the video game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt; my $image = Image::Magick-&amp;gt;new;
 say $image-&amp;gt;ReadImage(&#39;mayhemtraining9.png&#39;);
 say $card-&amp;gt;Composite(compose =&amp;gt; &#39;over&#39;, image =&amp;gt; $image, x =&amp;gt; 100, y =&amp;gt; 165);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/_pub_2012_11_designing-board-games-with-perl/image.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;added image&#34; /&gt;
Now we&amp;rsquo;re finally getting somewhere! This is really starting to look like a card. Use the same technique to overlay an icon onto the card. As in so many games, these icons symbolize an ability that the card grants the player who uses it. You can get free icons from all over the web; one of my favorite libraries is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.glyphish.com&#34;&gt;Glyphish&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt; my $icon = Image::Magick-&amp;gt;new;
 say $icon-&amp;gt;ReadImage(&#39;target.png&#39;);
 say $card-&amp;gt;Composite(compose =&amp;gt; &#39;over&#39;, image =&amp;gt; $icon, x =&amp;gt; 100, y =&amp;gt; 570);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/_pub_2012_11_designing-board-games-with-perl/icon.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;added icon&#34; /&gt;
You can&amp;rsquo;t get away with icons all the time; a little text will explain things to new players. Adding some explanation to the card would be really tricky, if it weren&amp;rsquo;t for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imagemagick.org/discourse-server/viewtopic.php?f=7&amp;amp;t=3708&#34;&gt;some really neat code that Gabe Schaffer contributed to the ImageMagick forums a long time ago&lt;/a&gt;. Basically without this code you&amp;rsquo;d have to make the text wrap at word boundaries yourself, but with it, you can just do a simple &lt;code&gt;Annotate&lt;/code&gt; call like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt; $card-&amp;gt;Set(font =&amp;gt; &#39;promethean.ttf&#39;, pointsize =&amp;gt; 35);
 my $text = &#39;Demolish one of your buildings to use this ability.&#39;;
 my $text_wrapped = wrap($text, $card, 400);
 say $card-&amp;gt;Annotate(text =&amp;gt; $text_wrapped, x =&amp;gt; 100, y =&amp;gt; 690, font =&amp;gt; &#39;promethean.ttf&#39;, fill =&amp;gt; &#39;white&#39;, pointsize =&amp;gt; 35);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/_pub_2012_11_designing-board-games-with-perl/text.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;added text&#34; /&gt;
A game like this wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be very interesting if you could place any card anywhere you want. To solve this, I want to to add something to the card to indicate how other cards can connect to it. This is the most challenging part yet, because I want to make a half-circle/half-rectangle connector. Because this is a bit more complicated and I want to use it for drawing connection points on various sides of the card, I&amp;rsquo;ll turn it into a subroutine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt; sub draw_connection_point {
   my ($card, $color, $rotation, $x, $y) = @_;

   # draw a half circle, it&#39;s a half cuz we&#39;re drawing outide the image
   my $half_circle  = Image::Magick-&amp;gt;new(size=&amp;gt;&#39;70x35&#39;);
   say $half_circle-&amp;gt;ReadImage(&#39;canvas:transparent&#39;);
   say $half_circle-&amp;gt;Draw(stroke =&amp;gt; $color, fill =&amp;gt; $color, strokewidth=&amp;gt;1, primitive=&amp;gt;&#39;circle&#39;, points=&amp;gt;&#39;35,35, 35,70&#39;);

   # create the connection point image
   my $connection = Image::Magick-&amp;gt;new(size=&amp;gt;&#39;70x85&#39;);
   say $connection-&amp;gt;ReadImage(&#39;canvas:transparent&#39;);

   # add the half circle to the connection point
   say $connection-&amp;gt;Composite(compose =&amp;gt; &#39;over&#39;, image =&amp;gt; $half_circle, x =&amp;gt; 0, y =&amp;gt; 0);

   # extend the connection point the the edge
   say $connection-&amp;gt;Draw(stroke=&amp;gt;$color, fill =&amp;gt; $color, strokewidth=&amp;gt;1, primitive=&amp;gt;&#39;rectangle&#39;, points=&amp;gt;&#39;0,35 70,85&#39;);

   # orient the connection point for its position
   say $connection-&amp;gt;Rotate($rotation);

   # apply the connection point to the image
   say $card-&amp;gt;Composite(compose =&amp;gt; &#39;over&#39;, image =&amp;gt; $connection, x =&amp;gt; $x, y =&amp;gt; $y);
 }

 draw_connection_point($card, &#39;purple&#39;, 0, 265, 740);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/_pub_2012_11_designing-board-games-with-perl/connection.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;connection added&#34; /&gt;
Sometimes it&amp;rsquo;s nice to give players hints about stuff so they can form better strategies. To that end, I added a series of pips above the title to indicate how many copies of this card are in the deck. In this case, this card is unique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt; my $quantity = 1;
 my $pips = &#39;.&#39; x $quantity;
 say $card-&amp;gt;Annotate(text =&amp;gt; $pips, y =&amp;gt; -340, fill =&amp;gt; &#39;white&#39;, pointsize =&amp;gt; 70, gravity =&amp;gt; &#39;Center&#39;);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/_pub_2012_11_designing-board-games-with-perl/finished.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;finished&#34; /&gt;
Remember to remove the cut line before you save the file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt; #say $card-&amp;gt;Draw(stroke=&amp;gt;&#39;red&#39;, fill =&amp;gt; &#39;none&#39;, strokewidth=&amp;gt;1, primitive=&amp;gt;&#39;rectangle&#39;, points=&amp;gt;&#39;38,38 562,787&#39;);
 say $card-&amp;gt;Write(&#39;mayhem.png&#39;);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/_pub_2012_11_designing-board-games-with-perl/cut-line-removed.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;cut lines removed&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;rationale&#34;&gt;Rationale&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that I&amp;rsquo;ve shown you how to create a card, you may have one question. Why would you go through the work of coding it rather than just using Photoshop or the Gimp? There are lots of reasons to code it including things like you don&amp;rsquo;t know how to use image editors. However the really important reason is the same reason you write code to do anything&amp;hellip; automation! A game isn&amp;rsquo;t made of just one card. Likewise, games aren&amp;rsquo;t designed in just one try. It takes lots of play testing and revisions. If you design your board game using code you can whip out a new revision as easily as changing a config file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, automatic image generation isn&amp;rsquo;t only for games&amp;hellip;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;next-time&#34;&gt;Next Time&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve shown you how to create the images for a game. If you&amp;rsquo;re like me, the next thing you want to do is print your game. You could do this at home, but it will cost you a lot of time and money (ink jet ink costs more than human blood). You could take it to Kinkos, but you won&amp;rsquo;t get a nice quality product because they don&amp;rsquo;t specialize in making games. Instead, you can upload your files to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thegamecrafter.com&#34;&gt;The Game Crafter&lt;/a&gt;, where you&amp;rsquo;ll get a custom game that looks like it game from the game store. There&amp;rsquo;s a nice easy to use web interface to do this, but you&amp;rsquo;re a Perl programmer. Why do something manually if you can automate it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides that, it&amp;rsquo;s a real-world example of interacting with a web service written completely in Perl—on both sides. Who wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be interested in that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;for-the-impatient&#34;&gt;For The Impatient&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thegamecrafter.com/games/lacuna-expanse:-a-new-empire&#34;&gt;The Lacuna Expanse Board Game&lt;/a&gt; is available for purchase now if you&amp;rsquo;re interested. Also, I&amp;rsquo;ve &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/plainblack/Lacuna-Board-Game&#34;&gt;released the code I wrote to develop it via this public GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Newcomer Experience in the Perl Community Survey</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/pub/2012/10/newcomer-experience-in-the-perl-community-survey.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Oct 2012 06:00:01 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/pub/2012/10/newcomer-experience-in-the-perl-community-survey.html/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I am currently running &lt;a href=&#34;https://limesurvey.sim.vuw.ac.nz/index.php?sid=89971&amp;amp;lang=en&#34;&gt;a survey looking at the Perl community&lt;/a&gt; specifically and I am looking for people who joined the Perl community within the last two years. I am equally interested in hearing from people having had either positive or negative experiences as newcomers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;perl-subcultures-and-newcomer-experience-in-perl&#34;&gt;Perl subcultures and newcomer experience in Perl&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Perl community has been a growing and evolving multi-faceted entity that is now comprised of a large number of social groups (for example, 262 Perl Mongers groups as of 10/10/12) and various sub-projects that all have their own history and subculture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some projects are very newcomer conscious while others are not. Projects may rely on different strategies and means when trying to integrate new recruits. Younger projects like &lt;a href=&#34;http://mojolicio.us/&#34;&gt;Mojo&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;http://perldancer.org/&#34;&gt;Dancer&lt;/a&gt; may do things differently compared to older projects such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://catalystframework.org/&#34;&gt;Catalyst&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;http://moose.perl.org/&#34;&gt;Moose&lt;/a&gt;. Depending on a project&amp;rsquo;s subculture, there may be more or fewer resources dedicated to helping newcomers, people may be more or less supportive, or people may or may not voluntarily mentor newcomers. We could also debate about the differences between Perl 5 and Perl 6 when dealing with newcomers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is then a lot of variation in the way newcomers of the overall Perl community are handled making each person&amp;rsquo;s newcomer experience pretty unique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among all these different types of experience, some of them will lead one to become a valued sustainable contributor (from the Perl community perspective) while others may simply end up in people slowly giving up or even running away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This study tries to identify the important aspects of one&amp;rsquo;s newcomer experience in Perl that have a positive influence in generating &amp;ldquo;good&amp;rdquo; contributors—&amp;rdquo;good&amp;rdquo; in terms of being good citizens for the Perl community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-is-it-going-to-help-perl&#34;&gt;How is it going to help Perl?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The data will help gain insights about the experience of newcomers within the Perl community. In addition, it will allow to understand how to design effective newcomer initiatives to ensure that Perl will remain a successful and healthy community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;where-is-the-project-going-after-that&#34;&gt;Where is the project going after that?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This survey is the first step of the research project as a refined survey will be later administered to other FOSS communities at the same time. This will allow to generate cross-community results that will be to some extent generalizable. This research project overall aims at helping FOSS communities to design newcomer initiatives in line with their well-being and sustainability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;about-the-survey&#34;&gt;About the survey&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This survey is anonymous, and no information that would identify you is being collected. I expect the survey to take around 20 minutes of your time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The survey is available at &lt;a href=&#34;https://limesurvey.sim.vuw.ac.nz/index.php?sid=89971&amp;amp;lang=en&#34;&gt;https://limesurvey.sim.vuw.ac.nz/index.php?sid=89971&amp;amp;lang=en&lt;/a&gt;. It will be available until Monday, 22 October, 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you know members of the Perl community who you think would be interested in completing it, please let them know about the survey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will post news about my progress with this research, and the results on my blog at &lt;a href=&#34;http://kevincarillo.org/&#34;&gt;kevincarillo.org&lt;/a&gt;. Don&amp;rsquo;t hesitate to contact me at &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:kevin.carillo@vuw.ac.nz&#34;&gt;kevin.carillo@vuw.ac.nz&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Overview of Lexing and Parsing</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/pub/2012/10/an-overview-of-lexing-and-parsing.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Oct 2012 06:00:01 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/pub/2012/10/an-overview-of-lexing-and-parsing.html/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Perl programmers spend a lot of time munging data: reading it in, transforming it, and writing out the results. Perl&amp;rsquo;s great at this ad hoc text transformation, with all sorts of string manipulation tools, including regular expressions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regular expressions will only get you so far: witness the repeated advice that you cannot parse HTML or XML with regular expressions themselves. When Perl&amp;rsquo;s builtin text processing tools aren&amp;rsquo;t enough, you have to turn to something more powerful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That something is &lt;em&gt;parsing&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;an-overview-of-lexing-and-parsing&#34;&gt;An Overview of Lexing and Parsing&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a more formal discussion of what exactly lexing and parsing are, start with Wikipedia&amp;rsquo;s definitions: &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lexing&#34;&gt;Lexing&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parsing&#34;&gt;Parsing&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, when people use the word parsing, they sometimes include the idea of lexing. Other times they don&amp;rsquo;t. This can cause confusion, but I&amp;rsquo;ll try to keep them clear. Such situations arise with other words, and our minds usually resolve the specific meaning intended by analysing the context in which the word is used. So, keep your mind in mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lex phase and the parse phase can be combined into a single process, but I advocate always keeping them separate. Trust me for a moment; I&amp;rsquo;ll explain shortly. If you&amp;rsquo;re having trouble keeping the ideas separate, note that the phases very conveniently run in alphabetical order: first we lex, and then we parse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;a-history-lesson-in-absentia&#34;&gt;A History Lesson - In Absentia&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, an article such as this would normally provide a summary of historical developments in this field, to explain how the world ended up where it is. I won&amp;rsquo;t do that, especially as I first encountered parsing many years ago, when the only tools (lex, bison, yacc) were so complex to operate I took the pledge to abstain. Nevertheless, it&amp;rsquo;s good to know such tools are still available, so here are a few references:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://directory.fsf.org/wiki/Flex&#34;&gt;Flex&lt;/a&gt; is a successor to &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lex_programming_tool&#34;&gt;lex&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gnu.org/software/bison/&#34;&gt;Bison&lt;/a&gt; is a successor to &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yacc&#34;&gt;yacc&lt;/a&gt;. These are well-established (old) tools to keep you from having to build a lexer or parser by hand. This article explains why I (still) don&amp;rsquo;t use any of these.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;but-why-study-lexing-and-parsing&#34;&gt;But Why Study Lexing and Parsing?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many situations where the only path to a solution requires a lexer and a parser:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Running a program&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is trivial to understand, but not to implement. In order to run a program we need to set up a range of pre-conditions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Define the language, perhaps called Perl&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write a compiler (combined lexer and parser) for that language&amp;rsquo;s grammar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write a program in that language&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lex and parse&lt;/em&gt; the source code&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all, it must be syntactically correct before we run it. If not, we display syntax errors. The real point of this step is to determine the programmer&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;intention&lt;/em&gt;, that is, the reason for writing the code. We don&amp;rsquo;t &lt;em&gt;run&lt;/em&gt; the code in this step, but we do get output. How do we do that?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Run the code&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we can gaze at the output which, hopefully, is correct. Otherwise, perhaps, we must find and fix logic errors.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rendering a web page of HTML + content&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The steps are identical to those of the first example, with HTML replacing Perl, although I can&amp;rsquo;t bring myself to call writing HTML writing a program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time, we&amp;rsquo;re asking: What is the web page designer&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;intention&lt;/em&gt;. What would they like to render and how? Of course, syntax checking is far looser that with a programming language, but must still be undertaken. For instance, here&amp;rsquo;s an example of clearly-corrupt HTML which can be parsed by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jeffreykegler.com/marpa&#34;&gt;Marpa&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;        &amp;lt;title&amp;gt;Short&amp;lt;/title&amp;gt;&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;Text&amp;lt;/head&amp;gt;&amp;lt;head&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Marpa::HTML&#34;&gt;Marpa::HTML&lt;/a&gt; for more details. So far, I have used &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Marpa::R2&#34;&gt;Marpa::R2&lt;/a&gt; in all my work, which does not involve HTML.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rendering an image, perhaps in SVG&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider this file, written in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.graphviz.org/content/dot-language&#34;&gt;DOT&lt;/a&gt; language, as used by the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.graphviz.org/&#34;&gt;Graphviz&lt;/a&gt; graph visualizer (&lt;em&gt;teamwork.dot&lt;/em&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;        digraph Perl
        {
        graph [ rankdir=&amp;quot;LR&amp;quot; ]
        node  [ fontsize=&amp;quot;12pt&amp;quot; shape=&amp;quot;rectangle&amp;quot; style=&amp;quot;filled, solid&amp;quot; ]
        edge  [ color=&amp;quot;grey&amp;quot; ]
        &amp;quot;Teamwork&amp;quot; [ fillcolor=&amp;quot;yellow&amp;quot; ]
        &amp;quot;Victory&amp;quot;  [ fillcolor=&amp;quot;red&amp;quot; ]
        &amp;quot;Teamwork&amp;quot; -&amp;gt; &amp;quot;Victory&amp;quot; [ label=&amp;quot;is the key to&amp;quot; ]
        }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given this &amp;ldquo;program&amp;rdquo;, a renderer give effects to the author&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;intention&lt;/em&gt; by rendering an image:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/_pub_2012_10_an-overview-of-lexing-and-parsing/teamwork.svg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s required to do that? As above, &lt;em&gt;lex&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;parse&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;render&lt;/em&gt;. Using Graphviz&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;dot&lt;/code&gt; command to carry out these tasks, we would run:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;        shell&amp;gt; dot -Tsvg teamwork.dot &amp;gt; teamwork.svg
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: Files used in these examples can be downloaded from &lt;a href=&#34;http://savage.net.au/Ron/html/graphviz2.marpa/teamwork.tgz&#34;&gt;http://savage.net.au/Ron/html/graphviz2.marpa/teamwork.tgz&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The link to the DOT language points to a definition of DOT&amp;rsquo;s syntax, written in a somewhat casual version of BNF: &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Backus%E2%80%93Naur_Form&#34;&gt;Backus-Naur Form&lt;/a&gt;. This is significant, as it&amp;rsquo;s usually straight-forward to translate a BNF description of a language into code within a lexer and parser.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rendering that same image, using a different language in the input file&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suppose that you decide that the Graphviz language is too complex, and hence you write a wrapper around it, so end users can code in a simplified version of that language. This actually happened, with the original effort available in the now-obsolete Perl module &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Graph::Easy&#34;&gt;Graph::Easy&lt;/a&gt;. Tels, the author, devised his own very clever &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Little_languages&#34;&gt;little language&lt;/a&gt;, which he called &lt;a href=&#34;http://bloodgate.com/perl/graph/manual/&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Graph::Easy&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I took over maintenance of &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Graph::Easy&#34;&gt;Graph::Easy&lt;/a&gt;, I found the code too complex to read, let alone work on, so I wrote another implementation of the lexer and parser, released as &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Graph::Easy::Marpa&#34;&gt;Graph::Easy::Marpa&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ll have much more to say about that in another article. For now, let&amp;rsquo;s discuss the previous graph rewritten in &lt;code&gt;Graph::Easy&lt;/code&gt; (&lt;em&gt;teamwork.easy&lt;/em&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;        graph {rankdir: LR}
        node {fontsize: 12pt; shape: rectangle; style: filled, solid}
        edge {color: grey}
        [Teamwork]{fillcolor: yellow}
        -&amp;gt; {label: is the key to}
        [Victory]{fillcolor: red}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s simpler for sure, but how does &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Graph::Easy::Marpa&#34;&gt;Graph::Easy::Marpa&lt;/a&gt; work? Easy: &lt;em&gt;lex&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;parse&lt;/em&gt;, render. More samples of &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Graph::Easy::Marpa&#34;&gt;Graph::Easy::Marpa&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s work are &lt;a href=&#34;http://savage.net.au/Perl-modules/html/graph.easy.marpa/index.html&#34;&gt;my Graph::Easy::Marpa examples&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should be clear by now that lexing and parsing are in fact widespread, although they often operate out of sight, with only their rendered output visible to the average programmer, user, or web surfer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these problems have in common a complex but well-structured source text format, with a bit of hand-waving over the tacky details available to authors of documents in HTML. In each case, it is the responsibility of the programmer writing the lexer and parser to honour the intention of the original text&amp;rsquo;s author. We can only do that by recognizing each token in the input as a discrete unit of meaning (where a word such as &lt;code&gt;print&lt;/code&gt; &lt;em&gt;means&lt;/em&gt; to output something of the author&amp;rsquo;s choosing), and by bringing that meaning to fruition (for &lt;code&gt;print&lt;/code&gt;, to make the output visible on a device).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all that I can safely claim that the ubiquity and success of lexing and parsing justify their recognition as vital constituents in the world of software engineering. Why study them indeed!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;good-solutions-and-home-grown-solutions&#34;&gt;Good Solutions and Home-grown Solutions&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s another—more significant— reason to discuss lexing and parsing: to train programmers, without expertise in such matters, to resist the understandable urge to opt for using tools they are already familiar with, with regexps being the obvious choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure, regexps suit many simple cases, and the old standbys of flex and bison are always available, but now there&amp;rsquo;s a new kid on the block: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jeffreykegler.com/marpa&#34;&gt;Marpa&lt;/a&gt;. Marpa draws heavily from theoretical work done over many decades, and comes in various forms:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;libmarpa&lt;br /&gt;
Hand-crafted in C.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Marpa::XS&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The Perl and C-based interface to the previous version of libmarpa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Marpa::R2&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The Perl and C-based interface to the most recent version of libmarpa. This is the version I use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Marpa::R2::Advanced::Thin&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The newest and thinnest interface to libmarpa, which documents how to make Marpa accessible to non-Perl languages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem, of course, is whether or not any of these are a good, or even excellent, choice. Good news! Marpa&amp;rsquo;s advantages are huge. It&amp;rsquo;s well tested, which alone is of great significance. It has a Perl interface, so that I can specify my task in Perl and let Marpa handle the details. It has its own &lt;a href=&#34;http://groups.google.com/group/marpa-parser?hl=en&#34;&gt;Marpa Google Group&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s already used by various modules on the CPAN (see &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/search?q=Marpa&#34;&gt;a search for Marpa on the CPAN&lt;/a&gt;); Open Source says you can see exactly how other people use it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even better, Marpa has a very simple syntax, once you get used to it, of course! If you&amp;rsquo;re having trouble, just post on the Google Group. (If you&amp;rsquo;ve ever worked with flex and bison, you&amp;rsquo;ll be astonished at how simple it is to drive Marpa.) Marpa is also very fast, with libmarpa written in C. Its speed is a bit surprising, because new technology usually needs some time to surpass established technology while delivering the all-important stability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, Marpa is being improved all the time. For instance, recently the author eliminated the dependency on Glib, to improve portability. His work continues, so that users can expect a series of incremental improvements for some time to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I myself use Marpa in &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Graph::Easy::Marpa&#34;&gt;Graph::Easy::Marpa&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/GraphViz2::Marpa&#34;&gt;GraphViz2::Marpa&lt;/a&gt;, but this is not an article on Marpa in specific.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-lexer-s-job-description&#34;&gt;The Lexer&amp;rsquo;s Job Description&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned earlier, the stages conveniently, run in English alphabetical order. First you lex. Then you parse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, I use &lt;em&gt;lexing&lt;/em&gt; to mean the comparatively simple (compared to parsing) process of tokenising a stream of text, which means chopping that input stream into discrete tokens and identifying the type of each. The output is a new stream, this time of stand-alone tokens. (Lexing is comparatively simpler than parsing.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lexing does nothing more than identify tokens. Questions about the meanings of those tokens or their acceptable order or anything else are matters for the parser. The lexer will say: I have found another token and have identified it as being of some type T. Hence, for each recognized token, the lexer will produce two items:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The type of the token&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The value of the token&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the lexing process happens repeatedly, the lexer will produce an output of an array of token elements, with each element needing at least these two components: type and value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In practice, I prefer to represent these elements as a hashref:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;        {
                count =&amp;gt; $integer, # 1 .. N.
                name  =&amp;gt; &#39;&#39;,       # Unused.
                type  =&amp;gt; $string,  # The type of the token.
                value =&amp;gt; $value,   # The value from the input stream.
        }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip; with the array managed by an object of type &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Set::Tiny&#34;&gt;Set::Tiny&lt;/a&gt;. The latter module has many nice methods, making it very suitable for such work. Up until recently I used &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Set::Array&#34;&gt;Set::Array&lt;/a&gt;, which I did not write but which I do now maintain. However, insights from a recent report of mine, &lt;a href=&#34;http://savage.net.au/Perl-modules/html/setops.report.html&#34;&gt;Set-handling modules&lt;/a&gt;, comparing a range of similar modules, has convinced me to switch to &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Set::Tiny&#34;&gt;Set::Tiny&lt;/a&gt;. For an application which might best store its output in a tree, the Perl module &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Tree::DAG_Node&#34;&gt;Tree::DAG_Node&lt;/a&gt; is superb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;count&lt;/code&gt; field, apparently redundant, is sometimes useful in the clean-up phase of the lexer, which may need to combine tokens unnecessarily split by the regexps used in lexing. Also, it is available to the parser if needed, so I always include it in the hashref.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;name&lt;/code&gt; field really is unused, but gives people who fork or sub-class my code a place to work with their own requirements, without worrying that their edits will affect the fundamental code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-parser-s-job-description&#34;&gt;The Parser&amp;rsquo;s Job Description&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The parser concerns itself with the context in which each token appears, which is a way of saying it cares about whether or not the sequence and combination of tokens actually detected fits the expected grammar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideally, the grammar is provided in BNF Form. This makes it easy to translate into the form acceptable to Marpa. If you have a grammar in another form, your work will probably be more difficult, simply because someone else has &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; done the hard work of formalizing the grammar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s a parser. What&amp;rsquo;s a grammar?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;grammars-and-sub-grammars&#34;&gt;Grammars and Sub-grammars&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I showed an example grammar earlier, for the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.graphviz.org/content/dot-language&#34;&gt;DOT&lt;/a&gt; format. How does a normal person understand a block of text written in BNF? Training helps. Besides that, I&amp;rsquo;ve gleaned a few things from practical experience. To us beginners eventually comes the realization that grammars, no matter how formally defined, contain within them two sub-grammars:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sub-grammar-1&#34;&gt;Sub-grammar #1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One sub-grammar specifies what a token looks like, meaning the range of forms it can assume in the input stream. If the lexer detects an incomprehensible candidate, the lexer can generate an error, or it can activate a strategy called &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.perl.org/users/jeffrey_kegler/2011/11/marpa-and-the-ruby-slippers.html&#34;&gt;Ruby Slippers&lt;/a&gt; (no relation to the Ruby programming language). This technique was named by Jeffrey Kegler, the author of Marpa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In simple terms, the Ruby Slippers strategy fiddles the current token (or an even larger section of the input stream) in a way that satisfies the grammar and restarts processing at the new synthesized token. Marpa is arguably unique in being able to do this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sub-grammar-2&#34;&gt;Sub-grammar #2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other sub-grammar specifies the allowable ways in which these tokens may combine, meaning if they don&amp;rsquo;t conform to the grammar, the code generates a syntax error of some sort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Easy enough?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I split the grammar into two sub-grammars because it helps me express my Golden Rule of Lexing and Parsing: &lt;em&gt;encode the first sub-grammar into the lexer and the second into the parser&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you know what tokens look like, you can tokenize the input stream by splitting it into separate tokens using a lexer. Then you give those tokens to the parser for (more) syntax checking, and for interpretation of what the user presumably intended with that specific input stream (combination of tokens).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That separation between lexing and parsing gives a clear plan-of-attack for any new project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case you think this is going to be complex, truly it only &lt;em&gt;sounds&lt;/em&gt; complicated. Yes, I&amp;rsquo;ve introduced a few new concepts (and will introduce a few more), but don&amp;rsquo;t despair. It&amp;rsquo;s not really that difficult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For any given grammar, you must somehow and somewhere manage the complexity of the question &amp;ldquo;Is this a valid document?&amp;rdquo; Recognizing a token with a regex is easy. (That&amp;rsquo;s probably why so many people stop at the point of using regexes to pick at documents instead of moving to parsing.) Keeping track of the context in which that token appeared, and the context in which a grammar allows that token, is hard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The complexity of setting up and managing a formal grammar and its implementation seems like a lot of work, but it&amp;rsquo;s a specified and well understood mechanism you don&amp;rsquo;t have to reinvent every time. The lexer and parser approach limits the code you have to write to two things: a set of rules for how to construct tokens within a grammar and a set of rules for what happens when we construct a valid combination of tokens. This limit allows you to focus on the important part of the application—determining what a document which conforms to the grammar means (the author&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;intention&lt;/em&gt;)—and less on the mechanics of verifying that a document matches the grammar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, you can focus on &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; you want to do with a document more than &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; to do something with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;coding-the-lexer&#34;&gt;Coding the Lexer&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lexer&amp;rsquo;s job is to recognise tokens. Sub-grammar #1 specifies what those tokens look like. Any lexer will have to examine the input stream, possibly one character at a time, to see if the current input, appended to the immediately preceding input, fits the definition of a token.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A programmer can write a lexer in many ways. I do so by combining regexps with a DFA (&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deterministic_finite_automaton&#34;&gt;Discrete Finite Automaton&lt;/a&gt;) module. The blog entry &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.perl.org/users/andrew_rodland/2012/01/more-marpa-madness.html&#34;&gt;More Marpa Madness&lt;/a&gt; discusses using Marpa in the lexer (as well as in the parser, which is where I use it).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is a DFA? Abusing any reasonable definition, let me describe them thusly. The &lt;em&gt;Deterministic&lt;/em&gt; part means that given the same input at the same stage, you&amp;rsquo;ll always get the same result. The &lt;em&gt;Finite&lt;/em&gt; part means the input stream only contains a limited number of different tokens, which simplifies the code. The &lt;em&gt;Automata&lt;/em&gt; is, essentially, a software machine—a program. DFAs are also often called STTs (State Transition Tables).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do you make this all work in Perl? &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/&#34;&gt;MetaCPAN&lt;/a&gt; is your friend! In particular, I like to use &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Set::FA::Element&#34;&gt;Set::FA::Element&lt;/a&gt; to drive the process. For candidate alternatives I assembled a list of Perl modules with relevance in the area, while cleaning up the docs for &lt;code&gt;Set::FA&lt;/code&gt;. See &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Set::FA#See-Also&#34;&gt;Alternatives to Set::FA&lt;/a&gt;. I did not write &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Set::FA&#34;&gt;Set::FA&lt;/a&gt;, nor &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Set::FA::Element&#34;&gt;Set::FA::Element&lt;/a&gt;, but I now maintain them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transforming a grammar from BNF (or whatever form you use) into a DFA provides:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Insight into the problem&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To cast BNF into regexps means you must understand exactly what the grammar definition is saying.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Clarity of formulation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You end up with a spreadsheet which simply and clearly encodes your understanding of tokens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spreadsheet? Yes, I store the derived regexps, along with other information, in a spreadsheet. I even incorporate this spreadsheet into the source code.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;back-to-the-finite-automaton&#34;&gt;Back to the Finite Automaton&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In practice, building a lexer is a process of reading and rereading, many times, the definition of the BNF (here the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.graphviz.org/content/dot-language&#34;&gt;DOT&lt;/a&gt; language) to build up the corresponding set of regexps to handle each case. This is laborious work, no doubt about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, by using a regexp like &lt;code&gt;/[a-zA-Z_][a-zA-Z_0-9]*/&lt;/code&gt;, you can get Perl&amp;rsquo;s regexp engine to intelligently gobble up characters as long as they fit the definition. In plain English, this regexp says: start with a letter, upper- or lower-case, or an underline, followed by 0 or more letters, digits or underlines. Look familiar? It&amp;rsquo;s very close to the Perl definition of &lt;code&gt;\w&lt;/code&gt;, but it disallows leading digits. Actually, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.graphviz.org/content/dot-language&#34;&gt;DOT&lt;/a&gt; disallows them (in certain circumstances), but DOT does allow pure numbers in certain circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is the result of all of these hand-crafted regexps? They&amp;rsquo;re &lt;em&gt;data&lt;/em&gt; fed into the DFA, along with the input stream. The output of the DFA is a flag that signifies Yes or No, the input stream matches/doesn&amp;rsquo;t match the token definitions specified by the given regexps. Along the way, the DFA calls a callback functions each time it recognizes a token, stockpiling them. At the end of the run, you can output them as a stream of tokens, each with its identifying type, as per The Lexer&amp;rsquo;s Job Description I described earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A note about callbacks: Sometimes it&amp;rsquo;s easier to design a regexp to capture more than seems appropriate, and to use code in the callback to chop up what&amp;rsquo;s been captured, outputting several token elements as a consequence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because developing the state transition table is such an iterative process, I recommend creating various test files with all sorts of example programs, as well as scripts with very short names to run the tests (short names because you&amp;rsquo;re going to be running these scripts an unbelievable number of times&amp;hellip;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;states&#34;&gt;States&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are states and why do you care about them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At any moment, the STT (automation, software machine) is in precisely &lt;em&gt;on)&lt;/em&gt; state. Perhaps it has not yet received even one token (so that it&amp;rsquo;s in the start state), or perhaps it has just finished processing the previous one. Whatever the case, the code maintains information so as to know exactly what state it is in, and this leads to knowing exactly what set of tokens is now acceptable. That is, it has a set of tokens, any of which will be legal in its current state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The implication is this: you must associate each regexp with a specific state and visa versa. Furthermore, the machine will remain in its current state as long as each new input character matches a regexp belonging to the current state. It will jump (make a transition) to a new state when that character does not match.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;sample-lexer-code&#34;&gt;Sample Lexer Code&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider this simplistic code from the synopsis of &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Set::FA::Element&#34;&gt;Set::FA::Element&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;        my($dfa) = Set::FA::Element -&amp;gt; new
        (
                accepting   =&amp;gt; [&#39;baz&#39;],
                start       =&amp;gt; &#39;foo&#39;,
                transitions =&amp;gt;
                [
                        [&#39;foo&#39;, &#39;b&#39;, &#39;bar&#39;],
                        [&#39;foo&#39;, &#39;.&#39;, &#39;foo&#39;],
                        [&#39;bar&#39;, &#39;a&#39;, &#39;foo&#39;],
                        [&#39;bar&#39;, &#39;b&#39;, &#39;bar&#39;],
                        [&#39;bar&#39;, &#39;c&#39;, &#39;baz&#39;],
                        [&#39;baz&#39;, &#39;.&#39;, &#39;baz&#39;],
                ],
        );
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;em&gt;transitions&lt;/em&gt; parameter the first line says: &amp;ldquo;foo&amp;rdquo; is a state&amp;rsquo;s name, and &amp;ldquo;b&amp;rdquo; is a regexp. Jump to state &amp;ldquo;bar&amp;rdquo; if the next input char matches that regexp. Other lines are similar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To use &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Set::FA::Element&#34;&gt;Set::FA::Element&lt;/a&gt;, you must prepare that transitions parameter matching this format. Now you see the need for states and regexps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is code I&amp;rsquo;ve used, taken directly from &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/GraphViz2::Marpa::Lexer::DFA&#34;&gt;GraphViz2::Marpa::Lexer::DFA&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;        Set::FA::Element -&amp;gt; new
        (
                accepting   =&amp;gt; \@accept,
                actions     =&amp;gt; \%actions,
                die_on_loop =&amp;gt; 1,
                logger      =&amp;gt; $self -&amp;gt; logger,
                start       =&amp;gt; $self -&amp;gt; start,
                transitions =&amp;gt; \@transitions,
                verbose     =&amp;gt; $self -&amp;gt; verbose,
        );
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s discuss these parameters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;accepting&lt;br /&gt;
This is an arrayref of state names. After processing the entire input stream, if the machine ends up in one of these states, it has accepted that input stream. All that means is that every input token matched an appropriate regexp, where &amp;ldquo;appropriate&amp;rdquo; means every char matched the regexp belonging to the current state, whatever the state was at the instant that char was input.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;actions&lt;br /&gt;
This is a hashref of function names so that the machine can call a function, optionally, upon entering or leaving any state. That&amp;rsquo;s how the stockpile for recognized tokens works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I wrote these functions myself and wrote the rules to attach each to a particular combination of state and regexp, I encoded into each function the knowledge of what type of token the DFA has matched. That&amp;rsquo;s how the stockpile ends up with (token, type) pairs to output at the end of the run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;die_on_loop&lt;br /&gt;
This flag, if true, tells the DFA to stop if none of the regexps belonging to the current state match the current input char. Rather than looping forever, stop. Throw an exception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might wonder what stopping automatically is not the default, or even mandatory. The default behavior allows you to try to recover from this bad state, or at least give a reasonable error message, before dying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;logger&lt;br /&gt;
This is an (optional) logger object.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;start&lt;br /&gt;
This is the name of the state in which the STT starts, so the code knows which regexp(s) to try upon receiving the very first character of input.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;transitions&lt;br /&gt;
This is a potentially large arrayref which lists separately for all states all the regexps which may possibly match the current input char.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;verbose&lt;br /&gt;
Specifies how much to report if the logger object is not defined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all of that configured, the next problem is how to prepare the grammar in such a way as to fit into this parameter list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;coding-the-lexer-revisited&#34;&gt;Coding the Lexer - Revisited&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The coder thus needs to develop regexps etc which can be fed directly into the chosen DFA, here &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Set::FA::Element&#34;&gt;Set::FA::Element&lt;/a&gt;, or which can be transformed somehow into a format acceptable to that module. So far I haven&amp;rsquo;t actually said how I do that, but now it&amp;rsquo;s time to be explicit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use a spreadsheet with nine columns:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start&lt;br /&gt;
This contains one word, &amp;ldquo;Yes&amp;rdquo;, against the name of the state which is the start state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accept&lt;br /&gt;
This contains the word &amp;ldquo;Yes&amp;rdquo; against the name of any state which will be an accepting state (the machine has matched an input stream).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;State&lt;br /&gt;
This is the name of the state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Event&lt;br /&gt;
This is a regexp. The event will fire the current input char matches this regexp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the regexp belongs to a given state, we know the DFA will only process regexps associated with the current state, of which there will be usually one or or at most a few.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When there are multiple regexps per state, I leave all other columns empty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next&lt;br /&gt;
The name of the &amp;ldquo;next&amp;rdquo; state to which the STT will jump if the current char matches the regexp given on the same line of the spreadsheet (in the current state of course).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Entry&lt;br /&gt;
The optional name of the function the DFA is to call upon (just before) entry to the (new) state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exit&lt;br /&gt;
The optional name of the function the DFA is to call upon exiting from the current state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regexp&lt;br /&gt;
This is a working column, in which I put formulas so that I can refer to them in various places in the Event column. It is not passed to the DFA in the transitions parameter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interpretation&lt;br /&gt;
Comments to myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve put the STT for &lt;a href=&#34;http://savage.net.au/Perl-modules/html/graphviz2.marpa/default.stt.html&#34;&gt;STT for GraphViz2::Marpa&lt;/a&gt; online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This spreadsheet has various advantages:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Legibility.&lt;/em&gt; It is very easy to read and to work with. Don&amp;rsquo;t forget, to start with you&amp;rsquo;ll be basically switching back and forth between the grammar definition document (hopefully in BNF) and this spreadsheet. I don&amp;rsquo;t do much (any) coding at this stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Exportability.&lt;/em&gt; Because I have no code yet, there are several possibilities. I could read the spreadsheet directly. The two problems with this approach are the complexity of the code (in the external module which does the reading of course), and the slowness of loading and running this code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I use &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.libreoffice.org/&#34;&gt;LibreOffice&lt;/a&gt; I can either force end-users to install &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/OpenOffice::OODoc&#34;&gt;OpenOffice::OODoc&lt;/a&gt;, or export the spreadsheet as an Excel file, in order to avail themselves of this option. I have chosen to not support reading the&lt;em&gt;.ods&lt;/em&gt; file directly in the modules (&lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Graph::Easy::Marpa&#34;&gt;Graph::Easy::Marpa&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/GraphViz2::Marpa&#34;&gt;GraphViz2::Marpa&lt;/a&gt;) I ship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could alternately export the spreadsheet to a CSV file first. This way, we can read a CSV file into the DFA fairly quickly, without loading the module which reads spreadsheets.
Be careful here with LibreOffice, because it forces you to use Unicode for the spreadsheet but exports odd character sequences, such as double-quotes as the three byte sequence 0xe2, 0x80, 0x9c. When used in a regexp, this sequence will never match a &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; double-quote in your input stream. Sigh. Do No Evil. If only.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could also incorporate the spreadsheet directly into my code. This is my favorite approach. I do this in two stages. I export my data to a CSV file, then append that file to the end of the source code of the module, after the &lt;code&gt;__DATA__&lt;/code&gt; token.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such in-line data can be accessed effortlessly by the very neat and very fast module &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Data::Section::Simple&#34;&gt;Data::Section::Simple&lt;/a&gt;. Because Perl has already loaded the module—and is executing it—there is essentially no overhead whatsoever in reading data from within it. Don&amp;rsquo;t you just love Perl! And MetaCPAN of course. And a community which contributes such wondrous code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An advantage of this alternative is that it allows end users to edit the shipped &lt;em&gt;.csv&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;.ods&lt;/em&gt; files, after which they can use a command line option on scripts to read their own file, overriding the built-in STT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all this, it&amp;rsquo;s just a matter of code to read and validate the structure of the STT&amp;rsquo;s data, then to reformat it into what &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Set::FA::Element&#34;&gt;Set::FA::Element&lt;/a&gt; demands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;coding-the-parser&#34;&gt;Coding the Parser&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, you know how to incorporate the first sub-grammar into the design and code of the lexer. You also know that the second sub-grammar must be encoded into the parser, for that&amp;rsquo;s how the parser performs syntax checking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How you do this depends intimately on which pre-existing module, if any, you choose to use to aid the development of the parser. Because I choose Marpa (currently &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Marpa::R2&#34;&gt;Marpa::R2&lt;/a&gt;), I am orienting this article to that module. However, only in the next article will I deal in depth with Marpa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whichever tool you choose, think of the parsing process like this: Your input stream is a set of pre-defined tokens (probably but necessarily output from the lexer). You must now specify all possible legal combinations of those tokens. This is the &lt;em&gt;syntax&lt;/em&gt; of the language (or, more accurately, the &lt;em&gt;remainder&lt;/em&gt; of the syntax, because the first sub-grammar has already handled all of the definitions of legal tokens). At this point, assume all incoming tokens are legal. In other words, the parser will not try to parse and run a program containing token-based syntax errors, although it may contain logic errors (even if written in Perl :-).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A combination of tokens which does not match any of the given legal combinations can be immediately rejected as a syntax error. Keep in mind that the friendliest compilers find as many syntax errors as possible per parse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because this check takes place on a token-by-token basis, you (ought to) know precisely which token triggered the error, which means that you can emit a nice error message, identifying the culprit and its context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;sample-parser-code&#34;&gt;Sample Parser Code&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a sample of a &lt;code&gt;Marpa::R2&lt;/code&gt; grammar (adapted from its synopsis):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;        my($grammar) = Marpa::R2::Grammar -&amp;gt; new
        ({
                actions =&amp;gt; &#39;My_Actions&#39;,
                start   =&amp;gt; &#39;Expression&#39;,
                rules   =&amp;gt;
                [
                        { lhs =&amp;gt; &#39;Expression&#39;, rhs =&amp;gt; [qw/Term/] },
                        { lhs =&amp;gt; &#39;Term&#39;,       rhs =&amp;gt; [qw/Factor/] },
                        { lhs =&amp;gt; &#39;Factor&#39;,     rhs =&amp;gt; [qw/Number/] },
                        { lhs =&amp;gt; &#39;Term&#39;,       rhs =&amp;gt; [qw/Term Add Term/],
                                action =&amp;gt; &#39;do_add&#39;
                        },
                        { lhs =&amp;gt; &#39;Factor&#39;,     rhs =&amp;gt; [qw/Factor Multiply Factor/],
                                action =&amp;gt; &#39;do_multiply&#39;
                        },
                ],
                default_action =&amp;gt; &#39;do_something&#39;,
        });
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the differences between this and the calls to &lt;code&gt;Set::FA::Element     -&amp;gt; new()&lt;/code&gt; in the lexer example, these two snippets are basically the same:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;actions&lt;br /&gt;
This is the name of a Perl package in which Marpa will look for actions such as &lt;code&gt;do_add()&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;do_multiply()&lt;/code&gt;. (Okay, the lexer has no such option, as it defaults to the current package.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;start&lt;br /&gt;
This is the &lt;em&gt;lhs&lt;/em&gt; name of the rule to start with, as with the lexer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;rules&lt;br /&gt;
This is an arrayref of &lt;em&gt;rule descriptors&lt;/em&gt; defining the syntax of the grammar. This is the lexer&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;transitions&lt;/em&gt; parameter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;default_action&lt;br /&gt;
Use this (optional) callback as the action for any rule element which does not explicitly specify its own action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The real problem is recasting the syntax from BNF, or whatever, into a set of &lt;em&gt;rule descriptors&lt;/em&gt;. How do you think about this problem? I suggest contrast-and-compare real code with what the grammar says it must be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the &lt;em&gt;teamwork.dot&lt;/em&gt; file I explained earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;        digraph Perl
        {
        graph [ rankdir=&amp;quot;LR&amp;quot; ]
        node  [ fontsize=&amp;quot;12pt&amp;quot; shape=&amp;quot;rectangle&amp;quot; style=&amp;quot;filled, solid&amp;quot; ]
        edge  [ color=&amp;quot;grey&amp;quot; ]
        &amp;quot;Teamwork&amp;quot; [ fillcolor=&amp;quot;yellow&amp;quot; ]
        &amp;quot;Victory&amp;quot;  [ fillcolor=&amp;quot;red&amp;quot; ]
        &amp;quot;Teamwork&amp;quot; -&amp;gt; &amp;quot;Victory&amp;quot; [ label=&amp;quot;is the key to&amp;quot; ]
        }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general, a valid &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.graphviz.org/&#34;&gt;Graphviz&lt;/a&gt; (DOT) graph must start with one of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;        strict digraph $id {...} # Case 1. $id is a variable.
        strict digraph     {...}
        strict   graph $id {...} # Case 3
        strict   graph     {...}
               digraph $id {...} # Case 5
               digraph     {...}
                 graph $id {...} # Case 7
                 graph     {...}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip; as indeed this real code does. The graph&amp;rsquo;s id is &lt;em&gt;Perl&lt;/em&gt;, which is case 5. If you&amp;rsquo;ve ever noticed that you can write a BNF as a tree (right?), you can guess what comes next. I like to write my &lt;em&gt;rule descriptors&lt;/em&gt; from the root down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drawing this as a tree gives:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;             DOT&#39;s Grammar
                  |
                  V
        ---------------------
        |                   |
     strict                 |
        |                   |
        ---------------------
                  |
                  V
        ---------------------
        |                   |
     digraph     or       graph
        |                   |
        ---------------------
                  |
                  V
        ---------------------
        |                   |
       $id                  |
        |                   |
        ---------------------
                  |
                  V
                {...}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;connecting-the-parser-back-to-the-lexer&#34;&gt;Connecting the Parser back to the Lexer&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wait, what&amp;rsquo;s this? Didn&amp;rsquo;t I say that &lt;em&gt;strict&lt;/em&gt; is optional. It&amp;rsquo;s not optional, not in the parser. It is optional in the DOT language, but I designed the lexer, and I therein ensured it would necessarily output &lt;em&gt;strict =&amp;gt; no&lt;/em&gt; when the author of the graph omitted the &lt;em&gt;strict&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the time the parser runs, &lt;em&gt;strict&lt;/em&gt; is no longer optional. I did this to make the life easier for consumers of the lexer&amp;rsquo;s output stream, such as authors of parsers. (Making the parser work less is often good.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, for &lt;em&gt;digraph&lt;/em&gt; &amp;lsquo;v&amp;rsquo; &lt;em&gt;graph&lt;/em&gt;, I designed the lexer to output &lt;em&gt;digraph =&amp;gt; &amp;lsquo;yes&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt; in one case and &lt;em&gt;digraph =&amp;gt; &amp;lsquo;no&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt; in the other. What does that mean? For &lt;em&gt;teamwork.dot&lt;/em&gt;, the lexer will output (in some convenient format) the equivalent of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;        strict   =&amp;gt; no
        digraph  =&amp;gt; yes
        graph_id =&amp;gt; Perl
        ...
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose &lt;em&gt;graph_id&lt;/em&gt; because the DOT language allows other types of ids, such as for nodes, edges, ports, and compass points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this produces the first six Marpa-friendly rules:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;        [
        {   # Root-level stuff.
                lhs =&amp;gt; &#39;graph_grammar&#39;,
                rhs =&amp;gt; [qw/prolog_and_graph/],
        },
        {
                lhs =&amp;gt; &#39;prolog_and_graph&#39;,
                rhs =&amp;gt; [qw/prolog_definition graph_sequence_definition/],
        },
        {   # Prolog stuff.
                lhs =&amp;gt; &#39;prolog_definition&#39;,
                rhs =&amp;gt; [qw/strict_definition digraph_definition graph_id_definition/],
        },
        {
                lhs    =&amp;gt; &#39;strict_definition&#39;,
                rhs    =&amp;gt; [qw/strict/],
                action =&amp;gt; &#39;strict&#39;, # &amp;lt;== Callback.
        },
        {
                lhs    =&amp;gt; &#39;digraph_definition&#39;,
                rhs    =&amp;gt; [qw/digraph/],
                action =&amp;gt; &#39;digraph&#39;, # &amp;lt;== Callback.
        },
        {
                lhs    =&amp;gt; &#39;graph_id_definition&#39;,
                rhs    =&amp;gt; [qw/graph_id/],
                action =&amp;gt; &#39;graph_id&#39;, # &amp;lt;== Callback.
        },
        ...
        ]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In English, all of this asserts that the graph as a whole consists of a prolog thingy, then a graph sequence thingy. (Remember, I made up the names &lt;code&gt;prolog_and_graph&lt;/code&gt;, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, a prolog consists of a strict thingy, which is now not optional, and then. a digraph thingy, which will turn out to match the lexer input of &lt;code&gt;/^(di|)graph$/&lt;/code&gt;, and the lexer output of &lt;code&gt;digraph =&amp;gt;     /^(yes|no)$/&lt;/code&gt;, and then a graph_id, which is optional, and then some other stuff which will be the precise definition of real live graphs, represented by &lt;code&gt;{...}&lt;/code&gt; in the list of the eight possible formats for the prolog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whew.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;something-fascinating-about-rule-descriptors&#34;&gt;Something Fascinating about Rule Descriptors&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take another look at those rule descriptors. They say &lt;em&gt;nothing&lt;/em&gt; about the values of the tokens! For instance, in &lt;em&gt;graph_id =&amp;gt; Perl&lt;/em&gt; what happens to ids such as &lt;em&gt;Perl&lt;/em&gt;. Nothing. They are ignored. That&amp;rsquo;s just how these grammars work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recall: it&amp;rsquo;s the job of the &lt;em&gt;lexer&lt;/em&gt; to identify valid graph ids based on the first sub-grammar. By the time the data hits the parser, we know we have a valid graph id, and as long as it plugs in to the &lt;em&gt;structure&lt;/em&gt; of the grammar in the right place, we are prepared to accept &lt;em&gt;any valid&lt;/em&gt; graph id. Hence &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Marpa::R2&#34;&gt;Marpa::R2&lt;/a&gt; does not even look at the graph id, which is a way of saying this one grammar works with &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; valid graph id.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This point also raises the tricky discussion of whether a specific implementation of lexer/parser code can or must keep the two phases separate, or whether in fact you can roll them into one without falling into the premature optimisation trap. I&amp;rsquo;ll just draw a veil over that discussion, as I&amp;rsquo;ve already declared my stance: my implementation uses two separate modules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;chains-and-trees&#34;&gt;Chains and Trees&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If these rules have to be chained into a tree, how do you handle the root? Consider this call to &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Marpa::R2&#34;&gt;Marpa::R2&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;new()&lt;/code&gt; method:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;        my($grammar) = Marpa::R2::Grammar -&amp;gt; new(... start =&amp;gt; &#39;graph_grammar&#39;, ...);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;graph_grammar&lt;/em&gt; is precisely the &lt;em&gt;lhs&lt;/em&gt; in the first rule descriptor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that, every rule&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;rhs&lt;/em&gt;, including the root&amp;rsquo;s, must be defined later in the list of rule descriptors. These definitions form the links in the chain. If you draw this, you&amp;rsquo;ll see the end result is a tree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the full &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Marpa::R2&#34;&gt;Marpa::R2&lt;/a&gt; grammar for DOT (as used in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/GraphViz2::Marpa&#34;&gt;GraphViz2::Marpa&lt;/a&gt; module) as an image: &lt;a href=&#34;http://savage.net.au/Ron/html/graphviz2.marpa/Marpa.Grammar.svg&#34;&gt;http://savage.net.au/Ron/html/graphviz2.marpa/Marpa.Grammar.svg&lt;/a&gt;. I created this image with (you guessed it!) &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.graphviz.org/&#34;&gt;Graphviz&lt;/a&gt; via &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/GraphViz2&#34;&gt;GraphViz2&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ve added numbers to node names in the tree, otherwise Graphviz would regard any two identical numberless names as one and the same node.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;less-coding-more-design&#34;&gt;Less Coding, More Design&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I&amp;rsquo;ll stop building the tree of the grammar (see the next article), and turn to some design issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;my-rules-of-thumb-for-writing-lexers-parsers&#34;&gt;My Rules-of-Thumb for Writing Lexers/Parsers&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The remainder of this document is to help beginners orient their thinking when tackling a problem they don&amp;rsquo;t yet have much experience in. Of course, if you&amp;rsquo;re an expert in lexing and parsing, feel free to ignore everything I say, and if you think I&amp;rsquo;ve misused lexing/parsing terminology here, please let me know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;eschew-premature-optimisation&#34;&gt;Eschew Premature Optimisation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yep, this old one again. It has various connotations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The lexer and the parser&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t aim to combine the lexer and parser, even though that might eventually happen. Do wait until the design of each is clear and finalized, before trying to jam them into a single module (or program).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The lexer and the tokens&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do make the lexer identify the existence of tokens, but not identify their ultimate role or meaning.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The lexer and context&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t make the lexer do context analysis. Do make the parser disambiguate tokens with multiple meanings, by using the context. Let the lexer do the hard work of identifying tokens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Context_analysis&#34;&gt;context analysis for businesses&lt;/a&gt;, for example, is probably not what you want either.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The lexer and syntax&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t make the lexer do syntax checking. This is effectively the same as the last point.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The lexer and its output&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t minimize the lexer&amp;rsquo;s output stream. For instance, don&amp;rsquo;t force the code which reads the lexer&amp;rsquo;s output to guess whether or not a variable-length set of tokens has ended. Output a specific token as a set terminator. The point of this token is to tell the parser exactly what&amp;rsquo;s going on. Without such a token, the next token has to do double-duty: Firstly it tells the parser the variable-length part has finished and secondly, it represents itself. Such overloading is unnecessary.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The State Transition Table&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the STT, don&amp;rsquo;t try to minimize the number of states, at least not until the code has stabilized (that is, it&amp;rsquo;s no longer under [rapid] development).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I develop my STTs in a spreadsheet program, which means a formula (regexp) stored in one cell can be referred to by any number of other cells. This is &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; convenient.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;divide-and-conquer&#34;&gt;Divide and Conquer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hmmm, another ancient &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aphorism&#34;&gt;aphorism&lt;/a&gt;. Naturally, these persist precisely because they&amp;rsquo;re telling us something important. Here, it means study the problem carefully, and deal with each part (lexer, parser) of it separately. Enough said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;don-t-reinvent-the-wheel&#34;&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t Reinvent the Wheel&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, I know &lt;em&gt;you&amp;rsquo;d&lt;/em&gt; never do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CPAN has plenty of Perl modules to help with things like the STT, such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Set::FA::Element&#34;&gt;Set::FA::Element&lt;/a&gt;. Check its See Also (in &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Set::FA&#34;&gt;Set::FA&lt;/a&gt;, actually) for other STT helpers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;be-patient-with-the-stt&#34;&gt;Be Patient with the STT&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developing the STT takes many iterations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The test cases&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For each iteration, prepare a separate test case.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The tiny script&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have a tiny script which runs a single test. Giving it a short—perhaps temporary—name, makes each test just that little bit easier to run. You can give it a meaningful name later, when including it in the distro.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The wrapper script&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have a script which runs all tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I keep the test data files in the data/ dir, and the scripts in the scripts/ dir. Then, creating tests in the t/ dir can perhaps use these two sets of helpers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I&amp;rsquo;ve only used &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Marpa::R2&#34;&gt;Marpa::R2&lt;/a&gt; for graphical work, the output of the wrapper is a web page, which makes viewing the results simple. I like to include (short) input or output text files on such a page, beside the SVG images. That way I can see at a glance what the input was and hence I can tell what the output should be without switching to the editor&amp;rsquo;s window.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a little bit of effort initially, but after that it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;so&lt;/em&gt; easy to check the output of the latest test.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve made available sample output from my wrapper scripts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://savage.net.au/Perl-modules/html/graphviz2/&#34;&gt;GraphViz2 (non-Marpa)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://savage.net.au/Perl-modules/html/graphviz2.marpa/&#34;&gt;GraphViz2::Marpa&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://savage.net.au/Perl-modules/html/graph.easy.marpa/&#34;&gt;Graph::Easy::Marpa&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;be-patient-with-the-grammar&#34;&gt;Be Patient with the Grammar&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with the STT, creating a grammar is at least for me very much a trial-and-error process. I offer a few tips:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tips:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Paper, not code&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good idea is not to start by coding with your editor, but to draw the grammar as a tree, on paper.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Watch out for alternatives&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This refers to when one of several tokens can appear in the input stream. Learn exactly how to draw that without trying to minimize the number of branches in the tree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, you will still need to learn how to code such a construct. Here&amp;rsquo;s a bit of code from &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Graph::Easy::Marpa&#34;&gt;Graph::Easy::Marpa&lt;/a&gt; which deals with this (note: we&amp;rsquo;re back to the &lt;code&gt;Graph::Easy&lt;/code&gt; language from here on!):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;        {   # Graph stuff.
                lhs =&amp;gt; &#39;graph_definition&#39;,
                rhs =&amp;gt; [qw/graph_statement/],
        },
        {
                lhs =&amp;gt; &#39;graph_statement&#39;, # 1 of 3.
                rhs =&amp;gt; [qw/group_definition/],
        },
        {
                lhs =&amp;gt; &#39;graph_statement&#39;, # 2 of 3.
                rhs =&amp;gt; [qw/node_definition/],
        },
        {
                lhs =&amp;gt; &#39;graph_statement&#39;, # 3 of 3.
                rhs =&amp;gt; [qw/edge_definition/],
        },
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is telling you that a graph thingy can be any one of a group, node, or edge. It&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Marpa::R2&#34;&gt;Marpa::R2&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s job to try these alternatives in order to see which (if any) matches the input stream. This ruleset represents a point in the input stream where one of several &lt;em&gt;alternatives&lt;/em&gt; can appear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tree looks like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;                        graph_definition
                               |
                               V
                        graph_statement
                               |
                               V
            ---------------------------------------
            |                  |                  |
            V                  V                  V
     group_definition   node_definition    edge_definition
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My comment &lt;code&gt;3 of 3&lt;/code&gt; says an edge can stand alone.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Watch out for sequences&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip; but consider the &lt;em&gt;node_definition&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;        {   # Node stuff.
                lhs =&amp;gt; &#39;node_definition&#39;,
                rhs =&amp;gt; [qw/node_sequence/],
                min =&amp;gt; 0,
        },
        {
                lhs =&amp;gt; &#39;node_sequence&#39;, # 1 of 4.
                rhs =&amp;gt; [qw/node_statement/],
        },
        {
                lhs =&amp;gt; &#39;node_sequence&#39;, # 2 of 4.
                rhs =&amp;gt; [qw/node_statement daisy_chain_node/],
        },
        {
                lhs =&amp;gt; &#39;node_sequence&#39;, # 3 of 4.
                rhs =&amp;gt; [qw/node_statement edge_definition/],
        },
        {
                lhs =&amp;gt; &#39;node_sequence&#39;, # 4 of 4.
                rhs =&amp;gt; [qw/node_statement group_definition/],
        },
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here &lt;code&gt;3 of 4&lt;/code&gt; tells you that nodes can be followed by edges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A realistic sample is: &lt;code&gt;[node_1] -&amp;gt; [node_2]&lt;/code&gt;, where &lt;code&gt;[x]&lt;/code&gt; is a node and &lt;code&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; is an edge, because an edge can be followed by a node (applying &lt;code&gt;3 of 4&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This full example represents a point in the input stream where one of several specific &lt;em&gt;sequences&lt;/em&gt; of tokens are allowed/expected. Here&amp;rsquo;s the &lt;em&gt;edge_definition&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;        {   # Edge stuff.
                lhs =&amp;gt; &#39;edge_definition&#39;,
                rhs =&amp;gt; [qw/edge_sequence/],
                min =&amp;gt; 0,
        },
        {
                lhs =&amp;gt; &#39;edge_sequence&#39;, # 1 of 4.
                rhs =&amp;gt; [qw/edge_statement/],
        },
        {
                lhs =&amp;gt; &#39;edge_sequence&#39;, # 2 of 4.
                rhs =&amp;gt; [qw/edge_statement daisy_chain_edge/],
        },
        {
                lhs =&amp;gt; &#39;edge_sequence&#39;, # 3 of 4.
                rhs =&amp;gt; [qw/edge_statement node_definition/],
        },
        {
                lhs =&amp;gt; &#39;edge_sequence&#39;, # 4 of 4.
                rhs =&amp;gt; [qw/edge_statement group_definition/],
        },
        {
                lhs =&amp;gt; &#39;edge_statement&#39;,
                rhs =&amp;gt; [qw/edge_name attribute_definition/],
        },
        {
                lhs    =&amp;gt; &#39;edge_name&#39;,
                rhs    =&amp;gt; [qw/edge_id/],
                action =&amp;gt; &#39;edge_id&#39;,
        },
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, I have to stop somewhere, so&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;wrapping-up-and-winding-down&#34;&gt;Wrapping Up and Winding Down&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope I&amp;rsquo;ve clarified what can be a complex and daunting part of programming, and I also hope I&amp;rsquo;ve convinced you that working in Perl, with the help of a spreadsheet, is the modern (or &amp;ldquo;only&amp;rdquo;) path to lexer and parser bliss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://savage.net.au/index.html&#34;&gt;Ron Savage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; is a longtime Perl programmer and prolific CPAN contributor.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Show off Perl in Plat_Forms 2012</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/pub/2012/08/show-off-perl-in-plat-forms-2012.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Aug 2012 13:21:52 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/pub/2012/08/show-off-perl-in-plat-forms-2012.html/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://raudss.us/&#34;&gt;Torsten Raudssus&lt;/a&gt;, who wrote in with this announcement.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;what-is-plat-forms&#34;&gt;What is Plat_Forms?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.plat-forms.org/&#34;&gt;Plat_Forms&lt;/a&gt; is a contest and competition in which top-class teams of three programmers compete to implement the same requirements for a web-based system within two days, using different technology platforms (e.g. Java, .NET, Perl, PHP, Python, Ruby, Scala, Smalltalk, JavaScript or what-have-you).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its purpose is not to determine &amp;ldquo;the&amp;rdquo; best platform, but rather to provide new insights into the real (rather than purported) pros, cons, and emergent properties of each platform. The evaluation will analyze many aspects of each solution, both external (scalability, functionality, reliability, security, performance, etc.) and internal (structure, modularity, understandability, flexibility, etc.). &lt;a href=&#34;#fn:footnote1&#34; class=&#34;footnote&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In just two days, the teams will implement as much of the requested functionality as they can and at the same time optimize the usefulness of the resulting system (functionality, usability, reliability, etc.), the understandability of the code, the modifiability of the system design, the efficiency and scalability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The contest will be conducted on October, 9-10, 2012. At the end of the 2 days, the teams hand over their source code and a turnkey-runnable VMware configuration of their system. &lt;a href=&#34;#fn:footnote2&#34; class=&#34;footnote&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The event is at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://maps.google.com/maps?q=Freie+Universit%C3%83%C2%A4t+Berlin,+Berlin,+Germany&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;ll=52.456009,13.293457&amp;amp;spn=22.652618,17.995605&amp;amp;sll=52.446685,13.285786&amp;amp;sspn=0.005509,0.004393&amp;amp;oq=Freie+Universit%C3%83%C2%A4t+berlin&amp;amp;t=h&amp;amp;hq=Freie+Universit%C3%83%C2%A4t+Berlin,+Berlin,+Germany&amp;amp;z=6&#34;&gt;Freie Universität Berlin in Berlin, Germany&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;perl-and-plat-forms&#34;&gt;Perl and Plat_Forms&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We, of course, want to represent Perl at this event. But we need teams and sponsorships to make this happen. Sadly the end of the registration is very near, but I think that we still have a chance to gather some productive and business effective working teams. A team has 3 people. We can register a maximum of 4 teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies may wish to enter a team of their own developers, as this gives them a chance to perform in a new and different environment, test themselves as a team against others, and see how other teams work together. As well as these opportunities, companies should also consider just sponsoring your most famous web framework to help send a team to show that it IS the best web framework! :-) Please help us make this a representative event for the modern Perl world. Sadly the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.plat-forms.org/results-2011&#34;&gt;results&lt;/a&gt; of last year weren&amp;rsquo;t that good, and we think, we can do better ;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to participate you must give us your details &lt;strong&gt;before Fri 2012-09-07&lt;/strong&gt;, as then the registration for the event closes. Our contact email is at the end. If you want to sponsor the event, you can also contact us after the registration end date, but please &lt;strong&gt;ASAP&lt;/strong&gt; :).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;contact-and-more-info&#34;&gt;Contact and More Info&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://raudss.us/&#34;&gt;Torsten Raudssus&lt;/a&gt; organizes the team and the sponsorships this year, so if you want to see your team here or would like to sponsor, please contact him (&lt;strong&gt;ASAP&lt;/strong&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:getty@cpan.org&#34;&gt;getty@cpan.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;#Plat_Forms on irc.perl.org&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://wiki.enlightenedperl.org/platforms2012&#34;&gt;Wiki Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Taken from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.plat-forms.org/&#34;&gt;Plat_Forms homepage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:footnote1&#34; class=&#34;reversefootnote&#34;&gt; ↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Taken from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.plat-forms.org/platforms-2012-rev-2-announcement&#34;&gt;Plat_Forms 2012 rev2 homepage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:footnote2&#34; class=&#34;reversefootnote&#34;&gt; ↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Embrace the Reluctant Perl Programmer</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/pub/2012/08/embrace-the-reluctant-perl-programmer.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Aug 2012 06:00:01 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/pub/2012/08/embrace-the-reluctant-perl-programmer.html/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;editor&amp;rsquo;s note: an earlier version of this article appeared at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.modernperlbooks.com/mt/2012/06/the-reluctant-perl-programmer.html&#34;&gt;The Reluctant Perl Programmer&lt;/a&gt;. Per the suggestion of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.askbjoernhansen.com/&#34;&gt;Ask Bjørn Hansen&lt;/a&gt;, this revision appears on Perl.com.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;who-we-are&#34;&gt;Who We Are&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all love Perl for different reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of us are programmers at heart. We love writing code. We love solving problems. We love that the distance between a problem and its solution is often a few lines of Perl which flow almost effortlessly from our minds through our fingers to our screens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of us are administrators. We love order. We love consistency. We love knowing that the scripts we wrote in 2008 or 1998 or 1988 run unmodified on every system we touch and we don&amp;rsquo;t have to think about it. We love that Perl doesn&amp;rsquo;t get in the way of our solving problems, whether we have a few minutes to fight a fire or a few weeks to plan something big.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of us are artists. We tinker. We play. We experiment. We write poems and steal features from wherever we can find them. We color outside the lines, and we love the flexibility we have to let our muses take us where they will, because we know that Perl will stay out of our way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of us are engineers. We love reliability. We love working software. We love when an upgrade is boring, when there are no unpleasant surprises. We love having the CPAN always within reach, with far more great software than we can ever use there for us whenever we want it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are many and we are varied. We build great things, and we collectively make up something even greater.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started with the vision of one man far too lazy and hubristic to solve a simple problem of cross-continent communication in the easy way. We grew as system administrators acknowledged that something more powerful and consistent than shell but simpler and more forgiving than C occupied an enormous ecological niche. Then we grew again as we realized that a web server could do more than just serve a plain static page, and that wrangling text was a job for a powerful, malleable language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along the way we built something grand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re pragmatic. We&amp;rsquo;re relentlessly pragmatic. We get things done. We iterate and improve and refine. We&amp;rsquo;ve stolen the Unix ethos (build many small tools, loosely coupled) and turned it into the CPAN and the ecosystem around the CPAN such that, at times, the CPAN is our language far more than Perl is, and many of us are all the better for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet not everyone can benefit from that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;who-they-are&#34;&gt;Who They Are&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We stand on little ceremony, but we do stand on ceremony. Some say the &amp;ldquo;right&amp;rdquo; way to write Perl is a thin layer of glue connecting as much of the CPAN as you need. Others suggest that the &amp;ldquo;right&amp;rdquo; way to write Perl is the code they wrote in 1987 when Larry first introduced his work to the world. Most of us are somewhere in between.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of us are somewhat wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider the plight of the reluctant programmer who faces a problem. He or she may pick up Perl, and what then?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where does this reluctant programmer go for information? Where does this reluctant programmer go for help?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where can you learn that the first dozen Perl tutorials easily found with a search engine are out of date or even wrong? Where can you learn that any of a dozen good text editors or IDEs are available and are better than &lt;code&gt;notepad.exe&lt;/code&gt;? Where can you learn how to install CPAN modules on ActivePerl (or that Strawberry Perl exists)—and more importantly, why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where can you go from &amp;ldquo;I need to process this report by the end of the day, and I have this text file, and I heard PERL was good for that?&amp;rdquo; to &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; can solve my problems with this language, and I never considered myself a programmer before!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those of us who&amp;rsquo;ve already undergone that transition may find it difficult to remember the days gone by. We&amp;rsquo;ve spent so long shaping the language, our tools, and our community to fit our problems, perhaps we&amp;rsquo;ve forgotten both the energy of promise and the growing pains of our youths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once upon a time, we all just wanted to get something done. There is much to admire in that approach. By all means, let us continue solving problems. Let us encourage people to solve their problems. Let us solve problems so well we never encounter them again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us not forget, however, to let reluctant programmers solve their problems immediately, however poorly, and only then help them open their eyes to the new possibilities their successes now afford them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;who-we-may-be&#34;&gt;Who We May Be&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This change is a change of mindset, not of technology nor tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With few exceptions, our growth will not come from those who already know the beauty of programming and the freedom of Perl. It will come from those who merely (as if it were a mere thing!) wish to solve a problem. If and when they succeed, they will need guidance to understand the new powers they possess, and we can be there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet first, we must accept that their goals are not our goals—not yet anyhow, and perhaps not never. Their goals may be strange to us, but they are no less valuable for their peculiarities. In truth, that makes them more valuable. These are more problems for us to solve, more ideas for us to adopt, and more people to welcome into our community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By all means, let us help them write great code and let us teach them the value of working with the community in the structures and per the techniques we have developed to harness our powers. Let us mentor them so that we may welcome them as peers and equals in ability (even as we acknowledge them as worthy of respect and praise from the start). Yet let us first welcome them into the greater Perl community with all of the pragmatism we embrace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;all-are-welcome&#34;&gt;All are Welcome&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reluctant programmers, come solve your problems with us. We are proud of what we have built together, but we build beautiful things and share them with you because in their &lt;em&gt;use&lt;/em&gt; we find the greatest beauty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are welcome here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;chromatic is the author of &lt;a href=&#34;http://modernperlbooks.com/books/modern_perl/&#34;&gt;Modern Perl: the book&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Perl Unicode Cookbook: Further Resources</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/pub/2012/06/perlunicook-further-resources.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jun 2012 06:00:01 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/pub/2012/06/perlunicook-further-resources.html/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This series has shown you several features of Unicode by example, as well as several techniques for working with Unicode correctly and easily with recent releases of Perl 5. By now you know more than many programmers do about Unicode, but your journey to mastery continues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perl 5 includes several pieces of documentation which explain Unicode and Perl&amp;rsquo;s Unicode support. See &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/perlunicode&#34;&gt;perlunicode&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/perluniprops&#34;&gt;perluniprops&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/perlre&#34;&gt;perlre&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/perlrecharclass&#34;&gt;perlrecharclass&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/perluniintro&#34;&gt;perluniintro&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/perlunitut&#34;&gt;perlunitut&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/perlunifaq&#34;&gt;perlunifaq&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perl 5 and the CPAN provide several modules and distributions to allow the effective use of Unicode. As of Perl 5.16, many of these are in the core library. Many of them work just as well with earlier versions of Perl 5, though for the best and most correct support for Unicode as a whole, consider using Perl 5.14 or 5.16.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These modules include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/PerlIO&#34;&gt;PerlIO&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/DB_File&#34;&gt;DB_File&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/DBM_Filter&#34;&gt;DBM_Filter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/DBM_Filter::utf8&#34;&gt;DBM_Filter::utf8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Encode&#34;&gt;Encode&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Encode::Locale&#34;&gt;Encode::Locale&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Unicode::UCD&#34;&gt;Unicode::UCD&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Unicode::Normalize&#34;&gt;Unicode::Normalize&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Unicode::GCString&#34;&gt;Unicode::GCString&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Unicode::LineBreak&#34;&gt;Unicode::LineBreak&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Unicode::Collate&#34;&gt;Unicode::Collate&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Unicode::Collate::Locale&#34;&gt;Unicode::Collate::Locale&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Unicode::Unihan&#34;&gt;Unicode::Unihan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Unicode::CaseFold&#34;&gt;Unicode::CaseFold&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Unicode::Tussle&#34;&gt;Unicode::Tussle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Lingua::JA::Romanize::Japanese&#34;&gt;Lingua::JA::Romanize::Japanese&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Lingua::ZH::Romanize::Pinyin&#34;&gt;Lingua::ZH::Romanize::Pinyin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Lingua::KO::Romanize::Hangul&#34;&gt;Lingua::KO::Romanize::Hangul&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CPAN distribution &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Unicode::Tussle&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Unicode::Tussle&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; module includes many command-line programs to help with working with Unicode, including these programs to fully or partly replace standard utilities: &lt;em&gt;tcgrep&lt;/em&gt; instead of &lt;em&gt;egrep&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;uniquote&lt;/em&gt; instead of &lt;em&gt;cat -v&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;hexdump&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;uniwc&lt;/em&gt; instead of &lt;em&gt;wc&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;unilook&lt;/em&gt; instead of &lt;em&gt;look&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;unifmt&lt;/em&gt; instead of &lt;em&gt;fmt&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;ucsort&lt;/em&gt; instead of &lt;em&gt;sort&lt;/em&gt;. For exploring Unicode character names and character properties, see its &lt;em&gt;uniprops&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;unichars&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;uninames&lt;/em&gt; programs. It also supplies these programs, all of which are general ﬁlters that do Unicode-y things: &lt;em&gt;unititle&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;unicaps&lt;/em&gt;; &lt;em&gt;uniwide&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;uninarrow&lt;/em&gt;; &lt;em&gt;unisupers&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;unisubs&lt;/em&gt;; &lt;em&gt;nfd&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;nfc&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;nfkd&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;nfkc&lt;/em&gt;; and &lt;em&gt;uc&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;lc&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;tc&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, see &lt;a href=&#34;http://unicode.org/standard/standard.html&#34;&gt;the published Unicode Standard&lt;/a&gt; (page numbers are from version 6.0.0), including these speciﬁc annexes and technical reports:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;§3.13 Default Case Algorithms, page 113&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;§4.2 Case, pages 120-122&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Case Mappings, page 166-172, especially Caseless Matching starting on page 170&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://unicode.org/reports/tr44/&#34;&gt;UAX #44: Unicode Character Database&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://unicode.org/reports/tr18/&#34;&gt;UTS #18: Unicode Regular Expressions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://unicode.org/reports/tr15/&#34;&gt;UAX #15: Unicode Normalization Forms&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://unicode.org/reports/tr10/&#34;&gt;UTS #10: Unicode Collation Algorithm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://unicode.org/reports/tr29/&#34;&gt;UAX #29: Unicode Text Segmentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://unicode.org/reports/tr14/&#34;&gt;UAX #14: Unicode Line Breaking Algorithm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://unicode.org/reports/tr11/&#34;&gt;UAX #11: East Asian Width&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tom Christiansen &amp;lt;tchrist@perl.com&amp;gt; wrote this series, with occasional kibbitzing from Larry Wall and Jeﬀrey Friedl in the background.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of these examples came from the current edition of the &amp;ldquo;Camel Book&amp;rdquo;; that is, from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://http://shop.oreilly.com/product/9780596004927.do&#34;&gt;4&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; Edition of &lt;em&gt;Programming Perl&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Copyright © 2012 Tom Christiansen &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt;, 2012-02-13 by O&amp;rsquo;Reilly Media. The code itself is freely redistributable, and you are encouraged to transplant, fold, spindle, and mutilate any of the examples in this series however you please for inclusion into your own programs without any encumbrance whatsoever. Acknowledgement via code comment is polite but not required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previous: &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/pub/2012/06/perlunicook-demo-of-unicode-collation-and-printing.html&#34;&gt;℞ 44: Demo of Unicode Collation and Printing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Series Index: &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/pub/2012/04/perlunicook-standard-preamble.html&#34;&gt;The Standard Preamble&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Perl Unicode Cookbook: Demo of Unicode Collation and Printing</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/pub/2012/06/perlunicook-demo-of-unicode-collation-and-printing.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Jun 2012 06:00:01 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/pub/2012/06/perlunicook-demo-of-unicode-collation-and-printing.html/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;44-program-demo-of-unicode-collation-and-printing&#34;&gt;℞ 44: PROGRAM: Demo of Unicode collation and printing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The past several weeks of Unicode recipes have explained how Unicode works and shown how to use it in your programs. If you&amp;rsquo;ve gone through those recipes, you now understand more than most programmers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How about putting everything together?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a full program showing how to make use of locale-sensitive sorting, Unicode casing, and managing print widths when some of the characters take up zero or two columns, not just one column each time. When run, the following program produces this nicely aligned output (though the quality of the alignment depends on the quality of your Unicode font, of course):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;    Crème Brûlée....... €2.00
    Éclair............. €1.60
    Fideuà............. €4.20
    Hamburger.......... €6.00
    Jamón Serrano...... €4.45
    Linguiça........... €7.00
    Pâté............... €4.15
    Pears.............. €2.00
    Pêches............. €2.25
    Smørbrød........... €5.75
    Spätzle............ €5.50
    Xoriço............. €3.00
    Γύρος.............. €6.50
    막걸리............. €4.00
    おもち............. €2.65
    お好み焼き......... €8.00
    シュークリーム..... €1.85
    寿司............... €9.99
    包子............... €7.50
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s that program; tested on v5.14.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt; #!/usr/bin/env perl
 # umenu - demo sorting and printing of Unicode food
 #
 # (obligatory and increasingly long preamble)
 #
 use utf8;
 use v5.14;                       # for locale sorting and unicode_strings
 use strict;
 use warnings;
 use warnings  qw(FATAL utf8);    # fatalize encoding faults
 use open      qw(:std :utf8);    # undeclared streams in UTF-8
 use charnames qw(:full :short);  # unneeded in v5.16

 # std modules
 use Unicode::Normalize;          # std perl distro as of v5.8
 use List::Util qw(max);          # std perl distro as of v5.10
 use Unicode::Collate::Locale;    # std perl distro as of v5.14

 # cpan modules
 use Unicode::GCString;           # from CPAN

 # forward defs
 sub pad($$$);
 sub colwidth(_);
 sub entitle(_);

 my %price = (
     &amp;quot;γύρος&amp;quot;             =&amp;gt; 6.50, # gyros, Greek
     &amp;quot;pears&amp;quot;             =&amp;gt; 2.00, # like um, pears
     &amp;quot;linguiça&amp;quot;          =&amp;gt; 7.00, # spicy sausage, Portuguese
     &amp;quot;xoriço&amp;quot;            =&amp;gt; 3.00, # chorizo sausage, Catalan
     &amp;quot;hamburger&amp;quot;         =&amp;gt; 6.00, # burgermeister meisterburger
     &amp;quot;éclair&amp;quot;            =&amp;gt; 1.60, # dessert, French
     &amp;quot;smørbrød&amp;quot;          =&amp;gt; 5.75, # sandwiches, Norwegian
     &amp;quot;spätzle&amp;quot;           =&amp;gt; 5.50, # Bayerisch noodles, little sparrows
     &amp;quot;包子&amp;quot;              =&amp;gt; 7.50, # bao1 zi5, steamed pork buns, Mandarin
     &amp;quot;jamón serrano&amp;quot;     =&amp;gt; 4.45, # country ham, Spanish
     &amp;quot;pêches&amp;quot;            =&amp;gt; 2.25, # peaches, French
     &amp;quot;シュークリーム&amp;quot;    =&amp;gt; 1.85, # cream-filled pastry like éclair, Japanese
     &amp;quot;막걸리&amp;quot;            =&amp;gt; 4.00, # makgeolli, Korean rice wine
     &amp;quot;寿司&amp;quot;              =&amp;gt; 9.99, # sushi, Japanese
     &amp;quot;おもち&amp;quot;            =&amp;gt; 2.65, # omochi, rice cakes, Japanese
     &amp;quot;crème brûlée&amp;quot;      =&amp;gt; 2.00, # tasty broiled cream, French
     &amp;quot;fideuà&amp;quot;            =&amp;gt; 4.20, # more noodles, Valencian (Catalan=fideuada)
     &amp;quot;pâté&amp;quot;              =&amp;gt; 4.15, # gooseliver paste, French
     &amp;quot;お好み焼き&amp;quot;        =&amp;gt; 8.00, # okonomiyaki, Japanese
 );

 # find the widest allowed width for the name column
 my $width = 5 + max map { colwidth } keys %price;

 # So the Asian stuff comes out in an order that someone
 # who reads those scripts won&#39;t freak out over; the
 # CJK stuff will be in JIS X 0208 order that way.
 my $coll  = Unicode::Collate::Locale-&amp;gt;new( locale =&amp;gt; &amp;quot;ja&amp;quot; );

 for my $item ($coll-&amp;gt;sort(keys %price)) {
     print pad(entitle($item), $width, &amp;quot;.&amp;quot;);
     printf &amp;quot; €%.2f\n&amp;quot;, $price{$item};
 }

 sub pad($$$) {
     my($str, $width, $padchar) = @_;
     return $str . ($padchar x ($width - colwidth($str)));
 }

 sub colwidth(_) {
     my($str) = @_;
     return Unicode::GCString-&amp;gt;new($str)-&amp;gt;columns;
 }

 sub entitle(_) {
     my($str) = @_;
     $str     =~ s{ (?=\pL)(\S)     (\S*) }
              { ucfirst($1) . lc($2)  }xge;
     return $str;
 }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simple enough, isn&amp;rsquo;t it? Put together, everything just works nicely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previous: &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/pub/2012/06/perlunicook-unicode-text-in-dbm-files-the-easy-way.html&#34;&gt;℞ 43: Unicode Text in DBM Files (the easy way)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Series Index: &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/pub/2012/04/perlunicook-standard-preamble.html&#34;&gt;The Standard Preamble&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next: &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/pub/2012/06/perlunicook-further-resources.html&#34;&gt;℞ 45: Further Resources&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Perl Unicode Cookbook: Unicode Text in DBM Files (the easy way)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/pub/2012/06/perlunicook-unicode-text-in-dbm-files-the-easy-way.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jun 2012 06:00:01 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/pub/2012/06/perlunicook-unicode-text-in-dbm-files-the-easy-way.html/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;43-unicode-text-in-dbm-hashes-the-easy-way&#34;&gt;℞ 43: Unicode text in DBM hashes, the easy way&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/pub/2012/06/perlunicook-unicode-text-in-stubborn-libraries.html&#34;&gt;Some Perl libraries require you to jump through hoops to handle Unicode data&lt;/a&gt;. Would that everything worked as easily as Perl&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://perldoc.perl.org/open.html&#34;&gt;open&lt;/a&gt; pragma!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For DBM files, here&amp;rsquo;s how to implicitly manage the translation; all encoding and decoding is done automatically, just as with streams that have a particular encoding attached to them. The &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/DBM_Filter&#34;&gt;DBM_Filter&lt;/a&gt; module allows you to apply filters to keys and values to manipulate their contents before storing or fetching. The module includes a &amp;ldquo;utf8&amp;rdquo; filter. Use it like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;    use DB_File;
    use DBM_Filter;

    my $dbobj = tie %dbhash, &amp;quot;DB_File&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;pathname&amp;quot;;
    $dbobj-&amp;gt;Filter_Value_Push(&amp;quot;utf8&amp;quot;);  # this is the magic bit

 # ST

    # assume $uni_key and $uni_value are abstract Unicode strings
    $dbhash{$uni_key} = $uni_value;

  # FETCH

    # $uni_key holds a normal Perl string (abstract Unicode)
    my $uni_value = $dbhash{$uni_key};
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previous: &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/pub/2012/06/perlunicook-unicode-text-in-stubborn-libraries.html&#34;&gt;℞ 42: Unicode Text in Stubborn Libraries&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Series Index: &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/pub/2012/04/perlunicook-standard-preamble.html&#34;&gt;The Standard Preamble&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next: &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/pub/2012/06/perlunicook-demo-of-unicode-collation-and-printing.html&#34;&gt;℞ 44: Demo of Unicode Collation and Printing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Perl Unicode Cookbook: Unicode Text in Stubborn Libraries</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/pub/2012/06/perlunicook-unicode-text-in-stubborn-libraries.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jun 2012 06:00:01 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/pub/2012/06/perlunicook-unicode-text-in-stubborn-libraries.html/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;42-unicode-text-in-dbm-hashes-the-tedious-way&#34;&gt;℞ 42: Unicode text in DBM hashes, the tedious way&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Perl 5 has long been very careful about handling Unicode correctly inside the world of Perl itself, every time you leave the Perl internals, you cross a boundary at which &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; may need to handle decoding and encoding. This happens when performing IO across a network or to files, when speaking to a database, or even when using XS to use a shared library from Perl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, consider the core module &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/DB_File&#34;&gt;DB_File&lt;/a&gt;, which allows you to use Berkeley DB files from Perl—persistent storage for key/value pairs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using a regular Perl string as a key or value for a DBM hash will trigger a wide character exception if any codepoints won&amp;rsquo;t ﬁt into a byte. Here&amp;rsquo;s how to manually manage the translation:
        use DB_File;
        use Encode qw(encode decode);
        tie %dbhash, &amp;ldquo;DB_File&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;pathname&amp;rdquo;;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt; # STORE

    # assume $uni_key and $uni_value are abstract Unicode strings
    my $enc_key   = encode(&amp;quot;UTF-8&amp;quot;, $uni_key, 1);
    my $enc_value = encode(&amp;quot;UTF-8&amp;quot;, $uni_value, 1);
    $dbhash{$enc_key} = $enc_value;

 # FETCH

    # assume $uni_key holds a normal Perl string (abstract Unicode)
    my $enc_key   = encode(&amp;quot;UTF-8&amp;quot;, $uni_key, 1);
    my $enc_value = $dbhash{$enc_key};
    my $uni_value = decode(&amp;quot;UTF-8&amp;quot;, $enc_key, 1);
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By performing this manual encoding and decoding yourself, you know that your storage file will have a consistent representation of your data. The correct encoding depends on the type of data you store and the capabilities of the external code, of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previous: &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/pub/2012/06/perlunicook-unicode-linebreaking.html&#34;&gt;℞ 41: Unicode Linebreaking&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Series Index: &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/pub/2012/04/perlunicook-standard-preamble.html&#34;&gt;The Standard Preamble&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next: &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/pub/2012/06/perlunicook-unicode-text-in-dbm-files-the-easy-way.html&#34;&gt;℞ 43: Unicode Text in DBM Files (the easy way)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Perl Unicode Cookbook: Unicode Linebreaking</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/pub/2012/06/perlunicook-unicode-linebreaking.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jun 2012 06:00:01 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/pub/2012/06/perlunicook-unicode-linebreaking.html/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;41-unicode-linebreaking&#34;&gt;℞ 41: Unicode linebreaking&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve ever tried to fit a large amount of text into a display area too narrow for the full width of the text, you&amp;rsquo;ve dealt with the joy of linebreaking (or word wrapping). As you may have come to expect from Unicode now, the specification provides a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.unicode.org/reports/tr14/&#34;&gt;Unicode Line Breaking Algorithm&lt;/a&gt; which respects the available line breaking opportunities provided by Unicode text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unicode characters, of course, may have properties which influence these rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you have come to expect from Perl, a module implements the Unicode Line Breaking Algorithm. Install &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Unicode::LineBreak&#34;&gt;Unicode::LineBreak&lt;/a&gt;. This module respects direct and indirect break points as well as the grapheme width of the string. Its basic use is simple:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt; use Unicode::LineBreak;
 use charnames qw(:full);

 my $para = &amp;quot;This is a super\N{HYPHEN}long string. &amp;quot; x 20;
 my $fmt  = Unicode::LineBreak-&amp;gt;new;
 print $fmt-&amp;gt;break($para), &amp;quot;\n&amp;quot;;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result of its &lt;code&gt;break()&lt;/code&gt; method is an array of lines broken at valid points. (The default maximum number of columns is 76, so this example works well for email and console use. See the module&amp;rsquo;s documentation for other configuration options.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previous: &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/pub/2012/06/perlunicook-case--and-accent-insensitive-locale-comparison.html&#34;&gt;℞ 40: Case- and Accent-insensitive Locale Comparisons&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Series Index: &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/pub/2012/04/perlunicook-standard-preamble.html&#34;&gt;The Standard Preamble&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next: &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313/pub/2012/06/perlunicook-unicode-text-in-stubborn-libraries.html&#34;&gt;℞ 42: Unicode Text in Stubborn Libraries&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>

