<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Velociraptor on Perl.com - programming news, code and culture</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/velociraptor/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Velociraptor on Perl.com - programming news, code and culture</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2014 02:48:28 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/tags/velociraptor/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Announcing: the Perl Nerd Merit Badge contest</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/article/64/2014/1/29/Announcing--the-Perl-Nerd-Merit-Badge-contest/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2014 02:48:28 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/article/64/2014/1/29/Announcing--the-Perl-Nerd-Merit-Badge-contest/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It all started late last year with brian d foy&amp;rsquo;s successful &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.crowdtilt.com/campaigns/make-perl-nerd-merit-badges&#34;&gt;Crowdtilt campaign&lt;/a&gt;. Now we&amp;rsquo;ve got our hands on three exclusive, not-available-to-buy anywhere else, bona fide Perl Nerd Merit Badges. What do you have to do for a chance to win a badge and the envy and respect of your perly peers? Read on &amp;hellip;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-to-enter&#34;&gt;How to enter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re looking to find the best Perl programming tricks out there. It can be a Perl code example or an undiscovered CPAN module or app. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t have to be original. All you have to do is send us an email that describes the trick, what&amp;rsquo;s so cool about it, including a code example by &lt;strong&gt;February 21&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; 2014&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three best submissions will each win a Perl Nerd Merit Badge and have their Perl trick published on this website with full accreditation. Please read the contest rules below before entering. Good luck!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/64/Perl_Nerd_Merit_Badges.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-velociraptor-as-a-perl-icon&#34;&gt;The Velociraptor as a Perl icon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Keating &lt;a href=&#34;http://mdk.per.ly/2011/03/02/evolution-of-the-velociraptor/&#34;&gt;wrote&lt;/a&gt; an illuminating article on the background behind the velociraptor as a Perl 5 logo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;contest-rules&#34;&gt;Contest Rules&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All entries must be emailed to perltricks.com@gmail.com.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A person may enter the competition multiple times, but only one entry is necessary for a chance to win.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The closing date for submissions is February 21&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; 2014.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PerlTricks.com will notify the winners by email, using the email addresses of the winning submissions within 1 week of the closing date.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PerlTricks.com will endeavour to send the prizes within one month of the competition closing. The prize will be mailed to the winners&amp;rsquo; contact address by standard US mail. Overseas entries are welcome but may take longer to receive their prize. Entrants will be required to pay all shipping costs above $10.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The entrants&amp;rsquo; email addresses will only be used for the purpose of communicating about the competition and not shared with any 3rd party.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The judges decision is final.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;By entering the competition the entrants&amp;rsquo; agree that their submissions are the property of PerlTricks.com.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No part of the prize is exchangeable for cash or any other prize.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The contest is subject to US law.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Enter the contest today, &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:perltricks.com@gmail.com?subject=Nerd%20Merit%20Badge%20Contest&#34;&gt;email us&lt;/a&gt; your Perl trick!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;This article was originally posted on &lt;a href=&#34;http://perltricks.com&#34;&gt;PerlTricks.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>

