<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Hashtag on Perl.com - programming news, code and culture</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/hashtag/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Hashtag on Perl.com - programming news, code and culture</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2016 08:05:37 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/tags/hashtag/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Don&#39;t forget to #Perl</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/article/don-t-forget-to--perl/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2016 08:05:37 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/article/don-t-forget-to--perl/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When it comes to open source communities, programming comes first, but talking about programming is a close second. Perl programmers are pretty good about blogging (the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/dnmfarrell/Perly-Bot&#34;&gt;Perly-Bot app&lt;/a&gt; that populates our community articles sidebar tracks around 30 blogs), but I&amp;rsquo;ve noticed that on Twitter, many Perl-related tweets lack a &lt;code&gt;#Perl&lt;/code&gt; hashtag. That&amp;rsquo;s a shame, as it helps others discover Perl related tweets via search, clicking the hashtag and in the &amp;ldquo;highlights&amp;rdquo; notification on the Twitter mobile app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes you may not want to include a Perl hashtag: perhaps you&amp;rsquo;ve hit the tweet character limit (&lt;code&gt;#Per&lt;/code&gt; is no good!) or maybe you&amp;rsquo;re blogging about several languages including Perl, and don&amp;rsquo;t want to dissuade non-Perl programmers from clicking the link. There are probably many scenarios where it doesn&amp;rsquo;t make sense to include the hashtag, and that&amp;rsquo;s fine. For everything else, there is &lt;code&gt;#Perl&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hashtags are case insensitive so &lt;code&gt;#Perl&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;#perl&lt;/code&gt; are good, but I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t &lt;code&gt;#PERL&lt;/code&gt; unless you&amp;rsquo;re trolling (yw trolls!). Unlike many programming languages, our favorite language has a unique name (kind of - there is the Perl &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.surnamedb.com/Surname/Perl&#34;&gt;surname&lt;/a&gt;). Let&amp;rsquo;s take advantage of it by including &lt;code&gt;#Perl&lt;/code&gt; in our tweets. If enough of us do it, who knows, we might even start trending again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;This article was originally posted on &lt;a href=&#34;http://perltricks.com&#34;&gt;PerlTricks.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>

