<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Dawn Wallis on Perl.com - programming news, code and culture</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/authors/dawn-wallis/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Dawn Wallis on Perl.com - programming news, code and culture</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 Feb 2019 18:16:43 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/authors/dawn-wallis/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>The Perl Conference in Pittsburgh - Call For Presentations</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/article/the-perl-conference-in-pittsburgh-cfp/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Feb 2019 18:16:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/article/the-perl-conference-in-pittsburgh-cfp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Sure, there&amp;rsquo;s more than one way to do it, but yours is the best, right? Seize this opportunity to prove it by submitting a talk for The Perl Conference in Pittsburgh! Submit your presentation ideas by March 1. If it&amp;rsquo;s accepted you&amp;rsquo;ll attend the conference as a guest speaker for free and get a free room upgrade just for submitting your proposal!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are looking for all level of speakers, first-timers are welcome! The audience will range in levels of expertise and so all level of talks are welcome - your advanced talk is sure to be a hit, just like any &amp;ldquo;Getting started with&amp;rdquo; presentations geared toward beginners. We know the Perl community can benefit from what you have to say! Find out more and submit your idea &lt;a href=&#34;http://bit.ly/tpcipcfp&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not sure you want to give a presentation? We understand. Consider at least attending a few of them. The main conference is Jun 17-19 with master class tutorial sessions surrounding it on Jun 16, 20, and 21. Register to attend The Perl Conference in Pittsburgh &lt;a href=&#34;https://perlconference.us/tpc-2019-pit/registration/&#34;&gt;today&lt;/a&gt;, and you&amp;rsquo;ll receive the early bird discount!
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Cover image &lt;a href=&#34;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Pittsburgh_Skyline_at_night_(3021295447).jpg&#34;&gt;Wikimedia&lt;/a&gt; licensed under Creative Commons&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Call for Perl Conference North America Photos</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/article/call-for-perl-conference-photos/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Jul 2018 20:08:02 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/article/call-for-perl-conference-photos/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Perl Conference organizers are asking for your help! Do you have any pictures taken at past Perl conferences (North America) from 1999 through 2018? That’s right! Organizers are seeking photos spanning the last 20 years. This can be any conference photo from The Perl Foundation run events like Yet Another Perl Conference (YAPC) and The Perl Conference (TPC). The full list of qualifying events is on &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yet_Another_Perl_Conference#North_America&#34;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have a photo or photos that you’d like to share from previous YAPC::NA or TPC::NA events please send a link or full resolution file to admin@perlconference.us.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Perl Conference North America is Just Around the Corner</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/article/the-perl-conference-north-america-is-just-around-the-corner/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 May 2018 08:08:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/article/the-perl-conference-north-america-is-just-around-the-corner/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://perlconference.us/tpc-2018-slc/&#34;&gt;The Perl Conference&lt;/a&gt; in North America (TPC::NA::2018) is almost here! We’re returning to Salt Lake City, Utah this year at the Little America Hotel once again. The conference is next month from Monday, June 18th through Wednesday, June 20th, with additional in-depth tutorial days June 17th, 21st, and 22nd. Tickets are available for sale on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eventbrite.com/e/the-perl-conference-in-salt-lake-city-2018-tickets-41850611305&#34;&gt;the conference&amp;rsquo;s Eventbrite page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conference venue offers amazing views, but there is so much more to explore if you have time to check the area out. There are some famous attractions nearby like the &lt;a href=&#34;https://nhmu.utah.edu&#34;&gt;National History Museum of Utah&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.shopcitycreekcenter.com&#34;&gt;City Creek Center&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.redbuttegarden.org&#34;&gt;Red Butte Garden and Arboretum&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.templesquare.com&#34;&gt;Temple Square&lt;/a&gt;. You can find out more information about these attractions and Salt Lake City at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.visitutah.com&#34;&gt;visitutah.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TPC::NA::2018 offers a variety of topics and speakers intended for beginners through advanced attendees. Learn about Perl’s higher order functions in David Golden’s presentation &lt;a href=&#34;https://perlconference.us/tpc-2018-slc/sessions/#481&#34;&gt;Taking Perl to Eleven with Higher-Order Functions&lt;/a&gt;. Explore the future of Perl 5 with Sawyer X in &lt;a href=&#34;https://perlconference.us/tpc-2018-slc/sessions/#379&#34;&gt;Perl 5.28 and Beyond&lt;/a&gt;. Speaker Matt Trout will tell you about extending and transforming Perl in &lt;a href=&#34;https://perlconference.us/tpc-2018-slc/sessions/#587&#34;&gt;Tower of Babble&lt;/a&gt;, while Michael Conrad pops open the hood in his &lt;a href=&#34;https://perlconference.us/tpc-2018-slc/sessions/#371&#34;&gt;Building the Graphics of the DeLorean Digital Dash&lt;/a&gt; presentation. There’s a lot to learn and more to see, visit &lt;a href=&#34;https://perlconference.us/tpc-2018-slc/sessions/&#34;&gt;the full session list&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are also 3 dedicated days of tutorial sessions surrounding the main conference event days. Dave Rolsky has &lt;a href=&#34;https://perlconference.us/tpc-2018-slc/session/introduction-to-go/&#34;&gt;courses on Go&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://perlconference.us/tpc-2018-slc/session/introduction-to-moose/&#34;&gt;Moose&lt;/a&gt; while Elizabeth Mattjsen will help you make a &lt;a href=&#34;https://perlconference.us/tpc-2018-slc/session/making-your-perl-5-modules-work-in-rakudo-perl-6/&#34;&gt;Perl 5 module for use in Rakudo Perl 6&lt;/a&gt;. The &lt;a href=&#34;https://perlconference.us/tpc-2018-slc/tutorials/&#34;&gt;full course list and prices are available on the Tutorials page&lt;/a&gt;. After purchasing a separate ticket to any one of these sessions, you can get hands-on training in half or full day lessons from Perl experts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the organizers of TPC::NA::2018, we are really looking forward to seeing you next month!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>

