<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Zbigniew Lukasiak on Perl.com - programming news, code and culture</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/authors/zbigniew-lukasiak/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Zbigniew Lukasiak on Perl.com - programming news, code and culture</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Nov 2010 19:31:41 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/authors/zbigniew-lukasiak/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>The Philosophy of WebNano</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/pub/2010/11/the-philosophy-of-webnano.html/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Nov 2010 19:31:41 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/pub/2010/11/the-philosophy-of-webnano.html/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;why-webnano&#34;&gt;Why WebNano&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many web applications have common components: a login page, a comment box, an email confirmation mechanism, a generic CRUD page. All of these are well-defined components. It&amp;rsquo;s easy to believe that it should not be difficult to abstract them away into libraries. Yet every time you start a web application you need to write that boring comment box again and again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why are there so few such libraries? Why is writing them so hard? There are more and less important reasons, but there are many reasons. Most projects to make components eventually die the death of a thousand cuts. Some of those problems can be solved and I believe that solving them would make a difference. &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/WebNano&#34;&gt;WebNano&lt;/a&gt; is my attempt at doing that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably the most popular Perl web framework is &lt;a href=&#34;http://catalystframework.org/&#34;&gt;Catalyst&lt;/a&gt;. It is also the web framework I know the best—this is why I chose it as the point of reference for my analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;controllers-in-request-scope&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Controllers in request scope&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Five years ago I was staring at the first Catalyst examples and had foggy intuition that there was something not quite optimal. The essence of object oriented programming is that the most accessed data should be available to all methods in a class without explicitly passing it via parameters, but the Catalyst examples always started with &lt;code&gt;my ( $self, $c, ... ) = @_&lt;/code&gt;. That&amp;rsquo;s not very &lt;a href=&#34;http://c2.com/cgi/wiki?DontRepeatYourself&#34;&gt;DRY&lt;/a&gt;. The &lt;code&gt;$c&lt;/code&gt; parameter gets passed everywhere as if it were a plain old parameter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point I &lt;a href=&#34;http://perlalchemy.blogspot.com/2009/10/catalystcomponentinstancepercontext.html&#34;&gt;counted how often methods from the manual use the controller object versus how often they use the context object which contains the request data&lt;/a&gt;. The result was 117 and 38 respectively. Many people commented that their code often uses the controller object. It&amp;rsquo;s hard to judge this unless you can see that code, but as my code resembled the example code from the manual, this seems common. This disproportion is only an illustration. The question is not about switching &lt;code&gt;$c&lt;/code&gt; with &lt;code&gt;$self&lt;/code&gt;. The question is why the request data, which undeniably is in the center of the computation carried out in controllers, is anything other than instance data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My curiosity persisted until about a year ago, when I received a reply in private communication from some members of the core team. They want the controller object to be immutable (see &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.woobling.org/2009/05/immutable-data-structures.html&#34;&gt;Immutable Data Structures&lt;/a&gt;). That&amp;rsquo;s impossible if the values of one or more of its attributesmust necessarily change with each incoming request. Immutable objects are a good design choice and I accepted this answer but later I wondered what would happen if the framework recreated the controller object anew with each request? Then it could hold the request data and still be immutable for the lifetime of the request.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This would be a big change for Catalyst; Catalyst controllers are created at the starup time, together with all the other application components (models and views) and changing that does not seem feasible. I decided to write a new web framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have tried many Perl web frameworks but I found only one more that uses controllers in request scope. This is a fundamental distinguishing feature of WebNano. It&amp;rsquo;s not only about reducing the clutter of repeatable parameter passing. Instead, I believe that putting object into their natural scope will fix a lot of the widely recognized &lt;a href=&#34;http://jjnapiorkowski.vox.com/library/post/does-anyone-else-hate-the-stash.html&#34;&gt;problems with the Catalyst stash and data passed through it&lt;/a&gt;. In procedural programming it is not controversial to put your variable declarations into the narrowest block that encompasses their uses. The same should be true for objects. Using the same controller to serve multiple request &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a bit faster then recreating it each time, but that gain is modest. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cpantesters.org/cpan/report/7c61aa08-d810-11df-8503-f91d06264d1f&#34;&gt;Object::Tiny on one of the tester machines could create 714286 object per second&lt;/a&gt; and even &lt;a href=&#34;http://moose.perl.org/&#34;&gt;Moose&lt;/a&gt;, the slowest framework tested there, can create more then a 10000 objects per second. Eliminating a few of such operations, in most circumstances, is not worth compromising on the architecture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also tested these theoretical estimations with more down to earth &lt;a href=&#34;http://httpd.apache.org/docs/2.0/programs/ab.html&#34;&gt;ab&lt;/a&gt; benchmarks for a trivial application serving just one page. WebNano was the fasted framework tested, by a wide margin. This is still an artificial test, but it should be accurate enough to show that the cost introduced by this design choice does not need to be big.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;decoupling&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Decoupling&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WebNano may have tested as the fastest framework because it does not do much. WebNano is really small. Its &lt;em&gt;lib/&lt;/em&gt; directory currently contains just 233 lines of code (as reported by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dwheeler.com/sloccount/&#34;&gt;sloccount&lt;/a&gt;) and &lt;a href=&#34;http://deps.cpantesters.org/?module=WebNano;perl=latest&#34;&gt;minimal dependencies&lt;/a&gt;. CPAN libraries cover all corners of web application programming, so WebNano can provide a basic structure and otherwise get out of the way. Assuming simplicity allowed me to remove a lot of code required for advanced flexibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, Catalyst started the process of decoupling the web framework from other parts of the application. With Catalyst you can use any persistence layer for the model and any templating library for the view. Yet with this flexibility the &lt;code&gt;model()&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;view()&lt;/code&gt; methods in Catalyst are very simple. There is no common behaviour among the various libraries, so all these methods do is find a model or view by its name. For WebNano I decided that &lt;code&gt;-&amp;gt;Something&lt;/code&gt; is shorter and no less informative then &lt;code&gt;-&amp;gt;model(&#39;Something&#39;)&lt;/code&gt;, so I removed the &lt;code&gt;model()&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;view()&lt;/code&gt; methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also decided to leave out component initialization. This is a generic task used in all kinds of programs. Any library which performs this task needs to know nothing about the web part of the application, and CPAN offers many such initialization libraries. In my limited experiments &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/MooseX::SimpleConfig&#34;&gt;MooseX::SimpleConfig&lt;/a&gt; was very convenient. For more complex needs, &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Bread::Board&#34;&gt;Bread::Board&lt;/a&gt; seems like a good choice. This initialization layer needs to know how to create all the objects used by the application, but you need no WebNano adapter to use them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;localized-dispatching&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Localized dispatching&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Out of the box WebNano supports only one very simple dispatching model. Dispatching controls which subroutine to call with which arguments and depends directly on the behavior of the subroutines themselves. This is why I don&amp;rsquo;t believe in external dispatchers where you configure all the dispatching for the application in one place. The dispatching might be in one place, but any practical change you make requires updates in two places. WebNano&amp;rsquo;s default dispatching is easy to extend and override on per-controller basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing a dispatcher is not hard; it&amp;rsquo;s only complex and difficult when you try to write a dispatching model to work for every possible application. I prefer to write a simple dispatcher covering only the most popular dispatching scenarios and let the users of my framework write any specialized dispatching code for specialized controllers. With WebNano this is possible because these specialized dispatchers don&amp;rsquo;t interfere with each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also believe that this will make the controller classes more encapsulated and facilitate building libraries of application controllers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;granularity&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Granularity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like the way Catalyst structures your web related code into controller classes. This is a step forward from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/CGI::Application&#34;&gt;CGI::Application&lt;/a&gt; way of packing everything into one class. I have no hard data to support my impression, but the granularity of packing a few related pages into one controller class feels just about right. It gives room for expansion by adding new classes and dividing existing ones, and it does not clutter the application code with several nearly empty classes. This is a very important feature. I copied this design wholeheartedly in WebNano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;experiments-with-inheritance-and-overriding&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Experiments with inheritance and overriding&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the WebNano tests is an application which subclasses the main test app. It passes all the original tests and could be completely empty if I did not want to test the overriding of the inherited parts. I have seen many times a need for such behaviour, from branding websites to SaaS to reusable intranet tools. Too many applications solve the problem of reuse by copying code. Inheritance has its problems, but it enables ad-hoc reuse better than cut and paste programming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be aware that you need to override much more than just methods. My experiment with WebNano overrides application parts: controllers, templates, and configuration. It also overrides individual controllers at the template and method levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This type of inheritance could enable a natural mechanism to publish applications to CPAN, because they could operate with no special installation. Users could run them directly from &lt;code&gt;@INC&lt;/code&gt; and only later override the configuration or templates as needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;universality&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Universality&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the most common case a web application serving a request needs to fetch data, perform some computations on this data, and render a template with the computed values. Those tasks typically consume 99% of the overall time spent serving a request. The other 1% of time spent in the application framework processing matters little; reducing it will produce little noticeable speed increase in the whole application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even so, there might be rare cases where the application needs to serve, for example, small JSON data chunks from a memory cache. Even when this is a small and simple part of the application, if it generates enough volume then the speed of the framework suddenly becomes important. Would you code that part in PHP?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was very tempted to use Moose in WebNano. Moose generates some significant startup overhead, though for web applications running in persistent environments this does not matter much because that overhead amortizes over many requests. If you run your application as CGI, this startup time becomes important. Even if CGI is perceived as passé now, it is still the easiest way to deploy web applications and (especially with the most widespread support from hosting companies). Fortunately, using &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/MooseX::NonMoose&#34;&gt;MooseX::NonMoose&lt;/a&gt; it is very easy to treat any hash based object classes as base classes for Moose based code, so using WebNano does not mean that you need to stick to the simplistic Object Oriented Framework it uses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plan is to make WebNano small but universal, then make extensions that will be more powerful and more restricted. I think it is important that the base platform can be used in all kinds of circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusions&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is early to say if WebNano will live to the promise of facilitating the development of web application components. There is a first component at CPAN: &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/WebNano::Controller::CRUD&#34;&gt;WebNano::Controller::CRUD&lt;/a&gt;. It still bears the label &amp;ldquo;experimental&amp;rdquo;, but I used it in &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zby/Nblog&#34;&gt;Nblog&lt;/a&gt;. When I compare it to my first similar product &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/Catalyst::Example::Controller::InstantCRUD&#34;&gt;Catalyst::Example::Controller::InstantCRUD&lt;/a&gt;, there aren&amp;rsquo;t many differences. As you might predict, the methods have one less parameter (&lt;code&gt;$c&lt;/code&gt;). Inheritable templates are also nice for deployment—you don&amp;rsquo;t need to write your own templates to see it working, and later you can easily override the defaults. There is a bit more dispatching code, but thanks to that, the code retrieves the result object in only one place. In Catalyst this is possible with chained dispatching. In the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/zby/WebNano/tree/master/examples/DvdDatabase/lib/DvdDatabase/Controller/&#34;&gt;examples directory&lt;/a&gt; there are four variations on this CRUD theme. I remain undecided about whis is optimal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The surprising thing when converting Nblog from Catalyst to WebNano was how little I missed the rich Catalyst features, even though WebNano has still so little code. I think it is a promising start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently I discovered echoes of many of my design choices in the publications by the Google testing guru &lt;a href=&#34;http://misko.hevery.com/&#34;&gt;Miško Hevery&lt;/a&gt;. My point of departure for the considerations above were general rules such as decoupling and encapsulation, where his concern is testability. The resulting &lt;a href=&#34;http://misko.hevery.com/2008/08/21/where-have-all-the-singletons-gone/&#34;&gt;design without singletons&lt;/a&gt; is remarkably similar. There is a lot of good articles at his blog, some were similar to what I already had considered (&lt;a href=&#34;http://misko.hevery.com/2009/04/15/managing-object-lifetimes/&#34;&gt;managing object lifetimes&lt;/a&gt;) and others were completely new to me (&lt;a href=&#34;http://misko.hevery.com/2009/04/08/how-to-do-everything-wrong-with-servlets/&#34;&gt;how to do everything wrong with servlets&lt;/a&gt;). I recommend them all.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>

