<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Productivity on Perl.com - programming news, code and culture</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/productivity/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Productivity on Perl.com - programming news, code and culture</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 22 Sep 2015 22:16:48 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/tags/productivity/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Activating Perl 6 syntax highlighting in Vim</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/article/194/2015/9/22/Activating-Perl-6-syntax-highlighting-in-Vim/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Sep 2015 22:16:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/article/194/2015/9/22/Activating-Perl-6-syntax-highlighting-in-Vim/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Modern versions of the Vim text editor ship with Perl 6 syntax highlighting, but automatically activating it is tricky because Perl 6 files can have ambiguous file extensions. It can get tiresome to correct the file type every time you open a Perl 6 file, so I&amp;rsquo;m going to show you a few tricks that I use to make Vim detect Perl 6 files automatically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;showing-and-setting-the-filetype-in-vim&#34;&gt;Showing and setting the filetype in Vim&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all I want to make sure that syntax highlighting is turned on by default, so I add this option to my &lt;code&gt;.vimrc&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;syntax on
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To edit your &lt;code&gt;.vimrc&lt;/code&gt; just start Vim and enter this command &lt;code&gt;:e $MYVIMRC&lt;/code&gt;. Save your changes with &lt;code&gt;:w&lt;/code&gt;, and then reload your &lt;code&gt;.vimrc&lt;/code&gt; with &lt;code&gt;:so %&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that I have syntax highlighting turned on, I need to know how set Vim&amp;rsquo;s file type to Perl 6 when I&amp;rsquo;m working with Perl 6 files. I can see the current file type by typing this command &lt;code&gt;:set filetype?&lt;/code&gt;. To set the file type to Perl 6, I use this command &lt;code&gt;:set filetype=perl6&lt;/code&gt;. The &lt;code&gt;filetype&lt;/code&gt; keyword can be shortened to &lt;code&gt;ft&lt;/code&gt;. In which case the last command becomes &lt;code&gt;:set ft=perl6&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;detecting-perl-6-files&#34;&gt;Detecting Perl 6 files&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the challenge becomes correctly detecting when I&amp;rsquo;m working with Perl 6 files in Vim. Perl 6 scripts shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be a problem: Vim (not Vi) automatically parses the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shebang_line&#34;&gt;shebang&lt;/a&gt; line to determine the file type. However this fails when the script has an extension like &lt;code&gt;.pl&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;use-the-pm6-file-extension&#34;&gt;Use the .pm6 file extension&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vim will automatically use Perl 6 syntax highlighting if the file extension is &lt;code&gt;.pm6&lt;/code&gt;. So when working with Perl 6 module files, it&amp;rsquo;s better to use this extension. This doesn&amp;rsquo;t help when I&amp;rsquo;m working on other people&amp;rsquo;s Perl 6 projects however. It also doesn&amp;rsquo;t help for test files, which do not have an equivalent Perl 6 file extension (&lt;code&gt;.t6&lt;/code&gt; test files are ignored when installing Perl 6 modules).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;use-a-modeline&#34;&gt;Use a modeline&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A modeline is a line of code in the text of the file which Vim reads and executes. So to activate Perl 6 syntax highlighting I just need to add this modeline to every Perl 6 file I work with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-perl&#34; data-lang=&#34;perl&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# vim: filetype=perl6&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take a look at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Mouq/json5/blob/master/lib/JSON5/Tiny.pm6#L54&#34;&gt;source code&lt;/a&gt; of JSON5::Tiny for a real-World example. To Perl 6 this code looks just like an ordinary comment, but Vim will use it to turn on Perl 6 syntax highlighting. The modeline can appear anywhere in the code, but it&amp;rsquo;s better to place it at the start or end of the file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Older versions of Vim (pre 7.3) and when Vim is run under root privileges, disable modelines as a security risk. Don&amp;rsquo;t run Vim as root! But if you have an older Vim, you can turn on modelines with &lt;code&gt;:set modeline&lt;/code&gt;. As with &lt;code&gt;filetype&lt;/code&gt;, modeline can be abbreviated to &lt;code&gt;ml&lt;/code&gt;, so &lt;code&gt;set ml&lt;/code&gt; works too. To activate modelines automatically, add this line to your &lt;code&gt;.vimrc&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;set ml
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The downside of using modelines? First there is aforementioned security risk for older Vims. Also it feels impure to add editor directives to the code I&amp;rsquo;m working with, as not everyone uses Vim. These seem like minor issues though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;use-a-local-vimrc&#34;&gt;Use a local vimrc&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often different Open Source projects will have different coding conventions that I need to follow, so it can be helpful to use a local vimrc file to store these project-specific settings. This works for syntax highlighting too. In order to use local vimrc files, I add the following code to my &lt;code&gt;.vimrc&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;if filereadable(&amp;quot;.vimrc.local&amp;quot;)
  so .vimrc.local
endif
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will check the current working directory for &lt;code&gt;.vimrc.local&lt;/code&gt; file, and automatically execute it if it finds it. &lt;strong&gt;Warning&lt;/strong&gt; this is a security risk - Vim will execute ANY instruction in a local vimrc, so I am very careful when working with projects that are not my own. Next I create a &lt;code&gt;.vimrc.local&lt;/code&gt; file in the root project directory and add this auto command to it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;au Bufnewfile,bufRead *.pm,*.t,*.pl set filetype=perl6
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now when I open or create any file with a Perl extension, Vim will set the syntax highlighting to Perl 6. I like this technique because it&amp;rsquo;s not intrusive: it doesn&amp;rsquo;t require any changes to the Perl 6 files themselves, so it works well on shared projects (I never check-in my local vimrc to the Git repo).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;use-code-detection&#34;&gt;Use code detection&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can also have Vim try to detect Perl 6 code automatically. Two directives which would indicate we&amp;rsquo;re working with Perl 6 instead of Perl 5 code: the shebang line and the &lt;code&gt;use v6;&lt;/code&gt; directive. To check for these, I&amp;rsquo;ll add a function to my .vimrc:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;function! LooksLikePerl6 ()
  if getline(1) =~# &#39;^#!.*/bin/.*perl6&#39;
    set filetype=perl6
  else
    for i in [1,2,3,4,5]
      if getline(i) == &#39;use v6;&#39;
        set filetype=perl6
        break
      endif
    endfor
  endif
endfunction

au bufRead *.pm,*.t,*.pl call LooksLikePerl6()
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This function uses &lt;code&gt;getline()&lt;/code&gt; to check the first line of the file to see if it looks like a Perl 6 shebang. This should work well for &lt;code&gt;.pl&lt;/code&gt; scripts, but Perl 6 module files will not have a shebang, so the next part of the script checks the first 5 lines of the file for the &lt;code&gt;use v6;&lt;/code&gt; directive. The last line of code is an auto command which will call the function anytime we open file with a Perl file extension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main drawback of this technique is that not all Perl 6 code uses the &lt;code&gt;use v6;&lt;/code&gt; directive, and so when working with module files, the code detection can fail. However the code detection could be improved to use more rules for detecting Perl 6 code such as class declarations. The &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/vim-perl/vim-perl&#34;&gt;vim-perl&lt;/a&gt; plugin has more sophisticated Perl 6 code detection &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/vim-perl/vim-perl/blob/master/ftdetect/perl11.vim&#34;&gt;rules&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;complete-vimrc&#34;&gt;Complete .vimrc&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This &lt;code&gt;.vimrc&lt;/code&gt; contains all the code shown above:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;syntax on

&amp;quot;Recognize modeline # vim: filetype=perl6
set ml

&amp;quot;check for a local vimrc
if filereadable(&amp;quot;.vimrc.local&amp;quot;)
  so .vimrc.local
endif

&amp;quot;check for Perl 6 code
function! LooksLikePerl6 ()
  if getline(1) =~# &#39;^#!.*/bin/.*perl6&#39;
    set filetype=perl6
  else
    for i in [1,2,3,4,5]
      if getline(i) == &#39;use v6;&#39;
        set filetype=perl6
        break
      endif
    endfor
  endif
endfunction

au bufRead *.pm,*.t,*.pl call LooksLikePerl6()
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that&amp;rsquo;s it, four useful-but-imperfect techniques for detecting file types in Vim. I tend to use a combination of all four. This would be a nice problem not to have. I&amp;rsquo;d like the Perl 6 community to agree and encourage unambiguous file extensions like &lt;code&gt;.pm6&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;.t6&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;.pl6&lt;/code&gt;. Larry Wall called this &amp;ldquo;free advertising&amp;rdquo;. It&amp;rsquo;s also a simple way to make Perl 6 programmers more productive. Not every text editor is as customizable as Vim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;This article was originally posted on &lt;a href=&#34;http://perltricks.com&#34;&gt;PerlTricks.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello perldoc, productivity booster</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/article/155/2015/2/26/Hello-perldoc--productivity-booster/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2015 13:42:57 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/article/155/2015/2/26/Hello-perldoc--productivity-booster/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Imagine this scenario: you&amp;rsquo;re using the DateTime module but you can&amp;rsquo;t remember the exact name of a function it provides. What do you do? You could open your browser, go to &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/&#34;&gt;MetaCPAN&lt;/a&gt;, search for DateTime and look up the answer in the module&amp;rsquo;s documentation. A faster way would be to switch to the command line, and type &lt;code&gt;perldoc DateTime&lt;/code&gt; to display the module&amp;rsquo;s documentation right there in the terminal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;perldoc&lt;/code&gt; is a command line program for reading Perl documentation. It comes with Perl, so if you&amp;rsquo;ve got Perl installed, perldoc should be available too. Using perldoc is easy: as you&amp;rsquo;ve already seen, to view the documentation of a module you&amp;rsquo;ve installed, at the command line type:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-perl&#34; data-lang=&#34;perl&#34;&gt;$ perldoc Module::Name&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;perldoc will search for the module and if it finds it, display the module&amp;rsquo;s documentation (written in Pod). Using perldoc you can learn more about any aspect of Perl almost instantly. Want to know more about Pod? Try &lt;code&gt;perldoc pod&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;dial-f-for-functions&#34;&gt;Dial -f for functions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perl has a huge number of built-in functions, about 224 depending on the Perl version. Who can remember exactly how they all work? I know I can&amp;rsquo;t. To lookup a Perl function, use perldoc with the &lt;code&gt;-f&lt;/code&gt; switch. For instance to look up the documentation on the &lt;code&gt;rindex&lt;/code&gt; function:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-perl&#34; data-lang=&#34;perl&#34;&gt;$ perldoc &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;f rindex&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which will display:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;rindex STR,SUBSTR,POSITION
rindex STR,SUBSTR
      Works just like index() except that it returns the position of the
      last occurrence of SUBSTR in STR. If POSITION is specified,
      returns the last occurrence beginning at or before that position.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aha! This is all well and good, but what do you do if you can&amp;rsquo;t remember the function name? Well you could use &lt;a href=&#34;https://metacpan.org/pod/B::Keywords&#34;&gt;B::Keywords&lt;/a&gt;, but another way would be to check out &lt;code&gt;perlfunc&lt;/code&gt; the Perl documentation on built-in functions. To read it, with perldoc just type:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-perl&#34; data-lang=&#34;perl&#34;&gt;$ perldoc perlfunc&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;predefined-variables&#34;&gt;Predefined Variables&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with functions, Perl has a large number of predefined variables that do everything from storing the program name to tracking the state of the regex engine. They&amp;rsquo;re really useful, but often have obscure names like &lt;code&gt;$^O&lt;/code&gt; (the OS name). So if you find yourself needing to check whether you&amp;rsquo;re looking at a list separator (&lt;code&gt;$&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt;) or an output separator (&lt;code&gt;$/&lt;/code&gt;), just use perldoc with the &lt;code&gt;-v&lt;/code&gt; switch:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-perl&#34; data-lang=&#34;perl&#34;&gt;$ perldoc &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;v $/&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because some predefined variables have weird names, you may need to quote them on the command line for perldoc to work:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-perl&#34; data-lang=&#34;perl&#34;&gt;$ perldoc &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;v &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;$&amp;#34;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The predefined variables documentation is known as &lt;code&gt;perlvar&lt;/code&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s well worth a read through at least once (&lt;code&gt;perldoc perlvar&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;searching-the-documentation&#34;&gt;Searching the documentation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perl has a lot of great documentation, but it can be hard to remember the names of all of the entries. If you ever want to browse the table of contents, use &lt;code&gt;perl&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-perl&#34; data-lang=&#34;perl&#34;&gt;$ perldoc perl&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many people recommend perltoc for this, but for finding relevant entries, I think the perl entry is easier to browse than perltoc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perl also has an extensive FAQ, (another entry that&amp;rsquo;s worth a read through). It has loads of answers to common queries. As usual you can read it with &lt;code&gt;perldoc faq&lt;/code&gt;, but you can also search it using the &lt;code&gt;-q&lt;/code&gt; switch. Want to know if there are any good IDEs for Perl? (a common newbie question):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-perl&#34; data-lang=&#34;perl&#34;&gt;$ perl &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;q ide&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Is there an IDE or Windows Perl Editor?
 Perl programs are just plain text, so any editor will do.

 If you&#39;re on Unix, you already have an IDE--Unix itself. The Unix
 philosophy is the philosophy of several small tools that each do one thing
 and do it well. It&#39;s like a carpenter&#39;s toolbox.

 If you want an IDE, check the following (in alphabetical order, not order
 of preference):

 Eclipse


     The Eclipse Perl Integration Project integrates Perl editing/debugging
     with Eclipse.

 Komodo


     ActiveState&#39;s cross-platform (as of October 2004, that&#39;s Windows,
     Linux, and Solaris), multi-language IDE has Perl support, including a
     regular expression debugger and remote debugging.
...
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;finding-module-install-locations&#34;&gt;Finding module install locations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;perldoc isn&amp;rsquo;t just about documentation. If you need to find out where a module is installed, using the &lt;code&gt;-l&lt;/code&gt; switch, perldoc will return the filepath of the module:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-perl&#34; data-lang=&#34;perl&#34;&gt;$ perldoc &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;l Test::More&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you get the path, you can open it in an editor directly:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-perl&#34; data-lang=&#34;perl&#34;&gt;$ vi $&lt;span style=&#34;color:#960050;background-color:#1e0010&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;perldoc &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;l Test::More)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One trick here: some modules don&amp;rsquo;t have any POD in them, for those modules, use &lt;code&gt;-lm&lt;/code&gt; to still return the path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;read-module-source-code-in-perldoc&#34;&gt;Read module source code in perldoc&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, perldoc can also display module source code. Just use the &lt;code&gt;-m&lt;/code&gt; switch:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-perl&#34; data-lang=&#34;perl&#34;&gt;$ perldoc &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;m Test::More&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;wrap-up&#34;&gt;Wrap up&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article has covered the most common features, but perldoc has a bunch of other capabilities that you can read about at the command line with &lt;code&gt;man perldoc&lt;/code&gt;. The Perl documentation is also &lt;a href=&#34;http://perldoc.perl.org/&#34;&gt;online&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep in mind that as you get more proficient with perldoc, you&amp;rsquo;ll need the online resources less and less. Get in the habit of switching to the command line, looking up something in perldoc and flipping right back to programming - it&amp;rsquo;s a productivity win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;perldoc-cheatsheet&#34;&gt;perldoc cheatsheet&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;perldoc [option]

Module Options                               
--------------                               
         Module documentation     
-l       Module filepath          
-lm      Module filepath (alt.)   
-m       Module source


Search Options
--------------
-f     Get a built-in function definition
-v     Get a variable definition
-q      Search the faq for a keyword


Commonly Used Entries
---------------------
perl         Language overview, list of all other entries
perltoc      Table of contents
perlfunc     Built-in functions documentation
perlvar      Predefined variables documentation
perlref      References documentation
perlre       Regex documentation
faq          The Perl FAQ

Help
----
man perldoc     List of all perldoc options
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;This article was originally posted on &lt;a href=&#34;http://perltricks.com&#34;&gt;PerlTricks.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>

