<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Terminator on Perl.com - programming news, code and culture</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/terminator/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Terminator on Perl.com - programming news, code and culture</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 Feb 2016 09:29:18 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/tags/terminator/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>An introduction to Tmux</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/article/an-introduction-to-tmux/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Feb 2016 09:29:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/article/an-introduction-to-tmux/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://tmux.github.io/&#34;&gt;Tmux&lt;/a&gt; is a terminal multiplexer: it&amp;rsquo;s like a power-up for terminal programming. You can manage several terminals under a session, split terminal screens, detach and re-attach sessions and much more. If you do most of your programming at the command line, you&amp;rsquo;ll find using a terminal multiplexer invaluable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;setup&#34;&gt;Setup&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First you&amp;rsquo;ll need to install Tmux via your package manager or &lt;a href=&#34;https://tmux.github.io/&#34;&gt;download&lt;/a&gt; it. Tmux is highly configurable but the first change I&amp;rsquo;d recommend is to ssh, not Tmux. Make ssh &amp;ldquo;keep alive&amp;rdquo; for all connections by adding this to &lt;code&gt;~/.ssh/config&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;host *
   ServerAliveInterval 300
   ServerAliveCountMax 3
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the file doesn&amp;rsquo;t exist, create it. This configuration instructs your local machine for all user ssh sessions to send a server alive message every 300 seconds to keep the ssh session alive. If the local machine sends 3 unanswered messages, it will disconnect the session. You should tweak these settings to suit your needs: for instance by restricting the &lt;code&gt;host&lt;/code&gt; to specific domains you can have different settings per domain. If you have a slow or unreliable internet connection, consider changing &lt;code&gt;ServerAliveInterval&lt;/code&gt; to a lower number to send more frequent messages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have permission on the servers you use, you can update them with a similar configuration, in &lt;code&gt;/etc/ssh/sshd_config&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;ClientAliveInterval 300
ClientAliveCountMax 3
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-prefix-and-one-true-command-trade&#34;&gt;The Prefix and One True Command&amp;trade;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once Tmux is installed, start a new Tmux session from the command line:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ tmux
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Ctrl-b&lt;/code&gt; is the &lt;strong&gt;prefix&lt;/strong&gt; combination. Press the Ctrl key AND the letter b at the same time. When inside a Tmux session, the prefix is nearly always pressed before the shortcut key to trigger a command.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prefix combination is really important. Once you get the hang of the prefix combination, you can pretty much bootstrap yourself into learning Tmux with just one command. To display a list of Tmux commands, type: &lt;code&gt;Ctrl-b ?&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means press &lt;code&gt;Control&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;b&lt;/code&gt; together, release, then press &lt;code&gt;?&lt;/code&gt;. Tmux should display:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;bind-key        C-b send-prefix
bind-key        C-o rotate-window
bind-key        C-z suspend-client
bind-key      Space next-layout
bind-key          ! break-pane
bind-key          &amp;quot; split-window
bind-key          # list-buffers
bind-key          $ command-prompt -I #S &amp;quot;rename-session &#39;%%&#39;&amp;quot;
bind-key          % split-window -h
bind-key          &amp;amp; confirm-before -p &amp;quot;kill-window #W? (y/n)&amp;quot; kill-window
bind-key          &#39; command-prompt -p index &amp;quot;select-window -t &#39;:%%&#39;&amp;quot;
bind-key          ( switch-client -p
bind-key          ) switch-client -n
bind-key          , command-prompt -I #W &amp;quot;rename-window &#39;%%&#39;&amp;quot;
bind-key          - delete-buffer
bind-key          . command-prompt &amp;quot;move-window -t &#39;%%&#39;&amp;quot;
bind-key          0 select-window -t :0
bind-key          1 select-window -t :1
bind-key          2 select-window -t :2
bind-key          3 select-window -t :3
bind-key          4 select-window -t :4
bind-key          5 select-window -t :5
bind-key          6 select-window -t :6
bind-key          7 select-window -t :7
bind-key          8 select-window -t :8
bind-key          9 select-window -t :9
bind-key          : command-prompt
bind-key          ; last-pane
bind-key          = choose-buffer
bind-key          ? list-keys
bind-key          D choose-client
bind-key          L switch-client -l
bind-key          [ copy-mode
bind-key          ] paste-buffer
bind-key          c new-window
bind-key          d detach-client
bind-key          f command-prompt &amp;quot;find-window &#39;%%&#39;&amp;quot;
bind-key          i display-message
bind-key          l last-window
bind-key          n next-window
bind-key          o select-pane -t :.+
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also change the prefix combination (see the Config options section). If you do that, remember to use your prefix combination instead of &lt;code&gt;Ctrl-b&lt;/code&gt; in the examples below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;window-control&#34;&gt;Window control&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s look at a key Tmux feature: windows. They&amp;rsquo;re similar to tabs in browsers. Each one is a different terminal from where you can run different commands at the same time. To create a new window press&lt;code&gt;Ctrl-b c&lt;/code&gt;. You can cycle between windows: &lt;code&gt;Ctrl-b n&lt;/code&gt; for the next window and &lt;code&gt;Ctrl-b p&lt;/code&gt; takes you to the prior window. &lt;code&gt;Ctrl-b w&lt;/code&gt; list all windows in a session and let&amp;rsquo;s you select which one to active (using the arrow keys and enter).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you know the window number you can also jump straight to it with &lt;code&gt;Ctrl-b #&lt;/code&gt; replacing &amp;ldquo;#&amp;rdquo; with the window number. By default they begin at 0, not 1!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might be wondering what&amp;rsquo;s the benefit of using Tmux windows over tabbed terminals. First, with regular terminals if the window manager crashes, you&amp;rsquo;ll lose the terminals as well. This won&amp;rsquo;t happen with Tmux: it will keep the terminals running in the background and you can re-attach a new terminal to them at any time. Windows can also be subdivided into panes, all running pseudo-terminals. Let&amp;rsquo;s look at them now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;pane-control&#34;&gt;Pane control&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Panes are great. You can split a window horizontally, vertically and with any dimensions you like. Have you ever wanted to quickly look up a man page whilst coding? Instead of dropping back to the terminal, looking up the man page and then foregrounding your editor, just open a new vertical pane, like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/an-introduction-to-tmux/tmux-split-screen.png&#34; alt=&#34;Tmux Panes&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you can read the man page and code at the same time; you can even copy and paste between the two panes. Much more convenient!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently I was processing a huge set of data; I arranged my Tmux window with 3 panes running the data processing and 1 pane monitoring the server resources with &lt;a href=&#34;http://hisham.hm/htop/&#34;&gt;htop&lt;/a&gt;. This server is almost overloaded:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/an-introduction-to-tmux/tmux-panes.png&#34; alt=&#34;Tmux Panes&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the key pane controls:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Ctrl-b &amp;quot;      split pane horizontally
Ctrl-b %      split pane vertically
Ctrl-b o      next pane
Ctrl-b ;      prior pane
Ctrl-b ←↑→↓   jump to pane
Ctrl-b Ctrl-o swap panes
Ctrl-b space  arrange panes
Ctrl-b-←↑→↓   change pane size
Ctrl-b !      pop a pane into a new window
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The arrows &lt;code&gt;←↑→↓&lt;/code&gt; represent the arrow keys, just use one of these. For example to jump to a pane on the right, you&amp;rsquo;d press &lt;code&gt;Ctrl-b →&lt;/code&gt;. The change pane size controls are a little different. To make that work you first have to have more than one pane. Next press &lt;code&gt;Ctrl-b&lt;/code&gt; and keep the control key held down. Now you can repeatedly press an arrow key to change the pane size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;Ctrl-b !&lt;/code&gt; is one of my favorite features. It pops the current pane out of the window and moves it to its own window. This is wonderful if you find yourself doing some unrelated activity in one pane and want to re-organize your setup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;scrolling-and-copy-paste&#34;&gt;Scrolling and copy/paste&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you can master scrolling and copy/paste in Tmux, you can master anything. I won&amp;rsquo;t lie, this is the clunkiest feature. But it&amp;rsquo;s really useful. The interface is modal, so start by entering scroll mode by typing &lt;code&gt;Ctrl-b [&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pressing &lt;code&gt;esc&lt;/code&gt; will exit scroll mode. You should know you&amp;rsquo;re in scroll mode because an orange line count appears in the top-right corner of the pane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you&amp;rsquo;re in scroll mode, you can move the cursor using the arrow keys and page up and down. By default Tmux doesn&amp;rsquo;t retain much history, but you can change that (see the Config options section).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can copy and paste in scroll mode. This is useful when you have split screens as a regular highlight and copy using the mouse won&amp;rsquo;t work across vertically split panes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/an-introduction-to-tmux/tmux-copy-fail.png&#34; alt=&#34;copy fail&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To copy, position the cursor where you want to start copying. Press &lt;code&gt;Ctrl-space&lt;/code&gt; to begin highlighting the text to copy. Press &lt;code&gt;Alt-w&lt;/code&gt; to copy the highlighted text. Pressing &lt;code&gt;Ctrl-b ]&lt;/code&gt; will paste the copied text. There are ways to make copy and paste easier: Tmux has a &amp;ldquo;vim like&amp;rdquo; copy mode (see the Config options section and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://man.openbsd.org/OpenBSD-current/man1/tmux.1&#34;&gt;man&lt;/a&gt; page for details).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/an-introduction-to-tmux/tmux-copy-win.png&#34; alt=&#34;copy win&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shortcut&lt;/strong&gt; You can jump into scroll mode and page up in one fell swoop with &lt;code&gt;Ctrl-b PgUp&lt;/code&gt; (thanks to Ludovic Tolhurst for the tip).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;bonus-feature-search&#34;&gt;Bonus feature - search&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you took the time to learn scroll mode, you deserve something extra, something special. Here is your prize: you can search the Tmux buffer! Just enter scroll mode with &lt;code&gt;Ctrl-b [&lt;/code&gt; and then press &lt;code&gt;Ctrl-r&lt;/code&gt;. Type your search text and press enter. Tmux will jump to the last match it finds. You can press &lt;code&gt;n&lt;/code&gt; to jump to the next match or &lt;code&gt;Shift-n&lt;/code&gt; to jump back one match.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also &lt;code&gt;Ctrl-s&lt;/code&gt; to search down the buffer, but I hardly ever use it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;session-control&#34;&gt;Session control&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sessions are one of the most useful features of Tmux. They let you group multiple terminal processes into a single Tmux session which can be worked on (attached), put into the background (detached) and discarded as you see fit. Programmers will often have different sessions for different projects. Because Tmux operates under a client-server architecture, even if the original terminal that started Tmux dies or your desktop GUI crashes, the Tmux session will be preserved, along with all of the terminal sessions in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Detach your Tmux session with &lt;code&gt;Ctrl-b d&lt;/code&gt;. This will return you to a regular terminal prompt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To list existing Tmux sessions just use the &lt;code&gt;ls&lt;/code&gt; command:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ tmux ls
0: 1 windows (created Thu Jan 28 08:15:20 2016) [190x50] (attached)
2: 2 windows (created Thu Jan 28 09:11:59 2016) [190x50]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This shows that I have two Tmux sessions running, one of which is attached to a terminal window already. To attach to a session just use the &lt;code&gt;attach&lt;/code&gt; command at the terminal prompt:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ tmux attach
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By default Tmux attaches to the next unattached session (&amp;ldquo;2&amp;rdquo;) in this case. If I have many different sessions and want to attach to a particular one, I can specify it with &lt;code&gt;-t&lt;/code&gt; for target:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ tmux attach -t 2
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;config-options&#34;&gt;Config options&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The file &lt;code&gt;~/.tmux.conf&lt;/code&gt; is a plaintext file used by Tmux for local config. This is what mine looks like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# set scroll history to 10,000 lines
set -g history-limit 10000

# modern encoding and colors
set -g utf8 on set-window-option -g utf8 on
set -g default-terminal screen-256color

# don&#39;t use a login shell
set -g default-command /bin/bash

# unbind the prefix and bind it to Ctrl-a like screen
unbind C-b set -g prefix C-a bind C-a send-prefix
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tmux starts with a tiny scroll history, so I like to bump that up. The modern encoding and colors are there to jive with my terminal setup - they may even be the default Tmux settings by now. By default Tmux uses a login shell, so every new pane will execute &lt;code&gt;.bash_profile&lt;/code&gt;. I prefer to disable that behavior and just launch regular non-login shells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tmux has hundreds more options: many users will switch to a different shell like zsh, enable pane switching with the trackpad, display custom data in the Tmux footer (like weather info!) and so on. Copying other programmers&amp;rsquo; &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/search?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;amp;q=.tmux.conf&#34;&gt;conf files&lt;/a&gt; is a great way to learn and experiment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To reload your &lt;code&gt;.tmux.conf&lt;/code&gt; within a Tmux session, type: &lt;code&gt;Ctrl-b :&lt;/code&gt; then &lt;code&gt;source-file ~/.tmux.conf&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;tmux-resources&#34;&gt;Tmux resources&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The official Tmux &lt;a href=&#34;https://tmux.github.io/&#34;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt; is a good starting point with summary information, a changelog, downloads and a link to the extensive &lt;a href=&#34;http://man.openbsd.org/OpenBSD-current/man1/tmux.1&#34;&gt;man page&lt;/a&gt;. The Arch Linux &lt;a href=&#34;https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Tmux&#34;&gt;tmux documentation&lt;/a&gt; covers advanced features and troubleshooting tips. The book &lt;a href=&#34;https://pragprog.com/book/bhtmux/tmux&#34;&gt;tmux - Productive Mouse-Free Development&lt;/a&gt; by Pragmatic Bookshelf is thorough introduction to Tmux.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://perltricks.com/article/153/2015/2/16/Get-to-grips-with-GNU-Screen/&#34;&gt;GNU Screen&lt;/a&gt; is another terminal multiplexer program. It&amp;rsquo;s older than Tmux and a little bit crufty, but it has most of the features Tmux has. The controls for Screen and Tmux are similar enough that if you know one of them you can get by using the other. The Tmux &lt;a href=&#34;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/tmux/tmux/master/FAQ&#34;&gt;FAQ&lt;/a&gt; lists the differences between them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;This article was originally posted on &lt;a href=&#34;http://perltricks.com&#34;&gt;PerlTricks.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Get to grips with GNU Screen</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/article/153/2015/2/16/Get-to-grips-with-GNU-Screen/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Feb 2015 14:15:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/article/153/2015/2/16/Get-to-grips-with-GNU-Screen/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;GNU Screen is a terminal multiplexer, a program that manages terminal windows. It&amp;rsquo;s been around for 28 years, which makes it older than Perl 5. So if you thought Perl had some archaic conventions, you ain&amp;rsquo;t seen nothing yet. But despite it&amp;rsquo;s age Screen is a powerful tool for managing terminals; if you often find yourself using more than one terminal, you owe it to yourself to start using a multiplexer for major productivity gains. Screen is the most widely used multiplexer, another popular option is &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/tmux/tmux&#34;&gt;tmux&lt;/a&gt;, but this article is about Screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;getting-started&#34;&gt;Getting started&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start Screen by simply typing &lt;code&gt;screen&lt;/code&gt; at the command line:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-perl&#34; data-lang=&#34;perl&#34;&gt;$ screen&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All commands in Screen start with the prefix &lt;code&gt;Control + a&lt;/code&gt;. The first command to learn is the most important; how to display the commands menu! To do this type &lt;code&gt;Control + a, ?&lt;/code&gt; (that is, press Control and the &amp;ldquo;A&amp;rdquo; key, release the keys and then type question mark). If you remember this one command, you can always get yourself out of trouble, even if you forget some of the other commands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;managing-windows&#34;&gt;Managing windows&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To open a new terminal window, type &lt;code&gt;Control + a, c&lt;/code&gt;. Screen will create a new window - this is a new terminal process. To see a list of open windows, type &lt;code&gt;Control + a, &amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt;. You can press up and down to highlight the window you want to use, and press enter to open it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also cycle through windows, by pressing &lt;code&gt;Control + a, n&lt;/code&gt; to move to the next window and &lt;code&gt;Control + a, p&lt;/code&gt; to move to the previous one. Every window is assigned a number, and you can jump straight to a window with: &lt;code&gt;Control + a, #&lt;/code&gt; where the pound key is the number window to jump to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally if you want to kill a window type &lt;code&gt;Control + a, k&lt;/code&gt;. To kill all windows and exit screen the combination is: &lt;code&gt;Control + a, \&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;split-screen&#34;&gt;Split Screen&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Screen can split the terminal window into multiple windows. This is really helpful if you need to look at multiple terminals simultaneously. Any window can be split vertically or horizontally and multiple times, leading to all kinds of &lt;a href=&#34;https://encrypted.google.com/search?tbm=isch&amp;amp;q=gnu%20screen&amp;amp;tbs=imgo:1&#34;&gt;combinations&lt;/a&gt;. To vertically split the screen type: &lt;code&gt;Control + a, |&lt;/code&gt; and to horizontally split type: &lt;code&gt;Control + a, S&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To highlight the next split window, type &lt;code&gt;Control + a, tab&lt;/code&gt; (there&amp;rsquo;s also a config option to select by mouse click, more on that later). The combination &lt;code&gt;Control + a, Q&lt;/code&gt;. will quit split screen mode.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;copy-and-paste&#34;&gt;Copy and paste&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Copying and pasting with Screen isn&amp;rsquo;t super easy. So much so that I often found myself using the terminal copy and paste instead (highlight with mouse, then &lt;code&gt;Control + C&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Control + V&lt;/code&gt;). However it&amp;rsquo;s useful to know Screen&amp;rsquo;s copy and paste because terminal copy and paste just crumbles on split screen mode, and you may want to use the mouse select for something more useful anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Copy and paste is modal, so you first have to enter &amp;ldquo;copy mode&amp;rdquo;. To do that type &lt;code&gt;Control + a, [&lt;/code&gt;. Now move the cursor to the beginning of the text you want to copy. Press &lt;code&gt;space&lt;/code&gt; to mark it and use the arrow keys (or h, j, k, l) to move the cursor to the end of the text you want to copy. Pressing &lt;code&gt;space&lt;/code&gt; again will copy the highlighted text. To paste, type &lt;code&gt;Control + a, ]&lt;/code&gt;. Ew.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;scrolling&#34;&gt;Scrolling&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By default Screen prevents scrolling using the X-Window scrollbar (it also doesn&amp;rsquo;t keep much history). This can be get very annoying, so you&amp;rsquo;ll want to know how to scroll. To do so, you need to enter copy mode with &lt;code&gt;Control + a, [&lt;/code&gt;. and then press &lt;code&gt;Control + u&lt;/code&gt; to scroll up and &lt;code&gt;Control + d&lt;/code&gt; to go down. Press &lt;code&gt;escape&lt;/code&gt; to exit copy mode. And until you can remember the combinations for scrolling, you&amp;rsquo;ll find yourself piping output to &lt;code&gt;less&lt;/code&gt; more than you ever imagined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;detaching-screen-sessions&#34;&gt;Detaching Screen Sessions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Screen sessions can be put into the background just like any other terminal process. Screen will keep open any terminal processes (like ssh sessions). This is very useful - if you find yourself working with more than 5 or 6 windows, it might be easier to detach and start a new screen session than adding more windows. To detach screen, the combination is &lt;code&gt;Control + a, d&lt;/code&gt;. When you detach, screen will print the session name and return to the terminal prompt. To re-attach to a detached session just use &lt;code&gt;screen -r&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-perl&#34; data-lang=&#34;perl&#34;&gt;$ screen &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;r&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have more than one screen session, you can display all detached sessions with &lt;code&gt;-ls&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-perl&#34; data-lang=&#34;perl&#34;&gt;$ screen &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;ls
There are screens on:
    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;30549&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;pts&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;localhost   (Detached)
    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;30498&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;pts&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;localhost   (Detached)
    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;29207&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;pts&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;localhost   (Detached)
&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt; Sockets in &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;/var/&lt;/span&gt;run&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;/screen/&lt;/span&gt;S&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;sillymoose&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then just re-attach to the session you want by providing the session name as an option to &lt;code&gt;-r&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-perl&#34; data-lang=&#34;perl&#34;&gt;$ screen &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;r &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;29207&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if you&amp;rsquo;ve really got multiple Screen sessions going, it can be hard to remember what they&amp;rsquo;re all doing. So when you start Screen, use the &lt;code&gt;-S&lt;/code&gt; option to give the session a name:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-perl&#34; data-lang=&#34;perl&#34;&gt;$ screen &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;S aws_ec2&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you name all your sessions, it&amp;rsquo;s much easier to know which one to re-attach to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-perl&#34; data-lang=&#34;perl&#34;&gt;$ screen &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;ls
There are screens on:
    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;31155&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;aws_ec2   (Detached)
    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;30866&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;email_servers (Detached)
    &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;30815&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;ecommerce_app (Detached)
&lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt; Sockets in &lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;/var/&lt;/span&gt;run&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;/screen/&lt;/span&gt;S&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;sillymoose&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;

$ screen &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;r email_servers&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;customizing-screen&#34;&gt;Customizing Screen&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Screen is highly configurable which is good because you&amp;rsquo;ll probably want to change a few of the default options. The first option you should consider isn&amp;rsquo;t a Screen option at all however.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To stop your ssh sessions from timing out, add the following to your &lt;code&gt;~/.ssh/config&lt;/code&gt; file:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-perl&#34; data-lang=&#34;perl&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# dont timeout connections&lt;/span&gt;
ServerAliveInternal &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;600&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the &lt;code&gt;~/.ssh/config&lt;/code&gt; file didn&amp;rsquo;t already exist, you may have to change the permissions on the file:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-perl&#34; data-lang=&#34;perl&#34;&gt;$ chmod &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;644&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;~&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;/.ssh/co&lt;/span&gt;nfig&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This option will have ssh send a byte every 10 minutes to the remote server to keep the session alive. You may want to change the frequency depending on your needs. Now you can have multiple ssh windows within screen, detach them for hours and return and you&amp;rsquo;ll still be logged in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like many other terminal programs, screen will look for a runcom config file (&lt;code&gt;~/.screenrc&lt;/code&gt;). I like the following options:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-perl&#34; data-lang=&#34;perl&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# no welcome message&lt;/span&gt;
startup_message off

&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# keep running processes on detach&lt;/span&gt;
autodetach on

&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# start windows at 1 instead of 0&lt;/span&gt;
bind c screen &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
bind &lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;^&lt;/span&gt;c screen &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
bind &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; select &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;
screen &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# large scrollback buffer&lt;/span&gt;
defscrollback &lt;span style=&#34;color:#ae81ff&#34;&gt;5000&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# on split screen, switch window focus by clicking&lt;/span&gt;
mousetrack on

&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;# refresh screen after closing a program&lt;/span&gt;
altscreen on&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are loads more options to choose from. Screen has a huge online &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gnu.org/software/screen/manual/screen.html&#34;&gt;manual&lt;/a&gt; and it&amp;rsquo;s terminal man page is comprehensive too. Any typed command listed in the manual can be run from within screen, or added to the &lt;code&gt;~/.screenrc&lt;/code&gt; file. For instance if you don&amp;rsquo;t like Screen&amp;rsquo;s default key bindings, checkout the &lt;code&gt;bindkey&lt;/code&gt; command for overriding them, as you don&amp;rsquo;t want to be typing them for another 28 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;screen-cheatsheet&#34;&gt;Screen Cheatsheet&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# Type before other commands
Prefix: Control + a

Shortcuts menu: ?

New window:    c      Split Vertical:   |       Copy mode:     [
Close window:  k      Split Horizontal: S       Start copy:    space
Next window:   n      Focus next region: tab    Scroll up:     u
Prior window:  p      Quit split screem: Q      Scroll down:   d
Jump window #: 0-9                              End copy:      space
List windows:  &amp;quot;                                Paste:         ]
                                                End copy mode: escape

Detach: d
Quit:   \

# Terminal commands
Launch Screen:     screen
Named session:     screen -S &amp;lt;name&amp;gt;
List sessions:     screen -ls
Re-attach session: screen -r [name]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;This article was originally posted on &lt;a href=&#34;http://perltricks.com&#34;&gt;PerlTricks.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>

